Now we know how to create variables.
We can move on and use these variables in
calculations within our program.
We're going to have a look at some of the
simple arithmetic covering addition,
subtraction, division and multiplication
within our [UNKNOWN].
So first of all, let's have a look at
addition.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
It's all very simple stuff.
First of all, we'll just tidy this up.
Let's get rid of those constants.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So let's say our program needs to add two
numbers together.
Each number is stored in its own unique
variable and we want to store
the product of the two numbers in a brand
new variable that we can call result.
So first off, we'll declare a new data
variable.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we'll actually use the like statement.
We'll make it the same as [UNKNOWN]
decimal 01.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] Let's line them up.
Now as you can probably imagine,
it doesn't take much in the way of the
code to add two numbers together.
All we need to do is write result,
which is a variable we declared here
[SOUND] equals.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Because my typing is terrible I'm just
gonna
copy integer 01 plus packed decimal 01.
With a full stop at the end.
Pretty printer and everything looks good,
but we'll check it.
I managed to get the syntax correct.
So let's take a look at what this is
actually doing.
Very, very straightforward.
It's just adding integer 01 and
packed decimal 01 and putting the product
of those two into the variable results.
If we want to check, and let's add the
right
statement and we'll just write results.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Activate our program.
And, there, we can see the result, 16.5.
Let's go through this a little bit deeper.
Even though it looks super simple,
there's just a few things that we need to
go through.
And, the first one is.
For any arithmetic operations, we always
have to have the equals sign.
To the left of the actual calculation.
And the variable to hold the result is to
be the left of the equal sign.
And the calculation is executed, the two
variables to the right of the equal sign
always stay the same, and it's only the
variable to the left that will be updated.
In our case, we have a variable called
result.
If that already held a number prior to the
calculation taking place,
it would then be overridden with the new
result of the calculation.
You'll also notice, I put space in front
and behind the equals sign.
You've always got to do this.
And also between the actual arithmetic
operators as well.
Always put space in front and behind.
As your calculations become more complex
you'll start to use parenthesis.
And you must insure that you insert blank
characters before and
after the parenthesis to separate them
from your arithmetic operators.
Now when I say you've got to make sure you
insert a space before and
after, one space is the minimum.
You can, for instance, like I often do so
I can line up my code and
make it a lot more readable, you can
insert as many spaces as you want.
And it will all still work the same.
And this allows us to define our
calculations
across many lines within the ABAP editor.
[SOUND] Now as you can imagine, we're not
just
stuck to calculate in the value of
variables we can.
[SOUND] Also use individual values
in our calculation, just as shown here.
Shows an example.
So, it's just output the result.
[SOUND]
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Oops.
There we go.