[BLANK_AUDIO]
And the last one we'll try, oops.
As you can guess, is multiplication.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And there we go.
All very simple.
Now just before we move on to the topic of
conversion rules,
I'll just add in that when we talk about
arithmetic,
you also have the option of using some
other statements called ADD,
SUBTRACT, DIVIDE, and MULTIPLY.
Now the syntax for these is a little bit
different,
because the way it works, let's make that
into a comment, is we can say ADD 8 to
result.
And then 8 would contain, let's have a
look in this case,
22 plus, that's 27.5 plus 8 would be 35.5.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's do a syntax check.
Haven't used this in years, actually.
Hope I got, yeah, I got it right.
[LAUGH] Let's just test it out.
Here we go.
So we can see the result is 35.5.
So it's adding in the value of 8 to
result.
But I've gotta say you hardly ever see
this used in programs.
And why would you want to use it when you
can use really simple
calculations just like this?