As we've been creating this program,
you'll have no doubt seen
we're using various different data types
when declaring our variables.
Now, it's a programmer's responsibility to
make sure the data types you use
are compatible with each other when you
use them for calculations or
moving data to and from those objects
throughout your program.
You do not want to be performing any
calculations on variables and
numbers that do not match.
For example,
a variable defined as an integer cannot be
multiplied by a character.
The two data types are incompatible, and
as a result, the system would generate
syntax errors and a runtime error if you
try to execute the program.
Now, SEP have built in some automatic data
type conversions
from many of the standard data types that
are available within ABAP.
There are scenarios where the inbuilt ABAP
conversion rules are not appropriate and
it is important you become familiar with
the inbuilt conversion rules, and
know when to manipulate the data prior to
using them in your calculations.
So, let's take a look at the conversion
rules that currently exist.
We won't go through every one, but you'll
get a good flavor of
what the conversion rules are and how you
can use them throughout your programs.
Now, conversion rules are predefined logic
that determine
how the contents of the source field can
be entered into a target field.
If you have an integer field containing
the value of one, and try to insert that
value into a character string, the built
in conversion rules will determine exactly
how this should be done without throwing
any syntax errors or runtime errors.
Let's have a look at some examples.
So, let's suppose we add a variable called
num1.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
A type packed decimal.
And we add the results.
Oops, help if I could code properly, hm.
We add the result of type integer.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
If we had a calculation where a packed
decimal number was
moved into an integer field, the inbuilt
conversion
rules would round the decimal places of
num1, up or
down, and insert the contents into the
result one field.
Blimey, you can see I wasn't paying
attention there.
One second, there we go.
So, let's fill this out a little bit more.
So, let's say we had a value of 3.33.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay, so what we will get here is result
one,
with result in a value of three.
Probably best if we output this to our
screen.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's see what we come out with.
[SOUND] There we go.
We end up with a value of three.
And, that's because the inbuilt conversion
rules rounded the number down.
If we add the value of 5.55, and this
time,
result will contain the value 6 because
the rounding will go up.
[SOUND] So, you can see,
automatic conversion rules are being
applied.
As you work with different data types
within your program,
many different conversion rules will be
applied automatically, and as I've stated
before, it's up to you as the programmer
to understand these conversion rules,
understand the data types you are using
within your program to ensure no run time
errors will occur.