Now I want to step back just a little bit
and discuss the division operator.
Earlier we saw the format of a simple
division calculation.
Now I'm sure you remember back to your old
school days,
that when you started to learn how to
divide one number by another number,
you were first taught about the remainder
values.
In our ABAP, we have three different ways
we can divide numbers together.
And this allows us to concentrate on the
remainder of the actual integer division,
and the standard division result with
decimal places.
So let's just go through these three so
that you become familiar with them when
you need to use them in your own program.
So back in the code.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's add another little separator.
And we'll generate some division
calculations.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Haven't used result 2 before, I don't
think, no.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So here's the first calculation.
I'll just generate
the outputs.
Okay.
I'll tell you what I'll do as well.
Let's just line these up so they will be
easier to read.
Oops [NOISE].
So we define three variables, num1, num2,
and result2.
Num1 has two decimal places with a value
of 5.45.
Num2 has two decimal places with a value
of 1.48.
And result2, which will be the product of
our calculation,
just does two decimal places with no value
defined, and I made a little error there.
There we go.
So our result will be num 1 divided by num
2.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hm, I've got an error somewhere, let's
have a quick look.
VALUE expected, not VALUES.
Oops.
Looks like I went all plural on it.
Here we go.
It's useful how the syntax checker
does actually identify what the errors are
sometimes.
You can see it's looking for
VALUE instead of VALUES.
Oh, looks like I've already used NUM1 in
the program.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Have I used num1?
Oh, there it is.
Look, used it up there.
Let's change it, we'll use numa and numb.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay, everything looks good.
I'll activate the program, and
when we execute it, can see a value of
zero.
Oh, silly me.
Look at that.
I'm outputting the wrong result.
Result two, that's what we want.
[SOUND] There we go.
So the result is 3.68.
So that's the standard division.
Nothing too spectacular there.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[NOISE] Now we'll have a look
at the integer division.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So we'll use the same values, and
obviously I've renamed the actual variable
names.
Now for the integer division, instead of
using the normal divide symbol, we
actually use DIV.
So what's integer division?
Well as a reminder, what it will do, it
will divide one number by the other, but
the result we'll get is just going to be
the integer value.
So this means we will not get the decimal
places.
Let's activate our program, and of course
I've got syntax errors.
Oh, silly me.
Copy and pasted all wrong.
There we go.
[SOUND] Now we'll execute the program.
[SOUND] I've done it again, haven't I?
Now outputting the wrong result.
[LAUGH] Here we go.
Oops.
[NOISE].
Now when we execute, we can see we're
getting a result of 3.
We're just getting the integer,
the full number, not the decimal places.
So now, as you can probably guess,
the last example we want to look at is the
remainder.
[NOISE]
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now i'm gonna make sure I get no
syntax errors this time.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[NOISE]
Okay.
Now with the remainder division type, we
want to use MOD.
So the result we get here is going to be
the large
number divided by the small, but we will
only be shown the remainder
value of what can not be divided directly
into num E.
I'm sure you know what I mean.
I might make it sound more complicated
than it is [LAUGH].
Let's execute the program and see.
Oh, one thing.
Look at that.
I nearly have that syntax error.
Just change that.
[SOUND] And we'll try our program.
Here we go.
So now we've got a remainder of 1.01,
which hopefully, by my calculations,
should be correct.
I should bring in the calculator,
5.45 divided by 3.48 3.6824.
That means 3 times 1.48 gives us a value
of 4.4.
So if we take 4.4 from the 5.45,
that gives us 1.01.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Which is the result we've got there.