We're now going to discuss modularizing
our programs.
And if you don't know already, it's really
good practice to try and
keep your programs as simple to read and
self contained as possible.
And what I mean is, try and split up any
large complicated tasks.
Into much smaller, simpler tasks.
By placing each task into its own separate
individual module that you
as a developer are able to concentrate on
without any other distractions.
Modularizing your code lets you focus on
that one single task and not get confused
by the big picture of a much larger
development that you may be working on.
By working on individual tasks, it makes
it much easier to develop and
debug your program.
It develop individual modules of code that
once tested incomplete,
you don't have to worry about again,
leaving you free to concentrate on any
other issues that may crop
up in other areas of your coding project
that you have to solve.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Creating individual source code modules
helps you avoid repeatedly writing
the same set of statement again and again.
And this in turn makes your programs
easier to read and
understand both by you and by others.
And a big benefit is when it comes to
support.
By creating these small modules of code,
anybody having to support your programs in
the future, maybe even you.
You'll find it much easier to read and
understand what's going on.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And when you first begin to design your
program,
it's important you concentrate on the
design.
Do not start coding straightaway.
You need to map out your solution maybe
use some pseudo-code or
maybe flow charts, whatever you prefer.
Only when your design makes sense,
should you then start turning your
solution into ABAP code.
Making sure,
you design your program first really helps
when it comes to modularizing your program
because you can see how you can split your
program up into separate pieces.
Which will allow you then, to focus on the
development of one piece at a time.
Now, if you recall, when we looked at
design in selection strings,
we used modularization techniques.
By making use of processing blocks such as
the start of selection block.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Maturization isn't just limited to using
processing blocks in our program.
The SAP system itself allows us to use a
number of techniques for
breaking our program open Into smaller,
more manageable pieces of code.
And throughout this section, we're gonna
take a look at just how we
can modularize our programs using the
various tools SAP provides.
[BLANK_AUDIO]