What we're going to concentrate on first,
is something called Source Code Modulars.
Now when we talk about modularizing our
program, all we mean
is we are gonna take a sequence of above
statements in our program, and
place them in a separate module.
Then in our normal ABAP program, we just
call this module.
Let's get straight down to the coding, and
have a look at how we can modularize
some of the code, we've used in previous
examples.
Here we have one of the previous examples,
and
I've modified it just a tiny bit, just to
tidy it up.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And if we go through it, you'll get the
you'll get the main gist.
And then we can start modularizing it.
So first of all at the top, of our table
statement we declare some types and some
data
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then we have our ABAP logic to
actually do something,
which is an array fetch, an individual
loop, clear statement,
another loop where we modify an entry in
the table.
Do an insert and then a couple of read
statements.
First of all, we are going to look at
using what is called Include Programs.
Now Include Programs, are made available
globally within an SAP system,
and their sole purpose is just for
modularizing code.
They are very simple to define, and accept
no parameters.
So first of all, just under the report
statements at the very top of our program,
let's fill in the statement to declare an
Include.
All we need to do is type, Include, and
then we just define the name.
So for this example,
let's do Z_Employee_Definitions,
with a full stop at the end.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Looks pretty simple, doesn't it?
So what we're telling the program here,
is to include our Include Program that
we've just named.
Into our main program.
And you probably worked out, that we
haven't actually created this include yet.
So, let's go ahead and do it.
You have two ways of creating an Include
File.
The first one, I open up a new session and
bring up SE38 again.
You can key in your include name, but I'm
not going to do it here,
I'll just Z example.
But instead of saying Source Code, and you
create your program,
you're going to create Program Attributes.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So here we just give it a title.
When we come down to type, instead of
choosing executable program,
we will choose, Include Program.
And then fill out the rest as we normally
would.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now the second method, is something I'm
sure you're familiar with already.
Oops, I'm jumping the gun.
[LAUGH] And that's by using Forward
Navigation.
If you remember, we used Forward
Navigation a lot when we created
Fields in our database table, and
we've used it within the ABAP Editor to go
check out field definitions and so on.
But we can do the same thing, to create
additional files within the ABAP Editor.
So all you need to do, is once you type
the include, just give it a double click,
and we get the pop up box saying Your
Include Does Not Exist.
Do you want to create it?
And we say Yes.
Assign it to the Local Development Class.
And that's it, we've created it, and
it gives us a blank program where we can
put our code.
I'm sure you'll agree Forward Navigation
is a lot more efficient.
Now from here, just to go back and, and
show you just that it's the same as
creating it through the SE-38,
we use the Go To menu, and have a look at
the program attributes.
We choose Yes to save.
You can see it's exactly the same screen.
It's chose the Include Program, it's a
test,
it's assigned to basis, and there's our
development class.
Now remember, this Include File, or
Program,
is a separate file on the SAP system, and
can be included in any other program.
So you have to treat it as a separate
program.
And you'll see that it's got it's own
check, it needs activating, and so on.
So, let's activate this right now.
Even though it's got nothing in, it should
activate.
And we get the pop-up box, asking us what
do we want to activate.
It shows a report program, and it's
highlighted our employee
definition include already, so we just
give it a green tick.
And now it's Active.
Now, if we step back.
Whenever we activate this program, our
main one.
It will automatically check to make sure
our include
program has already been activated.
And if it has, this one should activate
just fine.
So Include Programs, are really easy to
create and they help us
in our development by taking away some of
the noise from our main program.
And provide us with the ability to reuse
our code, throughout an SAP system.
So this is great.
We create that Include,
but you're probably thinking well, we've
put no code in it, and you're quite right.
So what we're gonna do, I'm gonna take
some of this code that we have here.
Oops, wrong key.
I'm gonna take this.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
I'll comment it out.
Go to our Include.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We'll choose Yes, to save our changes.
Click Change.
Now all we need to do, is paste our code
into our Include.
Now click Save.
Now, on purpose, I'm not going to activate
it here.
We'll, step back.
Now, I'll just show you to actually use
this code now.
We need to activate our main program.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And when we do it, we receive this message
saying we have
Syntax Errors, so we need to look at
those.
And it's telling us the LINE01_TYP is
unknown.
And this is because our Include has not
been activated.
The system doesn't have an active version
of that code,
that our main program can reference.
So to activate your program, you can
either go to your Include and
activate it or.
When activating your main program select
your Include as well.
And that way its assured that everything
will be active, and
all the data objects in this example get
referenced appropriately.
Now also, if we step back to this Include,
and
we'll make a change, we'll, we'll add an
error in here.
Let's just Add letter M for example.
We'll step back.
Now our main program is active at the
moment, and
that's only because it's using the active
version of our Include.
If we were to do a code check again,
you'll see that we got
this error message cropping open, telling
us our Include Program contains an error.
Now this seems fairly obvious, but what I
want to point out here.
Is when we do syntax checks in our main
program, it will also carry out that
syntax check, on the inactive version of
your include, so they work in tandem.
So let's go back in.
We'll change this, get rid of this error.
And then, everything's back.
So that's it, that's a very small example
of an Include Program, but
it shows you we've only put four or five
lines of text in the Include.
You could put 200, 300 lines of code into
that Include File which in effect helps
you encapsulate certain elements of your
program, pop them away in a separate file.
So, you don't have to worry about them,
and
you'll see this type of thing being used
quite often for both code
you know logic, and for data declaration
parts of a program.
Quite often people will create and
Include, put all the data and type
statements in the Include.
And then just type the logic for the code
in the main program.
And that way,
all the data declaration pieces can be
used in other programs as well.