Now, let's focus on procedures.
Now, for those new to ABAP,
there are a couple of techniques for
modularizing code that you
should really concentrate on.
And that's what we're gonna cover here.
When we want to split our
programs into separate modules,
we can use what are called procedures.
And, procedures are processing blocks
that we call from our main ABAP program.
And, procedures come in
the form of subroutines or
subprograms and function modules.
We use subroutines mainly for
local marginalization of our code.
And what I mean is, a small modular
unit of code that is self-contained,
that is called from the program
in which they are defined.
So, it's just like grouping together,
let's say 20 lines of code.
Wrapping it up into a subprogram and
just moving it to the end of your program.
You know, right down at the bottom.
Still in the same file, but just moved
away in its own little container.
So, we can use these subroutines to
write functions that we use many
times within our programs.
And at the same time,
any ABAP program can include subroutines.
Now, function modules,
they work a bit different.
They allow us to create modular
blocks of code that are held separate
to our ABAP program, and
they can be called from any other program.
So, subroutines are local
to our own program.
Function modules are global, and
can be called from any program.
You will see both sets of modularization
techniques used throughout an SAP system,
but by far the most used,
in my eyes at least, are function modules.
And an SAP system is packed
with function modules.
They encapsulate all the processing
logic used within the business system.
And SAP have made sure that
it can be reused both by
their own development teams and
by SAP customers.
Now, when we took a look
at include programs,
I mentioned an include program
cannot accept any parameters.
Procedures are different,
because they have an interface for
transferring data from our calling
program to the procedure itself.
So, because we can pass
data into a procedure,
it also means we can define data
definitions within the procedure
itself that are only
available to that procedure.
So, enough talking.
Let's have a look at how
we create subroutines and
see some of this in action.