One of the great benefits of using
subroutines is that it helps us
modularize our program code inside our
actual program.
It helps give our program structure.
So what we're gonna do right now is have a
look at how we can create
these subroutines.
Now there are a few methods but what I'm
going to show you
is by far the easiest and that's using
forward navigation.
And what we're going to do is
pop this one select statement into a sub
routine all by itself.
So I'm just going to copy it to the
clipboard, and I'll comment it out just so
we don't lose it, and then I'm going to
use a statement called perform.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now, the perform statement is what is used
to perform a sub-routine.
And all I need to do in its simplest form
is say perform and
then create a subroutine name.
You just make one up that represents the
type of function we want to do.
So, in this case, we're going to fill
itab02 with some data,
so i say itab underscore 02, actually
there is no underscore there,
itab02 underscore fill, full stop and
that's it.
Now, of course all we've done is type in
the code,
we haven't created it yet, so we'll use
forward navigation.
So I will double click.
And it says the sub-routine does not
exist, do you want to create it?
I'll chose yes.
And then it gives us an option of saying,
well where do you want to create it?
Now, we have the option of, we could
include it in the include that we created
but, you know, the include, maybe we just
want to keep that for data definition.
So, we won't choose that one.
He gives us the choice of creating a brand
new include.
And it's given it its own name which we
can change.
But I don't want to do that.
All I want to do is create this include in
the main body of our program.
So I'm gonna choose this one.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] Click the middle button.
And then what the system does,
it scrolls right to the bottom of the
screen and creates a form.
It gives us some comments here.
Then it allows us to enter whatever code
we want, inside the form.
So what we will do is because we have our
code copied to the clipboard,
I will just paste it in.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And that's it.
This code now belongs in its own
subrooting that we've included at
the bottom of our program.
So let's do a syntax check.
[SOUND] Everything is good and we can
activate.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] So, now, it's active and we know,
everything is good.
Let's just review it one more time.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We created a performance statement and
we're saying, perform this sub-routing.
Now, use forward navigation to jump to it.
[SOUND] And then the subroutine says,
select all the records
from that employee into the corresponding
fields of Table itab02.
So, the system will perform any code we
put inside the form endform structure,
and then once the system encounters the
endform statement processing will
be returned to the next statement under
our original perform statement.
So the next statement will be this loop
statement.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Processing will continue down to the
bottom of the report, but
it will terminate.
And please note, I'm considering this the
bottom of the report.
This is a sub-routine.
The system will not run through and
perform this at the end.
It knows this is a sub-routine and
[UNKNOWN] as being part of the program at
the very bottom.
It's a separate sub-routine in its own
right.
[BLANK_AUDIO]