Now there are some other things to
consider here.
Up to now, we have worked with global
variables only.
And what I mean is, all the variables we
have used
have been declared in the header of our
program and in our case here
as well as being declared in the header,
we've also declared them in the include.
So going back down to our form, this will
tell you
that your form can access what are
considered global variables.
It can access all the variables.
So in this case, we are changing the
contents of a global variable, or
a global internal table itab02.
Now, what we haven't discussed is the use
of
variables defined exclusively within our
subroutine.
Which we will class as a local variable.
Local variables can only be accessed
within the subroutine where they are
declared.
Once the system finishes processing code
within our subroutine and
control passes back to the main body of
our program,
all the local variables can no longer be
referenced.
Now some of the benefits of using local
variables
are that the variables only have to be
available in this routine,
so there's no point making them available
outside.
So by declaring them inside the
subroutine, we save a little bit
of memory usage, and because we are trying
to modularize our code,
by declaring local variables and using
local variables, we don't have
to worry about the variables being
declared in the main body of our program.
You know, everything is self contained.
Now I mentioned a little while ago, that
subroutines have an interface and
we can use local variables in our
subroutine to be used in the interface,
and we can give them any name we want, and
at the same time,
the calling program, so in our case the
main body.
That can use its own variable as well.
It doesn't have to use the same name that
we defined in the subroutine.
So to declare a variable in our
subroutine, there's no magic.
You already know the code.
All we do is make sure we are inside the
subroutine and we just start coding.
So we would use the data statement.
Let's say employee if I can spell.
Now, let's give it a different name.
Z employee.
Z, E-M-P-L.
How's that?
And we can say, it is like our z employees
table.
The fields, surname.
So here we have just defined a local data
variable within the form.
And it can only be referenced from the
code we place inside the form,
which we don't have much of just yet.
[LAUGH]
Now I mentioned we can declare
variables to be used in the interface of
our form.
And when we do that, we're telling the
system we're going to transfer
data throughout the subroutine data
interface.
So let's have a look at the code and see
how we do it.
So what I'm gonna do is go back to the top
of our program,
well, scroll down, hm, and we'll do
another perform statement.
So I'm gonna say perform itab 02 fill, now
let's say, again.
But this time, I'm going
to say using z field 1,
and z field 2.
So what are these z fields?
Well they can be anything at all.
So let's say up here, we have another data
statement.
We will say z field 1.
We will say like z employees.
Let's say surname this time.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And z field 2, we can say line forename.
Let's just do a syntax check, make sure we
got no errors.
And we do.
Let's have a look.
Oh, of course.
[LAUGH] I haven't created the subroutine
yet.
Let me just comment this out.
There we go.
Okay, everything is good.
So we'll put the code back in.
And now we will use forward navigation to
create this brand new form.
Says, do you want to create it?
I'll choose Yes.
And we'll say pop it in our main program.
And we're down at the bottom.
Now, add a few spaces.
Now notice how this differs.
Because we declared this perform statement
and
added the USING, now the two fields.
Our form was generated and included two
fields that will be used in the interface.
So this is one of the benefits of using
forward navigation.
You don't have to think too hard about the
actual syntax you need to use to
create a form.
Cuz double clicking using full navigation,
it creates the syntax for you.
But what I would say is, rename the fields
so that they are easier to understand.
They represent what you're passing
through.
So in our case, I'm gonna say z surname.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now I'm gonna rename this to z forename.
Now, something else to note is, the form
here is declared in two fields
that will be used in the interface of the
form, but notice there's no data type.
And they were taken from our perform
statement.
So, the fields used in our form
are declared exactly the same as those
declared in the main body of the program.
When our program is executed and
processing reaches the perform statements,
the contents of z field 1 and z field 2
will be copied in
to our P Z surname and P Z forename within
the form.
Now one thing to bear in mind, is if we
change the contents of our local
fields that have been declared in the form
header, so these two,
you will also be changing the values of
the fields
that were passed into the form by our
perform statement.
So let's add a line of code to see how
well this works,
and then we'll debug the code.
So in this form, I'm gonna say P,
here's that surname, no, actually,
what I'll do is write p_zsurname, then a
new line.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now do the same for forename.
Then I'm going to change the contents of
surname.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And that's it.
Now higher up in our program, where we
have the perform statement,
I'm just gonna make sure we're gonna pass
in some values,
so I will say Z field1 is equal to
ANDREWS.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
That's it, z field2 is equal to SUSAN.
So when the perform statement is executed,
these values will be passed through to the
form subroutine.
So let's check our code.
We have a missing full stop?
Of course we do.
Okay.
And we'll activate.
And then I will add a break point to the
first perform.
And then let's test it out.
So the first statement, it says perform
itab02 fill.
So let's step into this.
You can see it jumped down to the form.
Let's have a look at itab02, it's initial
at the moment.
Executes the statement, fills the table,
we've reached the end form.
Now processing passes back to the top of
that program.
We fill z field 1 and z field 2.
And then we perform our second subroutine.
I tab 02, fill again.
And we're parsing in these two fields.
So, let's move these up a little bit,
[SOUND] and
here, I'm gonna bring in z pname, and z
forname.
So here you can see the values
of z field 1 and z field 2 were
passed into the interface.
Oh sorry, were used in the interface so
that the local variables p_z surname and
p_z forename were filled with those
interface values.
We then have two write statements.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Which we can see on the screen.
And then, we're going to update z surname,
or p_z surname.
And see what happened?
Because the field is used in the
interface, our global variable,
z field 1 was also updated at the same
time.
So, this is a real important thing to keep
in mind when you're using fields in
the interface, and you're using the using
edition.
Any fields used in this declaration will
be changed as well.
So, I zoom through, well, we'll step
through.
Once that form is filled, then it
continues with the rest of the program,
which I can't remember really what it
does.
I guess it's doing a loop.
Better stick a break point here, so we can
zoom through this.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Zoom through that.
Simple describe.
And then the program crashed.
Let's have a look.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And yeah, there we go, there's the
problem.
We have this clear statement, so
the internal tables are actually empty at
the time we try to insert a record.
So here we should have some logic to say
If line count.
Let's add that.
If line count is greater than 0, perform
our insert statement.
And actually,
let's include.
Al this in this if statement.
Looks good.
So now, when we got down to the the insert
statements, right now,
it shouldn't do anything, because we have
this clear.
But if this was taken out, than the if
statement would be true.
Let's run it again.
I'll press the F6 key to execute this
first form fill.
F6 again.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Stick a breakpoint there.
So we go through that loop.
Cleared out the work area, and internal
table.
So now this loop should actually now
execute.
There we go.
Describe line count.
If it's greater than 0, perform the
insert.
If not, and the program's finished.
So a little detour into debugging my
error.
Their all examples are good examples.
But that's it.
That gives you a good
flavor of how to use sub-routines within
your program.
Now we're not going to subroutines just
yet.
We're going to look at some of the other
additions, and
how we can pass more than just fields
through the interface.