Subroutines are not only limited to
passing individual fields.
You can also pass internal tables as well
as a combination of individual fields and
tables.
Just remember you've always got to get the
sequence of fields correct when you're
passing fields and internal tables from
the main program to your form.
Because it's the sequence of the fields
when you create your perform statement
that determine which field is passed to
the interface variable of your form.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So let's have a look how we can do this.
So what I'm going to do is create a brand
new form.
[SOUND]
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now I'll say, let's, let's call this
itab02 write.
Why don't we go and write out the contents
of itab02?
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And instead of having the using addition,
what we do is include tables followed by
the table we want to pass through.
So in this case it's going to be itab02.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So we'll save our program
And then let's create our form by using
forward navigation.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] We select the "create a form" in
our program itself.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And it gets created at the bottom.
I'm just going to adjust a few things
here.
[SOUND] This code here is not actually
needed, so
we can remove that, and we'll just focus
on the basic
form of how it's generated, our
subroutine.
So as you can see, it looks fairly simple.
But there's a fundamental change that's
gone on here.
We have replaced the Using edition with
the Tables edition.
So now when the program is executed, the
perform statement ensures the contents of
our internal table that transferred to the
sub-routine installed
in the internal table Pitab02.
Once processing reaches the end of the
form, the contents of the local internal
table are then passed back to our global
internal table.
And just know this is for a table without
a header line.
If we are using the older techniques of
passing tables with header lines and
this perform statement structure that
we've just declared
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Up here, would only pass the headline of
the internal table to the sub-routine.
And that's not what we want.
To be able to pass the whole table
contents when
using an internal table with a header
line, you need to use square brackets.
So the Performs statement would look like
this.
Don't forget, I don't want you to be
coding this way.
So we always want to use work headers and
internal tables without header lines.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So let's go back down to our form.
And let's discuss the internal table
that's created for
us when the form was generated.
Now when an internal table is passed into
this subroutine, this local
internal table is actually always declared
with a header on.
And we can see this if we debug our
program.
So let's add some code.
So we'll start with creating a data
statement first.
And we'll declare temporary field, and
don't forget we we
already have our work, well we have our
line type already declared.
So I'm just creating a work edit here, the
same as the line time for
our internal table.
Which, stands to type wrong, so I think
it's this one.
And then we can do a loop statement.
Put P underscore itab02
into [SOUND] wa_tmp.
[SOUND] And we can write wa_tmp surname
to the screen, end the loop.
[SOUND] Let's pretty it up and do a check.
Everything looks good.
So now let's stick a break point in here.
[SOUND] That's right.
We need to activate, of course.
And do a break point.
[SOUND] And we'll test our code.
So now we have jumped straight into the
form.
[SOUND] We'll have a look at our itab02
table.
You can see it's got five records in and
we can see it's the newer style,
internal table, because we've got no
header record.
[SOUND] And if we have a look at this p
table.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] You can see here we got the hat
sign and
you can see we have a header record.
It's the old style.
But being good coders, what we've done
we've made sure we've used a brand
new work area when we're looping through
our local copy of the internal table.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So i'll just execute this as the output
[SOUND]
[BLANK_AUDIO]