Now let's take a look at how we can use a
combination of fields and
tables to be passed into a subroutine at
the same time.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] So let's go to the top of our
program.
We'll create another perform statement.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We'll call this perform iTab02_multi.
And here we can leave the table statement
in with our internal table.
But then we'll add in using, and we can
use as our
z_field1 and z_field2.
[SOUND] So you can see this is a
combination of the first two perform
statements all combined into one to allow
us to use a mix of fields and tables.
So let's generate this form.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] Here we go.
And you can see the form has been defined.
We have the table statement, and then we
have the using statement for the fields.
Now as I mentioned before, if you're
manually creating your, perform
statements, make sure you get the sequence
of fields correct, that you defined.
So, for example, if we had this, you know,
mixed around,
zed field two going to, zed field two then
zed field one.
Things will get mixed up, and we will
be putting zed field two into this local
variable, and zed field one into this one.
So you can see how it could create some
confusion.
So just keep an eye out on that.
[BLANK_AUDIO]