Subroutines were initially designed for
modularizing and
structuring your programs.
But they can be extended so that they can
be called externally from other programs.
If you're goal is to make a function
available throughout your SAP system,
you should really use function modules,
which we will come onto very soon.
But let's take a look at how we can create
external subroutines and how it all works.
So just like with any local subrooting
when the system completes executing
an external subrooting, control is passed
back to your calling program.
There are two ways in which you can call a
subrooting of and external program.
And I'll say right now try to always use
the first form, I am going to show you.
There is a very big reason for this.
And that's when you come on to learning
about ABAP objects if that's
what you choose to do, you have to use
this first form.
Also in this first form, we can actually
use variables to identify the program that
contains our subroutine, instead of hard
coding the full name throughout our code.
So let's look at an example.
I'll create some blank space here so I can
start coding.
Let's say we want to call a subroutine
called sub one.
Of a program called zedemployee_hire.
You would write the code as follows.
You start with a perform statement.
And we would specify our subroutine name.
So in this case it's sub-underscore one.
And then we would specify in program and
then the program name.
Said employee_hire.
And then as before in some of the other
perform statements we can
pass [SOUND] certain variables by using
the, using edition.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And finish with a full stop.
So that would mean we would have to have
program called zed employee_hire,
already existing with the subrouting
already in it, and
we're just passing across these fields.
And the difference between the standard
perform
is that we are specifically specifying the
program where the subroutine exists.
Now I said there were two methods of
calling a subroutine in
an external program.
And the other way of doing it is by using
brackets.
And you will see in this example it's very
similar.
But you will not be able to use this form
in the context of ABAP objects.
But anyway, it goes like this.
[SOUND] So you'd have to perform
subroutine 1 and
then we specify the table, sorry,
we specify the program by placing it
inside brackets.
And we can pass tables just as we've done
before.
[NOISE] And continue with the using
addition for the individual fields.
So, there are two methods of calling
external subroutines, but
I please advise you don't use this.
I'm just showing you it for completeness
and so
that you will understand some ABAP code
that you might see in SAP systems.
I've got to say, I don't see this being
used an awful lot at all.
Nearly all the forms of subrouting that
you will see are all contained
within the main body of programs
themselves.
Very rarely do you see subroutines being
called from other programs.
And, like I say, the best thing to do when
you need to do this is
to create function modules, which we are
going to come onto next.