Function modules make up a major part of
an SAP system.
Because for years SAP have modularized
their code using function modules to allow
for code reuse, both by themselves, their
own developers, and by their customers.
Now function modules are just specific
procedures that defined
within function groups and can be called
from any other ABAP program.
The function group acts like a container
for
all the function modules that logically
belong together.
For example, take all the function modules
for your HR payroll system.
Group them together into a function group.
Maybe there's a bunch of function modules
dealing with cost center reporting.
Well they can also be grouped together in
function module groups.
SAP systems literally have thousands upon
thousands of function modules
that are available for you to use in your
programs.
So there is no need to re-invent the wheel
all the time,
have a search around your SAP system.
To see if function modules already exist,
I've performed a function
you need in your program before having to
create it yourself.
Let's concentrate on how we can create
function groups and function modules.
And to do this, we're going to take a look
at the function build up.
So I'm going to step out of the ABAP
editor,
[SOUND] and go back to the main menu is
SAP.
Now way at the start this course,
I mentioned that the function builder can
be found under tools,
ABAP workbench, developments, and you'll
see it here.
Once you get used to the transactions,
you'll also be able to call it up using
transaction SE37.
[SOUND] For our example exercise we're
going to
write a program that uses an existing
function module.
But before we get onto that, we'll take a
look at the function module we're
going to use and explain how it's put
together.
Which will then allow us to discuss how we
can use it in our program.