Now, instead of typing in the function
module name, I'm just going to put part of
the name in and use wildcard characters to
do a search for the function module.
Just to help demonstrate really how many
function modules there are and
how you would go about searching out
function modules yourself.
So what I'm going to do is key in an
asterisk and
then key in the word amount followed by
another asterisk and then press F4.
Now this is showing me in this system,
I do have some filters set but there are
12 results that have come back.
And what I specifically want to show here
is we get the function module which is in
blue.
But then we get the function group which
is above it.
And we can see there are various function
modules
within our search that belong to the same
function group.
So let's say we, we don't know the exact
function module we want, but
we like the look of, say, these here.
There's four here.
They're in this ISOC group.
Now maybe there are more function modules
in this group, but
just don't have the word amount in them.
So what we can do is close this window.
And we'll go to transaction SE80.
Now, SE80, I mentioned before is the
object navigator.
And you'll find that you will use SE80 a
lot more than SE38.
But we've been using SE38, just to keep
focused on ABAP programming itself.
SE80 let's you do the ABAP programming,
you know, the ABAP editor, but
it also lets you go into function modules
and
all other development objects within an
SAP system.
So by coming to this drop down,
you can see that we can look up all sorts
of objects.
We can bring up programs.
If I double click, we'll see the program
over here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Packages, Function Groups, all sorts of
things.
Classes and Interfaces when you go on to
ABAP objects.
Business server pages and so on.
And depending how you have this figured,
that will determine what comes up in your
drop-down.
So I want to go back to Function Groups.
And we're going to key in ISOC,
which was the function group of those four
function
modules that had the word amount in there
that we just previously looked at.
So I'll key it in, press enter, and
then you see the various objects that
belong to this function group.
And the one we're interested in is
function modules, and as you can see
these are the four function modules that
turned up in our search, but
in actual fact, there are a whole bunch of
function modules that belong
to this function group that may be of some
interest.
And all we need to do to have a look to
see if these are what we want,
is double click and we will get to see the
code on the right hand side.
And just like any normal program, we can
test out the function module.
Now I'm gonna close this window.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And come back to our previous session.
Now the one we're going to work with is
actually called spell amount.
It's a very simple function module.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
But it includes everything we want to see
when trying to work out how function
modules work.
So we'll select spell amount, and then
choose display.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And what I'm gonna do now, is go along
each of these tabs, and
explain what they mean, and what's inside,
and how we use them with function modules.
So first of all, we have the function
module attributes.
Here you can see we have the function
group that this function module belongs
to, and we have some text to describe the
function module and group.
And we have various options further down.
Processing type defines the actual type of
function module.
This one is defined as normal but
we can have remote enabled which means it
can get triggered from an external system.
And then the update module, you can see.
This is set to start immediate,
and we have some various other options,
such as start delayed.
And then just basic information about when
the function module was created.
Let's move on to the import tab.
Now, this lists the individual fields we
will use for our data interface for
data we pass into the function module.
So, if we look at this from a function
module perspective, it's going to be
importing information that it can use
during the processing of its code.
And in this case, we got four fields, an
amount,
a currency, a filler and a language.
And we have some text on the right hand
side to give some information about
what the actual field is.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we have a couple of check boxes.
Hm, made them wide enough.
The first one is optional.
That means with this function module,
all of the fields that get imported,
they're all optional fields.
We don't have to fill them in.
When we call this function module from our
program, more often than not,
you will get some mandatory fields.
But this one, every field is optional.
And then we have pass by value.
Which means it's going to pass the actual
value into the function module.
Let's move onto the export tab.
Now once the function module does its
work, the fields
defined in the export tab are what get
sent back to our calling program.
So again, from a function module
perspective,
it exports this information out to whoever
called it.
Then we have a changing tab.
And as you might guess,
this just lists fields that would be
changed by the function module.
That is, we can identify fields that we
send into the function module,
the function module may then change the
values, and
these fields are then returned back to our
calling program.
So where the field's on the import tab,
the functional module only receives in.
The export, the functional module only
sends them back out to whoever called.
The changing, it receives data in, changes
it and then sends it back out.
So it's a combination of the two, really.
Then we have tables.
And just like when we looked at
subroutines,
we're not restricted to just passing in
individual fields.
We can pass in internal tables as well.
And this is where internal tables would be
set up.
Now the exceptions tab.
Every function module has the ability to
pass back exception information
to indicate if the function module was
executed successfully or not.
And we're not just limited to finding out
if it was successful.
But we can also determine specific error
messages.
So we could have a whole list of
exceptions here.
And as you can see with this function
module, we have not NOT_FOUND,
we have TOO_LARGE, and we could have a
whole host of other messages that get
passed back to our program,
to help us determine why the function
module didn't execute as we wanted it to.
These exceptions are not fixed.
Every function module defines its own
exceptions.
It's just like passing messages back to
the calling program
just to indicate if worked, or not.
And, if it didn't, why didn't it work?
So that the calling program can then use
its own logic to
determine what it should do next.
And the last tab is the source code
itself.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So this is where a programmer creates the
ABAP that
processes the data that was passed in, it
sends data back
out through the export, it can change
variables, and
also update internal tables and then
report any exceptions.
So just by looking at this code, it can
see some comments here.
It's showing you the fields it's
importing, the fields that it will export,
in this case just one.
And any exceptions.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The programmer in this case, starts out
with a describe field statements,
and we've got an if statement.
And we can just continue down to have a
look at the code and
try to determine what it does.
Now the beauty about function modules that
have already been created is,
we don't need to know what the code is
doing.
Because hopefully, we know what this
function module should return to us.
And in this case, this specific function
module.
What it does, it turns a numeric value
into words.
So let's say you had to send out printed
checks.
Well maybe your program could call this,
pass it in a numeric value, this would
return the value spelled out in words, and
then you could output that on the checks.
[BLANK_AUDIO]