Now, because function modules are created
separate to our normal programs,
we are given various tools that allow us
to test out function modules,
without having to write the code to call
them.
So, similar to how we would test our
program.
We are also given the tools to test
function modules, completely in isolation.
We can test the function module by
pressing the F8 key
once we're in this screen.
Or just click the icon, the little wrench
icon.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now I'm gonna step back, I'll step back
again.
Once we're at the first screen of SE38, we
can also test it from this location.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now every function module that you try and
test will look a little bit different.
Because the screen you see is determined
from the import parameters,
changing parameters, and tables.
So depending on all those settings, your
screen will look different,
depending on the different function module
you want to test.
So in this case, we know that all the
fields are optional, so we could just test
this without inputting any data, and let's
do that and see what gets returned.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So this is the output.
It shows us the input, and then this is
what's returned.
Seems a bit gibberish, doesn't it?
It all makes sense, actually.
Because, we get this little button here.
And this lets us focus on the result that
have been returned by the function module.
Now in this case, it's telling us, the
number zero.
Well, we didn't key anything in.
Number of decimals is zero.
We didn't specify the currency.
But look, it has returned the word zero to
us.
So actually, the function module ran
perfectly fine.
So now, let's key in an amount, and
this time, let's key in 123456.
So that's 123,456.
We will leave CURRENCY, FILLER and
LANGUAGE blank, and just execute.
Here you can see, this was the input, and
it's
returned to us ONE HUNDRED TWENTY-THREE
THOUSAND FOUR HUNDRED FIFTY-SIX.
So that worked just as we wanted.
Now we do have some other options, don't
we?
We have currency.
Let's have a look what happens when we key
that in.
My currency is Great British Pounds, so
I'll key in GBP and then execute.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now this function module, this time,
because it knows in Britain we have two
decimal places, it's identified that.
Let's focus in on the table that it's
returned.
So it knows we have two decimal places, so
it's returned ONE THOUSAND TWO HUNDRED and
THIRTY-FOUR.
And it's treated the 56 as the two decimal
places.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
If we chose a currency again of no decimal
places, I think that the Hungarian forint.
Then we're back to the full text.
It knows that the Hungarian forint has no
decimal places, so
we get ONE HUNDRED and TWENTY-THREE
THOUSAND FOUR HUNDRED and FIFTY-SIX.
So, a very small function module, but you
can see, it's got its uses.
But it shows exactly how we can test a
function module in isolation.
So that we don't have to worry about
getting the coding right in our program
before ensuring, yep, this is the function
module we want to use.
And it lets us test out the parameters
that we need to fill in very quickly,
so that when we come to do our coding,
we know what fields we're actually gonna
fill in in our ABAP code