Now we have identified the function module
we want to use in our program, and
tested it successfully.
Let's look at how we can call it from our
program by using ABAP.
So let me step out the function module
builder.
I'll go back to SE38.
Create a brand new program.
And we'll call
this Z Mod 2.
[SOUND]
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then we can start coding.
Now the first thing I want to do is set up
a parameter on the selection screen.
So I can enter a value.
So I'm going to define a parameter.
[SOUND] Let's call it my [UNKNOWN].
We'll make it an integer and
what we will do is make the screen look
half decent.
[SOUND] So let's do selection
screen begin of line.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's have a comment in there.
Start it at the first position for 15
characters.
We'll use a text element.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we have our parameter and then we'll
add in the end of line.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's see how we look.
Looking good so all we need to do now is
define the text.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Choose yes to create it.
And we'll key in enter a value.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's activate that.
[SOUND] Back to our program and then we'll
activate that as well.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then a quick test just to make sure it
looks okay on the screen and
it does as our text element and we can
enter a value in there.
[SOUND] So back to our code.
So now we can enter a value into the
screen.
What we want to do is pass that value to
our function module.
But of course we can't do that until we
define the code that allows us to call the
function module.
So instead of just typing in the code
straight to the editor, let's use
the pattern tool which is control F6 or
you can click pattern.
[SOUND] So
as you can see the call function option is
the first one the in list.
So all we need to do is enter spell
amount.
Which is our function module name and
click the continue button [SOUND] and
as if by magic it'll for us to save us a
whole bunch of typing and
you'll see a lot of the code is commented
out.
What I'm gonna do, I'm just gonna save it
and show you why.
I'm gonna double-click on the function
module itself,
to use forward navigation to go to the
function module.
And if you remember, on the importing tab,
all the fields were set as optional.
So I'll step back.
So when we use the pattern tool, any
optional fields,
it will automatically comment them out,
and
we just need to un-comment them to say
we're going to use them.
So in our case,
we're going to be exporting the amount
from our program to the function module.
And then inside the function module,
it will import that mount into its own
variable.
[SOUND]
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So you see, when we call a function
module,
the actual adapt statement itself is made
of, of the word Call and Function.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then we place the function itself
inside single quotes.
Include all the parameters, and then,
we have a full stop to terminate this
statement.
Now note the position of this period.
It appears on the line all by itself.
And it's there because the system
automatically commented out all
these optional variables for us, so the
system's not
going to know what we actually want to
fill in and what we don't fill in.
If the system put the period up here and
we uncommented
some of these variables then we would more
than likely get a syntax error.
Because the period would terminate the
statement up here at the end of the first
line and then we would have exporting list
of variables,
importing and so on.
For example if I do this
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We get some errors.
The system is not expecting the export
statement.
And that's all down to the placement of
the period.
I could bring it up to here.
But I'll just leave it there for now.
Oops.
[SOUND]
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And next, you'll notice the system
included an if statement for us.
Now the if statement is there so that we
always follow best practice and
check to make sure the function module was
called successfully.
Now you'll see that it says if [UNKNOWN]
not equals zero.
And that's indicating that if it's not
zero, there's a problem.
And if [UNKNOWN] that specific system
variable that we have used previously
will get filled with the values from the
exception.
So if [UNKNOWN] had a value of one.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We'll know the actual error message was
not found.
If it's two, we know the number that we
sent into
the function module was too large, and if
it's three,
it's some other error message the function
module didn't cater for.
So always check to see if [UNKNOWN] is
equal to anything other than zero,
every time you call a function module.
So let's have some code.
So if [UNKNOWN] is not equal to zero, we
don't want to try and
output the text that the function module
sends to us.
So why don't we do something like this?
[SOUND] Let's say,
result equals [SOUND]
the function [SOUND] module
[SOUND] returned a value of-
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then we can include [UNKNOWN].
Oops, what am I doing?
I do apologize.
I thought I was doing a write statement.
[LAUGH] Let's do that.
Let's do, right.
[BLANK_AUDIO]