Okay, so now we have the right statements,
and
it's going to write out the error code to
the screen if there is an error.
The next thing we want to do, is to be
able to write out to the screen
the amount in words that the function
module will return to us.
So, why don't we change this into an
[UNKNOWN] statement.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
We can say "the amount in words is" and
then we just need to output
the variable that's returned to us.
Now in this case, the variable that the
function module returns is inwards,
you will see that we've got an equals
sign,
but we need to assign our own variable
right here.
So let's use one called result.
Now of course we have to define result.
So I'm just going to save the program, do
some forward navigation
to see how IN_WORDS is actually defined in
the function module.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So we can see here it's defined by using
the light statement and referring to
spell.
And you can see spell is actually a
structure and
it's made up of all these individual.
Fields.
So we can do exactly the same.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So back in our code,
[SOUND] lets define results,
[SOUND] like spell.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
If we double click spell, oops, oh,
looks like a three click [LAUGH] it takes
us to the structure and
we can see that, our reference is working
fine in the program.
So now we can uncomment inwards which
means when the function
module executes successfully inwards will
be transferred to
our result variable, which is a structure.
And we can output it when the my-subrc
return code is zero.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now, we need to ensure importing is still
there because
we're gonna be importing the in words
variable and
assigning it to result, and also because
result is a structure
the write statements will probably not be
able to write out result.
It will probably not be able to do
automatic conversion because remember,
looking at the structure it had a mix of
data types in it.
So I'm just gonna save the code.
We have a look at SPELL which our results
structure is based on.
Here you can see we have NUMC, integers,
and characters, all mixed in.
So, in this case, I think we should get
syntax errors.
Let's have a look.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Result cannot be converted.
Yeah, so if you remember when we tested
our
function module lets go back in and test
it okay,
I need a number to work with what actually
gets returned is,
it's like a whole record made up of
individual fields.
So we have number, decimal, currency and
then word, and word is is quite large.
We carry on.
Another field called DEC word.
And then some more.
Actually breaking the words up into
individual fields themselves.
So we are getting returned a lot more than
just a piece of text, so
we have to cater for that.
So, I'll step back to the program and
if we look at the structure of spell.
Again, the piece of text we're really
interested in,
is the one that gets assigned to the field
word so that's what we need to write
out in our write statements.
So back down where we have
result all we need to do is reference the
field inside the structure.
And there's one more glaring mistake, or
just something I forgot to do and that's
we need to feed in the amount that we're
going to fill in on the selection screen.
So on the selection screen, we're using
the variable mynum.
So that's what we need to put here.
M Y N U M.
Now I think that should just about do it.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's activate, and then we'll test it
out.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So we'll use 46,791.
And we get the amount is 46,791.
We have success.
So there you go.
That's how you call a function module.
It's quite straight forward and
what I would advise is always use the
pattern function inside the ABAP
editor because it gives you all the
variables to work with automatically.
Now from here you should be able to use
any function module that is inside SAP
and by having so many function modules
available to you,
you should be able to more or less copy.
How existing function modules are set up
and create your own.