To create our first program from your SAP
[UNKNOWN],
you can either key in transaction SE38 or
you can navigate to the ABAP Editor
through the SAP menu tree.
Go to tools, ABAP Workbench Developments
and there you'll see SE38 ABAP Editor.
Double click and execute it.
Now, just before we create out program,
just something to keep in mind.
Try and keep your programs as simple as
possible do not make your programs
any more complicated than they need to be.
Now I say this because, through my many
years of experience with SAP,
more often than not, you have to pick up
somebody else's program, try and
understand it, and either make
enhancements to it, or
fix bugs that have been identified
sometime after it has gone live.
The worst thing in the world is opening up
a program and seeing 100 and
100 of 1000 lines of code with very few
comments and
it takes just an absolute age to
understand.
I advise you all to keep things really
simple.
Add lots of comments into your code, so
that anybody else, and
yourself, that comes to look at the
program later on, can easily understand
what the program is doing, and the flow of
the logic as it's executed.
It makes everybody's life just that much
easier.
So let's get going.
We'll enter our first program name.
Now remember, we have to use our customer
naming conventions.
In this case that means we're going to
start the program with the letter Z.
After a Z, you can name it whatever you
want we're
going to stick with the employee theme.
That we used when we created our table.
So I'm going to enter
said_employee_list_01.
You noticed that I used underscores just
to separate the words within the program.
Just to make things a little easier on the
eyes.
Ensure that the source code radio button
is selected.
And then click the Create button.
We're then presented with this Program
Attributes window.
And the first thing you need to key in is
the title for your program.
So I'm just going to enter some text that
describes what the program does.
[SOUND]
My Employee List Report.
Ensure that the original language is set
to EN, which it is by default.
And just something to note.
The language of the program
has an effect on what text entries are
displayed within certain programs.
You will see that the original language
field has automatically been filled in
with EN, for English It's important to
note that any text
entries you create within your program are
language specific and
they can be maintained for each country by
using a translation tool.
Now we're not gonna be doing this right
now, but it's just something for
you to keep in mind.
Now come down to the attributes and you'll
see the type click the drop down
button and select executable program now
this means
our program can be executed without the
need for us to create a transaction code.
And it also means the program can be run
as a background job.
We'll set the status of our program to
test program and
we'll set the application to basis.
Now these two fields are just used to help
manage the program within
the sub system itself.
And it describes what the programs will be
used for, and
also the program development status.
Now we don't need to touch any other field
here.
So, leave the Authorization Group, Logical
database, and Selection screen empty.
And make sure the Editor lock field is
left clear.
If you do turn on Editor lock it will
prevent the program from being edited.
That's not what we want [LAUGH].
Leave unicode checked active.
And I suggest you always leave it active
for every program you create.
This ensures your program can cater for
multibyte coding.
Ensure you leave the fixed point
arithmetic checked,
because without this any packed decimal
fields that we use within our program
will all be rounded to whole numbers.
And we will leave the start using variants
check box blank.
We will touch on variants later on, but
for now just go ahead and
click the Save button.
[SOUND] You should be familiar with this
object directory entry box.
And because we're not going to be
transporting our programs,
just click the local object button to
assign our
program to our temporary development
class.
And now you've made it you finally got to
the coding screen.