Now let's go down and focus on the coding
area.
And you can see when we created our
program,
the first set of lines we see [SOUND] Are
common lines.
[SOUND] And we were presented with seven
comment lines
that ideally can be used to start
commenting your program.
Now comments in ABAP can appear in two
ways.
First of all, we see an asterisk at the
start of a line.
If you put an asterisk in there,
it turns everything to the right of the
asterisk into a comment.
And note it's important that the asterisk
has to be in the first column.
If you make it in the second column or
beyond, it's no longer a comment.
[SOUND] The other way of writing
a comment is within a line itself.
So we can go to the end of this report
line,
insert a few spaces and when we do the
double quotes,
everything to the right turns into a
comment.
[SOUND] This becomes really useful, so
you can comment your programs line by
line, or at the very least,
a few lines of comments for each section
of your program
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So let's delete that.
[SOUND] The next line of code that
we see starts with a word report.
And this is called a statement.
And a report statement is always the first
statements
in any executable program we create.
The statement itself is then followed by
the program name that we created.
Then the statement line is terminated with
a full stop.
Now the full stop is way beyond the end of
the actual program name.
Doesn't really matter where it appears as
long it appears after the program name.
It could appear there, could appear
halfway,
could, could appear right at the end,
doesn't really matter.
But what is important to note is that
every statement in ABAP
must finish with the full stop or period.
This allows your statement to take up as
many lines in the editor as you wish.
So our report statement could in effect be
like that.
As long as we've got the period at the end
of the statement everything will be fine.
Here's the period that says when the
statement is finished.
[SOUND] Now just before we get on to
writing our first piece of code,
I'll just tell you about the help options.
If you place your cursor on any ABAP
statement,
you can then press this help on button
which we discussed earlier.
It will then bring up a window
automatically filling in the keyword and
all you need to do is press the continue
button.
And the system will display help on that
specific statement and
give you an explanation of what it is used
for on the syntax.
So I'll click the continue button and up
pops the ABAP help.
And you can see it's navigated direct to
the port statements and
tells you all the different additions that
you an add in there.
And this goes for every single other
statements within an SAP system.
Now as with SAP there's always more than
one way of doing things.
So what you can do as well, is just click
on the statements, and
then just press the F1 key.
And you'll notice it misses out that first
step,
that middle screen that we were shown.
Now one of the little tips I'll give you
right now, which I found really,
really useful when I was learning ABAP, is
a new transaction.
So we'll open up a new session.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And this transaction is called ABAPDOCU.
A-B-A-P-D-O-C-U.
And this is SAP's ABAP documentation with
examples.
So if you navigate the preview on the left
hand side, and
double click on any of the entries.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] This transaction will give you
example code that you can use to base
your own code on.
You can either copy and paste it into your
own ABAP editor or
play around with it directly here.
So we can execute this code by clicking on
the execute button and
the example program will run.
This is a really good transaction to help
you with learning ABAP because
it gives endless examples of how to use
the different statements.
So let's go back to our program there.
And what we'll do is enter our first line
of code.
So what I'll do first is just put our
report statement back to how it
should look.
And on a new line,
key in the write statement,
followed by [SOUND] Hello SAP world.
If you've done programming before,
I'm sure you'll be familiar with that
statement.
So have a guess what the right statement
will do.
It's fairly easy.
It will write whatever we put in quotes to
the output window.
Here we're asking it to output the text
hello SAP world.
The right statement looks very simple and
it is.
But there are lots of different additions
you can add to it.
To help format the output.
We'll come to those in a little while.
But right now no doubt you're eager to see
this report run and
see this spectacular output.
So what we'll do is first of all save our
program.
[SOUND] Once it's saved we can then
check the syntax of our program
[SOUND] Everything is correct.
And we need to activate the program.
[SOUND] And once it's activated you can
see the status has changed.
And then we're ready to test it.
So just press the test button.
And now we can see our report title, and
then the text we asked it to output.
How good's that?
You've written your first program.
All with adding just one line of code.
Now to celebrate, go grab yourself a nice
cup of coffee, have a cup of tea or
whatever your preference is, because we've
got a long way to go.