Now you've got your first program under
your belt.
Let's expand on the program a little bit
and add in a few more ABAP statements.
So let's step back.
Back to our coding screen.
And what we're gonna do now Is access some
of the data
records that we created when we built our
first table in the ABAP dictionary.
To do this,
the first thing we have to do is include
the table statement into our program.
And we'll place the table statement just
below the report statement.
So I'll create a few blank lines.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And I'll key in tables.
Now following tables, we key in the actual
table name that we created.
Now if memory serves me right,
I think it was z_ employee_list_01.
And then remember, we need a period at the
end of the statements.
Now, one little thing.
Remember, I mentioned about pretty
printer?
I like my programs to look a certain way.
And I'm always formatting them as I'm
going along.
So, what I'm gonna do here is just click
Pretty Printer,
and we can see, what has happened is the
table statement,
the write statement, they've been
converted to uppercase.
And then the actual table, and program
name, they will convert it to lowercase.
This is just my own personal preference,
and
if you want to play around with how the
programs looks for
yourself, you'll be able to do that
through the Utilities menu,
go to Settings and then from the ABAP
Editor go to Pretty Printer,
and these are the settings that I have.
So automatically indent, convert
upper/lowercase,
and I want to convert my keywords to
uppercase.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So let's quickly review what the table
statement does.
When the program is executed,
this table statement will create a table
structure in memory based on the structure
that we defined in the ABAP dictionary of
our zemployee list 01 table.
The table structure will contain all the
fields that we created.
And this will allow us to read records
from the table, and
store them in this temporary structure for
our program to use.
So, to get these records into our table
structure,
we're going to use the select statement.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So we'll key in select
asterisk from.
Now you'll see that I do get lazy, so I
like to do copy and paste quite a lot.
And that's how a simple select statement.
And what we're saying is, select
everything and the asterisk,
from our table.
Because the select statement is a loop,
we need to tell our program where the end
of the loop is.
We do that by keying in end select.
So our loop starts with a select and ends
with end select.
So if this statement is now going to read
every row of the table into our table
structure we need to do something with it.
So what we're going to do here
is just use the write command that we have
used before.
So I'll just cut that and paste it in, but
instead of saying write,
hello SAP world, we are going to say
write a whole row at once to the output
window.
I'll click Pretty Printer, just to tidy up
the code.
Now we have our select loop, we're going
to write out every row of our table and
display it to us in the output window.
So let's check our code.
[SOUND] We can see we have our first
syntax error,
and if you notice, the cursor is changed
position.
And it's gone to the table statement at
the start of the actual table
that we identified.
And it's telling us the dictionary,
structure or table is either not active or
does not exist.
So it's likely I've just got this name
wrong.
So all we need to do,
I'll open up another session.
Go to SE 11.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we can see we actually called our
table Z employees.
So I'm just going to copy this name to the
clipboard,
close that window, get rid of the syntax
error.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And paste the proper table name right
there.
Pretty Pinter again, just to format it.
Now, because we changed the table name up
here,
we also need to replace any of the
occurrence that we have.
So it needs to be there.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And there.
Pretty Printer again.
Good, we'll save our program, check the
code.
Now everything is fine.
The tables are recognized, and we can test
our program.
So click the Test button or just press the
F8 key.
And as if by magic, our output window
shows every row of our table.
If you remember, we add the employee
number as the first field and
the surname and the forename, the tiny
tool, and then date of birth.
So if we keep the output window in mind
when we go back to our code and
just have a look at the SELECT statement
again, we can see that a loop happened.
And every row of data was written to the
output window.
Now let's dig a little deeper, and have a
look at the output window again.
We can see here that the system
automatically
put each line from the table on a new row.
The write statement that we had in our
program didn't know that
each new row had to be output on the new
line.
But this was forced because of some
default settings held
within our system about our own individual
screen settings.
Now if we try to print this report,
it could well be that there are too many
columns, or
too many characters to actually fit On a
standard piece of A4.
This will be determined by the width of
the paper specified in the printer
settings.
So don't count on your output being in the
right format for the reports you create.
What I suggest is you use an addition to
the report
statements where you specify the width of
each line.
Which, if we go back to our program.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
If you click on the report statements and
press the F1 key.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
You'll see the line size column addition
that we can up.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And you can see right here, it says if the
line size specification is missing,
the line length corresponds to the current
screen width.
You can check the screen width by
referencing this built-in system field.
And he tells us the maximum width of the
list is 1,023 characters.
So what we're gonna do in this example, is
specify a line size.
I'll just use bit of copy and paste.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we'll add the addition to our report
statement.
We need to take out the less than sign.
And in this example, let's limit the line
size just to 40 characters.
And see what effect that has on the
output.
So we'll save our code, check it for
syntax errors, activate it, and then test
it.
And there you can see.
The line has been broken at 40 characters
in length.
Which I guess is right here.
It didn't do a line wrap or anything like
that.
It just truncated the whole line.
So keep in mind, if you're outputting your
list to paper, normally for,
I think is 132 characters as it specified
in the Help section.
And if you do landscape, it's even bigger.
But anything greater will likely be
truncated automatically.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So if we did 132.
[SOUND] This time, I'll just activate it
which automatically does the check.
And I'll test.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And now we're back to seeing the full
output.
And we can see 132 characters, actually
goes right up to this level here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's now enhance our program a little bit
more by adding
some specific formatting to the write
statements.
So what we're going to do is insert a line
break.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
At the start of every row that we output
within our select statements.
So first of all, I'm just gonna copy this
code.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Paste it in again.
Let's just separate our table statement
from our code.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we'll work with this select statement
right here.
So what we need to do, is where we got our
write statement,
include the forward slash.
And the forward slash is what will trigger
a new line for the write command.
So let's save the code.
And execute it.
And you can see the first select loop,
output the first five rows, the second
select loop, output the next five.
And look, it's identical.
Why do we think it's identical?
Well, it's all down to this report
statement again.
Because we specified the line size of 132,
the system automatically
wrapped the first select loop at 132
characters.
So every row that was output, once it got
to 132,
it then caused a brand new line to be
written.
If we increase this, lets say 532,
we should see the effect of this write
statement
wrapping along just a couple of rows.
[SOUND] So let's test it out.
And here we go.
The first row finishes here.
But then because we said we want the
output to be 532 characters long,
the next row was output immediately after
the first one.
And if we scroll along.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We can see it then output the next one as
well.
All the way until it got to 532 characters
before it then forced
another line break.
So I think here, it was actually the first
four records were output on the first row,
then the fifth was output on the second
one.
Then came our second select loop.
And because we've forced a line break
before every row was output,
they all appear correctly under one
another in our report.
So let's step back.
I'll put this back to 132.
And what we will do is add another little
bit of formatting just so
that we can see the separation between the
different select loops.
So what I'm going to do here is type,
uline.
And uline simply means underline.
I press the F1 key.
We'll see an explanation.
Writes a continuous underline in a new
line.
So that will help separate the different
select statement outputs that we have on
our screen.
It'll be a little easier on the eye.
So if we execute this.
[SOUND] There we go.
We can see this nice underline showing us
our second select loop.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The next thing we'll do, is just change
this select statements a little bit.
So we'll copy it again.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And create new underline.
I will remove the slash before the new row
is output.
And adding a write statement with a slash
on its own.
And that will mean a new line will be
output at the end of the previous line.
[SOUND] So we'll check it under our Pretty
Printer.
I always like it to look nice.
And we'll test our code.
And we can see a new line is being written
after a row is being output.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's go back and just change things up
just one more time.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
This time we'll go back to the SELECT
statement with the /zemployees like so.
But, we're going to include one more
statement, which is skip,
and skip means skip a line.
And you can have an addition with the skip
statements to allow
you to skip multiple lines, so in this
case, we'll say skip two lines.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Press the F1 key on skip.
Just to see the help on it.
There you can see skip.
Skip however many lines you want.
Or you can skip to a specific line number.
So let's close
the help.
Click Pretty Printer.
And execute our gold.
Here we go.
So we're using the same select statements
that we have here.
The second one.
Copied it down here, but we included the
skip two lines
right there.
Now, let's change things up just a little
bit more.
And this time, instead of outputting the
whole row of the table,
we will output individual fields.
So let' s create another SELECT statement.
In fact, you know what I'm gonna do right
now?
Because we're duplicating lots of lines,
and
it's starting to look complicated, let's
add some comments.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And this one we're going to work on.
Okay, another basic select statement, but
this time outputting individual fields.
So how do we do this?
Well, all we need to do is specify the
individual field.
So here we have the table name, and when
you want to specify an individual field,
you use a dash, and then the actual field
name.
So we have surname, forename, title,
date of birth, and I think the first field
was employee number.
So let's just choose surname.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
I think forename,
then we'll do date of birth.
Now, I'm not sure if I've got these field
names exactly correct, so
I'll just use forward navigation and check
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Surname, forename, and date of birth.
A stroke of luck.
So now, we'll do a syntax check.
Everything is good.
Activate our program, and then test.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So as we scroll down, here we go.
So our first record is Brown, Stephen,
with this date of birth, and we
can see [UNKNOWN] put it on an individual
line, Brown, Stephen, date of birth.
And the second record, third, fourth, and
then fifth.
So, that's writing individual lines.
Now let's tidy this up, because, maybe we
just want three fields on one line.
So we'll take out this line break in front
of second and third field.
X this out.
There we go.
Just the three fields we want, all on
their own individual line.
One last thing I'll do, I'll just insert
another underline
just to keep it tidy.
[SOUND] And there we go.
[BLANK_AUDIO]