And I want to introduce something called
Chaining Statements Together.
You will have noticed in our program,
that we are using the right statement
quite a lot.
Now to save us time, we can chain our
right statements together.
And this saves us from having to duplicate
the right statement on every
line that we write.
So to do this,
I'll copy a new
section of code.
Change some clients,
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And what we do with the WRITE statement is
add a colon after it.
This tells the SAP system that our WRITE
statement is going to write
out multiple fields or text literals as we
define.
So, here we have WRITE, new line and the
surname.
We're then gonna change the full stop to a
comma.
[NOISE] Get rid of the second WRITE
statement.
Do the same with the third.
[NOISE] Edit the code and then when we
have our last
item we want to output with a WRITE
statement,
that's where we put the period.
So what this is basically doing is,
the colon says to the system we're going
to output many items.
We separate the items by a comma and we
use the period to terminate the statement.
Very simple, and it can be used for
many other statements such as the move
statement.
So we can execute the code
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we should see we got exactly the same
output as the one above.
The only difference is we've chained our
write statements together,
saving our precious fingers from too many
key presses.