In this lesson, we're going to concentrate
on creating fields in our program.
There are two types of fields that we're
going to be looking at.
The first type is variables, and the
second one is constants.
Before we get into the nitty gritty,
we first need to generate a brand new
program.
To do this,
you can follow along with the steps that
we outlined in previous modules.
Or, you can use the copy function in your
ABAP Editor.
Personally, I like to generate a new
program myself, but
if you want to reuse a lot of the existing
code, choose the copy function and
that's what I'll do right now, just to
take you through it step by step.
So first of all, enter your original
program in the text box, and
click Ctrl+F5 or press the copy button.
For the window that's asking us to enter a
new name for our program and
we'll just put z employee list 02, then
press the copy button.
Then were given a screen that asks if we
want to copy any additional objects and
you can see we have documentation that in
user interface screens and includes.
We haven't created any of these objects in
the previous program, so we just need to
leave those blank and just click the copy
button.
Assign your new program to the local
object development class.
[UNKNOWN] And there you can see the status
bar at the bottom tells you the copy has
been successful.
So now it's automatically put the new
program name in the program text box.
So, just click the change button.
And one thing to know, the copy function
works successfully but
you'll notice, it copied across references
to our old report name.
So here we have a comment, so if you do
use the copy function,
just remember to update your comment and
your actual report name itself.
There we go.
Now for this example,
I'm just going to take away this line size
statement just so we don't come across
any line restrictions while we're testing
our program.
Now also, because we have many, many
select statements and write statements in
this program let's go through how we can
just use the fast comment facility.
So a lot of the time I will actually
delete a lot of code out of the program.
But just for demonstration purposes I'll
show you how
to comment code out really fast, so
normally you come in, and
you put an asterisk at the start of each
line, there's a quick way of doing this,
if you highlight the lines of code that
you want to comment,
then you can hold down the control key and
the less than sign and
it will automatically select the asterisk
in the first column of the ABAP Editor.
Comment a line, if you can't remember your
key presses, another way to do this.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Is through the utilities menu.
And, let's see if I can find it.
Here we go.
Under the block/buffer, choose insert
comment.
That's exactly the same thing.
But all the other stuff, I'm just going
to delete it.
In fact, I'm going to delete a lot of
things.
Okay I'll save the program and then we'll
get going with fields.
So i'm sure everybody has a good idea of
what a field is but just so
that we can cover it a field is a
temporary area of memory
that we can assign a name to, and
reference within our programs.
We use fields within our program to hold
calculation results.
They're used by the program to help
control the logic flow.
And because they are temporary areas of
storage, and that storage
is normally held in ram, they can be
accessed super fast.
Which helps speed up our program
execution.
There are many other uses for fields
within the program whilst creating your
own programs and reading other programs
created by other people.
So let's have a look at variables and how
we declare variables in our program.
Now variable is a field who's values
change during the program execution.
Hence the term itself, variable.
And there are a few rules for variables
that you got to follow.
They must start with a letter, they can
have a maximum size of thirty characters.
You cannot include the plus, comma, colon,
and parentheses in the name.
And you cannot use a reserved word.
Now when you are creating variables try
and
keep the name of the variable meaningful.
There's nothing worse than working with a
program where your variables are named a1,
a2, a3, and so on.
Try and give them good names, such as our
employee table.
It's got surname, forename, and date of
birth.
You know exactly what these fields are
for.
Now we declare variables.
By using the data statements.
So lets go ahead and use the data
statements within our program.
We'll go below the comments section,
in the first type of field we'll declare
will be an integer field.
So we'll type in data, and a space, and
then we'll give our field a name,
gonna call this integer 01,
and we specify a data type by using the
type word.
And integers are declared by using the
TYPE i.
And we terminate our statement with a full
stop.
Let's declare it another one.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And this time we'll use the packed decimal
[SOUND] so
I call the field packed decimal01,
TYPE p, for packed decimal.
And then you end the statement with a full
stop again.
Now, packed_decimal is there to help store
numbers with decimal places, and so on.
So, what we can do is,
actually, define how many decimal places
we want our variable to hold.
So, when we've got TYPE p, we can then put
space.
I'm putting the word decimals and
then number of decimal places we want to
store I'll put 2.
Use pretty printer and it coverts
everything how I like it and
we'll save the program now we have used
what are called elementary data types
to define these two variables, and these
types of variables have a fixed length in
ABAP, so we actually don't need to declare
how long the variables need to be.
Now a little later on we'll have a look at
all the elementary data types and
the space that they take up in memory.
One piece of information to know about the
packed_decimal is that it can
store up to fourteen decimal places.
So in business related scenarios that's
more than ample.
So as well as declaring variables this
way,
we have another option of declaring
variables.
Using what we call the like addition to
the data statements.
Let me show you how this looks.
So we can declare a brand new variable
we'll call it pipe decimal 02 and
instead of using the word type this time
we're going
to use the word like and we're going to
say like the packed
decimal01 field that we have already
defined.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now what this effectively does is makes
sure that the new variable called
packed decimal02.
Takes on exactly the same properties That
we defined for packed decimal 01.
Now, you may think, well, you know?
What's, what's so good about this?
Well, let me show you.
In the program, let's say you have a need
to create a whole number of variables.
All of the same data type.
Here we are practice [UNKNOWN] three and
practice [UNKNOWN] four.
By making them like, packed decimal 01,
we could potentially save ourselves a
whole bunch of time later on.
Because let's say our pack decimal 01
field Instead of
saying decimal places needs to be two
let's say we need to increase it to three.
Just by updating that one variable that
automatically updates all the other
variables that have been defined using the
like statement
referring to our original variable.
And another good thing about the [UNKNOWN]
statement
is we don't have to just refer to
variables in our program.
We can refer to variables or
fields in this case that exist in tables
within the sub system.
So, if your remember back when we defined
the zed employees table,
we had a field of, I think it was surname.
We can declare a new variable within our
program.
Lets call it, new surname.
And we can say, it's going to be like
table name zed employees.
dash, then the actual field name.
Which I think was surname.
Now from my many years experience using
ABAP, this saved me a whole bunch of time.
Because quite often, you have to include
numerous tables within your ABAP programs.
And you can never remember what the actual
dates or times are, of every field.
So just by using the like statement,
I'm referring to the actual field within
the table.
You can declare your brand new variables
in your program
without having to use your brain or
go searching throughout the SAP system to
find what the exact data type is.
So, just to make sure everything's okay
we'll, we'll just do a check.
Everything's good.
Now, I'll just tidy things up a little bit
so we can carry on.
So get rid of that one.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And those.
Also what I like to do.
I always like to line up my data type
declarations.
So, it's a little easier to read.
So, now, let's have a look at one other
addition
that we can add to our data's name.
And, that is how we declare initial values
for
the variables that we define in our
program.
And it's really easy.
So in this example, we have the integer
01.
All we need to do is add the word value.
And because it's an integer it's just
going to accept numeric values so we can
say 22.
And automatically assigns a value of 22 to
interger01 when the program starts.
Now for packed decimal fields, it
is very similar but there's one slight
difference.
Which I pin the value and then we have to
put the actual value
within single quotes, and this is because,
as I mentioned previously,
an ABAP statement is terminated at the use
of a period.
And for a packed decimal field that has
decimal numbers.
We used a period to define the decimal
place within the number.
Usually, this would terminate our
statement.
But, by putting a number within quotes,
it's telling ABAP and the SAP system,
you know?
We're not terminating the statements.
We're just declaring a decimal number.
And one more addition just for
completeness is you're not just
restricted to positive numbers if you want
to declare a negative number,
just put the appropriate sign for the
value of the field.