Let's now take a look at declaring the
other type of variable, called constants.
So a constant is a field within our
program whose value
stays the same during the complete
execution of the program.
We never want it to change.
Hence the term, constant.
We can declare constants by using the
constants statement instead of
the data statement.
And when we declare a constant, we must
also assign a value to that field.
When we are writing code, we can then only
ever reference the constant variable,
but never change the value of it.
If you do try and change the value of a
constant within your program,
you'll usually get a runtime error, so
don't try it.
[LAUGH] So let's have a look at the syntax
for declaring a constant variable.
The syntax is very similar to the data
statement, but
with a few minor differences.
First of all, you have to use the word
constants.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Give it a name.
Now, it was supposed to say MYCONSTANT1.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Give it a type.
And there we have it.
We're done.
We want to do another one.
This time we'll make it a normal integer.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Very easy.
And just one thing to note, you cannot
define
constants for data types, X strings,
for references, internal tables, and
structures containing internal tables.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So just remember,
we will come on to those data types at a
later stage of this training program.