In this module, we're going to take a look
at how we can change the transparent
tables that we created
earlier on in the course.
It's important you know how to do this and
the implications of adding and
taking away fields to the underlying
data in your database table.
So as a reminder, let's take a look at
the table we created called zemployees.
So in the SAP GUI, we can choose
transaction SE11, or under the tools menu,
ABAP Workbench and then Development,
you've got the ABAP Dictionary transaction
there in case you forget
the transaction code.
So, here it's already entered
the table name for me.
I'll choose display, and
we can see the six fields that
we entered to create our table.
Remember MANDT is the client field that is
automatically maintained by the system.
And then we have employee
which is our employee number,
our surname, forename,
title, and date of birth.
Now it's important to realize
that whenever you want to change
a database table,
you run the risk of losing data,
especially when you're affecting
the key fields in your table.
The database system itself will try and
determine if you can make adjustments
by deleting and creating new items which
change the underlying database catalog.
Or whether you have to re-implement
what you have already defined.
Quite often with large tables, you have
to manage the manipulation of the data
yourself so as to be sure
that you don't lose the data.
When your tasks involve just deleting
fields, it's quite a simple task.
But, depending on the table structure and
the contents,
this also has certain complications.
So, before you start any of
these database change tasks,
it's a good idea to mitigate against
as many risks as possible and
start by using a copy
of your database table.
This will allow you to test out any
change activities you want to make
without the risk of affecting the original
table and the underlying data.
And when you copy a database table,
you only copy the table structure itself.
This means just the table properties,
the fields, not the actual data.
So let's have a look at
how we can copy our table.
So we will step back,
back to our initial SE 11 screen.
We already have our table name,
ZEmployees, which we will copy.
Now all we need to do is go to
the Copy button, which is Ctrl+F5.
And decide on the table name
that we want to copy to.
So let's be very original and
stick a number 2 on the end.
Click the green tick for the okay,
and as normal, we'll be asked for
a development class.
And as in the last modules,
what we will choose is local object.
That's all there is to it.
You've now got a copy of the table.
So we have ZEMPLOYEES2 in
our database table there.
We can choose Display.
And we can see an exact
copy of the original table.
Now one thing to note is that even though
we've copied a table, we can't use it yet,
because if you have a look at the status,
it says new.
We need to activate our program.
So we'll click the Change button.
And then we'll click the Activate button.
Now remember, or table uses data elements,
which use data domains that we've
already set up in the previous module.
So all of those objects
are already active.
And when we activate our table,
all it needs to do is just activate the
table itself, no other objects behind it.
So now we can take a look at the table and
if you remember, I've said,
all we do is copy the table structure,
not the contents.
So if we look at the table contents.
We can see that we've got
no records in the table.
So what we will do now is enter some
records into our table so that later on,
when we try and add fields and
take fields away,
we will see various warning signs
coming up from the system to tell
us we may be about to delete data and
it will be unrecoverable.
So, let's go ahead just choose the, sorry,
we'll step back,
then we'll choose the Utilities menu,
Table contents, and Create entries.
So now you should be
familiar with this screen.
We can just create a number of employees.
Super original.
Let's do the drop-down box for
the date of birth.
Just so I get the format correct.
And save our record.
Okay, so now we've entered three records
and that should be enough to then allow us
to change the database and
see what effects it has on the data.
So just to make sure everything's
been entered correctly,
we'll just choose the Contents view,
and click Number of entries.
We have three, and we can execute and
have a look at the contents.
So let's step back and
go to the table design.
And what we're gonna do is add a brand new
field, and we'll make it a non-key field.
And this is the same process that we went
through when we added fields originally.
So let's have a field called initials.
And remember to use the Z, and
remember this is a brand new data element.
So I will double-click and
use forward navigation to generate it.
And for the domain, let's see if
there's an existing one called Char3.
And there is.
Character field length three.
So we can use that one.
There are our field labels, and
we'll activate that data element.
Local objects.
There we go,
that data element's now active.
So now when we step back to the table
we can see it's brought through
the field title and
the actual data type of the field.
Let's add another field,
this time called gender.
And no prizes to guess what we're
gonna call the data elements.
We can see the data element doesn't exist.
So forward navigation,
Yes to save the table,
Yes to create the data element.
I'll give it a name and
just copy it to the clipboard for
when we do the field label.
And here we'll just make it Char01, and
we can see it already exists,
which is fine.
Activate the object, then we'll step back.
And we have the field.
Let's have another one called salary.
ZSalary.
Double-click.
You know the drill.
Now this one is going to be
a currency field cuz it's salary.
So what we're gonna choo, do,
is choose a currency field called Curi9,
I think that exists.
Yeah, there we go.
And this is a currency field,
we can see it's got a length of
nine with two decimal places.
You can create your own, or
search in the the data dictionary and
use a different one if you like.
But I know this one exists and
I've used it before.
Go to Field label.
Local object.
Activate it, and step back.
Now, one important thing with the,
salary field is, because it's a currency,
we actually need to include
a separate currency field that is
attached to ZSalary to indicate
what currency the salary is in.
So I'm from the UK, so this, for me,
would be, GBP, Great British Pounds.
If you're in the US, it'd be US Dollars.
So to do that.
Let's create a brand new co,
I'll tell you what we'll do.
First of all, I'll show you
the error message, if we try and
activate the table without
a corresponding currency field.
Here we go, errors occurred.
Let's have a look.
So what this is saying is
we need a reference field,
a reference table,
to hold the type of currency.
So let's step back and do that.
Let's call it ECurrency.
And the actual data elements,
we will use one that already exists,
because currency fields, there should
be no need to create your own,
because they should already
exist in the system.
And I know there's one called curcy.
I'll use that and press Enter.
And there we can see, it's a Currency Key
field with the length of five.
Now that's all well and good, but
what we need to do next is tell
the system that our salary field is
going to reference our currency field.
So this brings us onto this currency tab.
And when we flip to it, we can see that
because we are using field type currency,
this field is now available for
us to fill in.
And what we will do is enter
our currency field in there.
And we just need to put
our table name in here.
So we're gonna say this
currency key field is
a reference field for our salary field.
So now we can activate the table,
and everything is good.
Let's have a look at
what this actually does.
Let's go and enter another record,
or change an existing one, and
see what options we have for
entering our salary and currency.