So again, go to Utilities.
You create entries.
Let's add a new record.
Put in the surname, and the forename.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And some initials, gender female, we'll
have a salary of one, two,
three, four, five, and then we enter the
currency key now at the moment,
you'll see there's no drop-down or
anything like that, so
you don't really know what we need to put
in this currency key field.
For now, I will put GBP, because I know
that's gonna be a proper entry.
But what we'll do is save the record,
then we'll go back to the design of our
table and we'll build in some error
checking to ensure that we do enter
correct currency values in this field.
And also what'd be useful is on the
gender, let's do an example where
we can introduce a drop-down box so we can
only choose two values, male and female.
Why don't you save, and step back, and
we'll do just that.
So to enable us to build in error
checking,
we need to what are called foreign keys.
And we'll use foreign keys to ensure the
use can only enter valid values.
So what we'll do is use some forward
navigation,
and we'll take a look at the value table
used for our currency field.
So we'll double click.
And under the Data Types tab, we can see
this data element
refers to a standard SAP delivered domain,
WAERS.
Let's take a look at this domain.
So we use forward navigation again.
We can see use of time currency key.
Number of characters five.
And we go to the value range town and
look down at the bottom, we can see we
have a value table.
We have covered the value range tab before
when we created our table, but
as a reminder, we can use a value table to
determine the entries
we can make in the field within our table
that is based on this domain.
So let's use some forward navigation to
look at this table.
Here we can see what the table is made up
of.
We've got six fields.
We've got the standard client, currency
key, our currency code.
And then some other fields let's take a
browse at the actual data.
And if we scroll down, here we go.
So this record right here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
That's the value I entered into our table,
GBP.
So I know it's going to be valid, but we
can make use of this check table or this
value range table, to ensure we allow the
user to only pick values from this table.
So let's step back.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we'll step back again.
And now we're back to our table.
So, what we need to do is go back to our
fields tab, highlight
our currency field, and then we're gonna
define a foreign key.
[SOUND] So we'll click the foreign key
button.
[SOUND] And we'll get asked if we want to
create it.
We'll choose yes.
[SOUND] Now we're being displayed this
create foreign key screen.
So what we'll do is key in some short text
and
we get the option of two fields.
Now, these two fields are the two key
fields from the TCURC currency table.
And from our table we do have the option
of ensuring that this
foreign key matches both fields so that
when we allow the user
to select an entry records that returned
will only be valid for
the client that we are working in.
But in our case we won't choose this
client field to be part of the key,
we'll just choose our W-A-E-R-S field.
So all we're gonna do is click this
generic option and
we can wipe out these just for clarity so
then this foreign key will just use our
currency field.
Much indeed W-A-E-R-S field.
In the [UNKNOWN] table.
All we need to do is click on copy and now
our foreign key has been created.
So let's activate our table.
[SOUND] And let's go and have a look at
the data you can see our last record in
row four.
I'm gonna place my cursor on the currency
key field.
I can press the F4 key and now we're
displayed with
with the drop-down box of all valid
entries that can go in there.
Now we have just chosen to display the
data in our table.
Therefore, we've got no entry box here.
It's only display only, but the drop-down
still works to show us the valid values.
If we went back to create a record or
change a record,
let's choose change now when we go to
the currency key field we can see that we
have the drop-down button that's appeared.
We can click it.
And choose an appropriate currency.
So let's go down and choose, $US.
And we can see it brings the value back,
and we can click save.
So our currency key has been saved in $US.
Let's go back.