So we're taking a look at foreign keys.
Now what i want to do, is discuss what's
called appendix structures.
And in our last example we added some
fields to our table.
We also have the option of using append
structures to add additional fields.
And this is the preferred method of
maintaining SAP delivered tables and
quite often extending your own customer
specific tables, why would
we use appendix structures rather than
just adding fields to our table?
Well, if it's a standard SAP table and we
add fields to it.
What if SAP released a new version of
software,
where they add some fields themselves?
Well, when we come to do an upgrade.
We're gonna have some serious
difficulties.
Because we could have added fields to the
table and
we tried to apply the update we could end
up with some serious errors.
Our fields could get overwritten by those
new fields that SAP have added.
You never want to be in that situation.
So to insure you don't come up against
this problem,
this is where append structures are a
great help.
Append structures give us a safe way to
enhance our tables and
standard sub-tables.
When we use append structures the existing
table remains unchanged
which removes any risk of our changes
being overwritten.
And quite often in an SAP system
you will see a table having multiple
append structures applied to it
because there have been different
development needs as time has gone by and
people want to add more fields to the
underlying standard sub-table.
So let's have a look at append structures,
how we create them how they are used.
So as you can see, we are already in
transaction SE11 with our table loaded.
What we need to do is use our mouse and go
to the append structure button.
[SOUND] We'll give it a click and
the system is automatically suggesting a
name for us.
And notice it's automatically telling us
to use our customer
name space making sure our pen structure
starts with the letter zed.
Let's accept this choice by the system
[SOUND] and
now we're displayed with what looks like
an empty table structure.
So let's go ahead and fill it in just like
we would with a normal table.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Extra fields for employees.
And when we come down to the body of the
screen,
notice this field now is called component.
And this is just where we create our new
fields.
But one thing to keep in mind, it would be
nice to differentiate our customer fields
in our table from our new custom
components in our append structure.
So the best way to do this is still stay
with the customer name space.
But where we'll use Z in the field name,
let's use ZZ.
And what we'll do is create a department
field.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And same thing with component type [SOUND]
use ZZ,
i choose yes to create.
[SOUND] It's just asking us to save the
append structure which we will do.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
It's asking us what type of object we want
to create and it's a data element.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] And let's choose.
Should we have a code or description?
Well let's choose 10 character code.
Let's say copy this [SOUND] choose a field
label.
[SOUND]
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And activate the data element.
[SOUND] [INAUDIBLE]
or step back.
Now we're back to our append structure,
is brought through the properties of the
data element and we can activate it.
[SOUND] So let's step back and it should
take us back to our table.
And now we have an extra row that shows
the actual append structure we've just
created.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
If we want to go back to it, you just
double-click the append structure.
[SOUND] So that's a very easy way to add
additional fields to our tables and
standard sub-tables without effecting the
structure of the sub-table itself.
Now let's take a look at the data within
our table and
have a look at what field the append
structure has added.
[SOUND]
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] If we scroll to the right, you'll
see our brand new department field
has been added as though it's just a
normal field in our table.
And we can enter data into the field, just
like any other field.
[BLANK_AUDIO]