The next thing we want to look at are
include structures.
Now include structures are very similar to
append structures, but
the main difference is that include
structures are reuseable objects.
And can be linked to many other tables,
ABAP programs, dialogue programs, and
structures.
There are a few things you need to keep in
mind though with include structures.
And that is include structures must be
flat structures,
meaning they cannot contain any additional
structures within them.
And the fields within an include structure
can have a maximum length of 16
characters.
Let's dive straight in and
see how we create include structures that
get attached to our employee table.
So whereas we had an append structure
button that we used for
append structures, we don't have an
include structure button.
So the first thing we need to do is make
sure we are in change mode.
Oh, one little thing.
I don't know if you noticed but because
we're in display mode here,
when we appended our append structure from
the previous video,
all we saw was this one append line.
We didn't see the actual field within the
append structure.
This is some quirk within SAP that when
you're in display mode,
you can see the field, but when you switch
back to change mode, it disappears.
Don't ask me the logic, I don't know why.
So anyway, what we want to do is create
our include.
And before we do it, just a quick note
that it's
important where you place your cursor when
we do this.
Because wherever your place your cursor on
your table,
the include will be inserted one row
above.
So if we add our cursor here on surname.
The include, would be between surname and
the employee field.
[SOUND] So why is that important?
Well if you wanted your include structure
to be part of the table key,
you have to make sure it appears at the
top of the table.
Because all table fields used as a table
key
need to be grouped together at the top of
your table.
But in our case, let's just insert it
above our append structure.
So I'm gonna place my cursor on the append
structure row,
then go to the edit menu, and then include
insert.
And remembering to use our customer name
space, we use Zed, and
we'll call this Z-E-M-P L for good luck.
Click the green continue tick and then we
get a warning message
just saying it's not active, well we know
that because we're just creating it.
And the green tick again.
And then we can see your include structure
has been inserted between the append and
the e-currency field.
So now let's go out to field to our
enclosed structure.
Let's just double-click it, use forward
navigation,
and we'll choose yes to save our table.
Yes to create the structure.
And then we have a screen very similar to
the append structure.
So just like before, let's key in a short
text,
and then we'll create individual fields.
Let's just create one field, and let's
call this location.
[SOUND] Oh.
I forgot, remember customer names based
on, we'll use ZZ to indicate it's not part
of our original table.
And we'll use ZLOCAT for the component.
And we'll use the forward navigation to
create the data element.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And again we'll keep it very simple and
use a ten character field.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So there we have our field added to the
include.
Let's activate the include, then step back
to our table.
And there we can see our include is set
there just above the append structure.
Our table is inactive, so once again,
activate our table and now we're good to
go.
We can use it however we wish.
So let's just view the table, view the
contents,
and hopefully we'll see the additional
field.
Here we go, inserted before the field in
our append structure.
And as you can see, it looks just like any
other field, and can be treated as so.
So what we'll do, let's edit a few records
just so we've got some data in there.
Department IT, of course.
Save the record.
Another one.
Hurries its time HR department.
Oh, I did say I was gonna use codes,
didn't I?
Nevermind lets stick with this [LAUGH] as
long as
we keep it below ten characters we'll be
fine.
So we scroll along we, there we can see
the data has been added to each record.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And if I flip back and just go to display
mode,
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] Sorry come back out and then go
into display.
There we can see the fields in a different
color, location which is
part of the include, and department part
of the append structure.
And as I've just done that, I've just
remembered one thing.
I've told you that there's this anomaly
with the fields for
the include and the append.
Not displaying in change view.
I seem to remember if you click on the row
with your include,
and then come up to the expand include
button, there we go, it shows it.
Shows you how long it is since I've
[LAUGH] I've used a, and
the same with the append structure.
Still, its a little strange why they don't
expand them by default, but there we go