Now I want to discuss key fields in a
little more detail.
If we want to add fields or take fields
away that are key fields, then we need to
take into consideration exactly what will
be going on in the database itself.
Up to now we have added fields to the
table included depend structures and
include structures.
But the system actually applies these
changes to the ABAP dictionary,
not the underlying database.
When we adjust any key fields the system
has to apply changes to the underlying
database itself.
And you need to think about this.
If you've got data in your table and
you're changing key fields,
who knows what effect it can have.
If you're introducing a new key field and
it probably won't have a massive effect.
It will probably still allow you to at the
field, activate it, so you can go in and
add new data to the new field ensuring
that your records stay unique.
If you try and change a field from being a
key field to not a key field
then you need to put your thinking cap on.
Because if you've got lots of data in the
underlying database, by taking away a key
field, it could mean that you introduce
duplicate records into your table
because now your table key is not as
unique as before.
You could end up with some undesired
effects, such as corrupt data, or
records being deleted from your table.
Let's dive in and have a look at how we
can introduce new fields and
take fields away, change fields, and that
sort of thing.
So you can see we've got the employee's
table here that we've been working with.
And what we will do is turn our surname
field into a key field.
And it's quite simple.
We just click the little tick to say it's
a key field.
And we might as well click the initial
values field as well.
And then we just need to activate.
[SOUND] It's activated fine.
We can view our data
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] And now you see the changing color
for surname, indicating it's a key field.
All our records are still the same, we
know they're unique,
so nothing much has happened.
[SOUND] But now, let's take away this key
field.
We'll still keep it in the table, but
we'll say it's not part of the key.
Now the system doesn't know what records
are in the table right now, so
when we try to activate it, we should get
some error messages warning us that,
hey, you're removing a field that was part
of the key, and
you could have some, you know, undesired
effects happening to the data.
So we'll activate, and truly know if we
got an error message
indicating that the old key had surname in
it, but now it doesn't.
And this is, this is not just a warning,
you know, it's an error.
It's telling us No, I'm not gonna activate
the table for
you because you may lose some data.
So how do we get around this?
We know that the data in our table is
actually gonna be okay.
So we want to allow this but you know, the
tool's saying we can't.
And that's why we need to open up a
different transaction.
So we can either open up a new session, or
go direct to the transaction we want,
which is SE14 from this screen.
Let's do that.
Utilities, then choose database utility.
When this screen appears, just keep in
mind that in a production environment,
you may be dealing with a table with
millions of records, and
you wouldn't want to execute this
transaction on a table of that size with
a processing time of direct,
which means it's going to run while your
screen is, is present right now.
It'd be best to run this program in the
background.
But for us, we know our table is super
small, so we can just
run the process in the foreground and it
should get done within seconds.
So all we need to do is click the Activate
and adjust database with save data.
Request adjust, we'll choose Yes.
And there we can see it's run
successfully.
So now if we step back our table has now
been activated.
We can view our data and
our surname field is back to how it was
before we made it a key field.
So that's it for key fields, really.
There's just one more thing I forgot to
mention, and that's these buttons up here.
If you did want to insert a new field as
part of your table key,
then you need to be able to adjust the
location of the fields on the screen.
So, let's say we wanted to insert a new
field above the surname field.
We would highlight the surname field and
then choose the insert button.
It moves everything down one, and we can
add our new field.
I'll remove it.
Let's say we wanted to move title as part
of the key, we can highlight it.
And then we have the cut, copy, and paste
buttons up here, so I can just use cut and
then paste.
You get the idea and that's it for table
keys.
Just so I don't screw this table up.
Let me exit out without saving.
Now go back in just to make sure
everything is good.
Yeah it's back how it was all active