Let's now take a look at deleting fields
from your table.
It doesn't happen very often,
but there may be instances where you need
to remove a field from a table.
And when you do this,
you must take special care, because you
run the risk of losing data.
So first of all, we've been looking at Key
Field.
So, if we start with those, and
you'll probably know that if we remove a
Key Field from our
table that contains data, it is more than
likely you'll end up losing records.
Because, the fields that make up your
table key, make each record unique.
Taking away a field from the key, can
result in non-unique records.
So, once the table is adjusted, some
records will be deleted.
SAP systems are very, very large systems,
and
tables are used all over the system for
various needs.
We've already seen how we can use the
Currency Check Table,
to bring up a list of values that we use
to enter data into our Employees Table.
Well, if that table was removed, then our
drop down would no longer work.
And it will highly likely inactivate our
table,
because our table uses components of that
currency table.
So, whenever you're working with a table,
and
you're thinking of deleting fields, keep
in mind, ask yourself some questions.
I this table being used as a check table,
for some other tables in this system?
And if so, how's it going to affect those
tables?
Now, if you do try and
delete fields from your table that are
being used elsewhere in the system,
your SAP system itself should stop you
from actually making the deletion.
Or at least give you a warning.
But, don't rely on that, always check
yourself.
And one final thing to remember is that if
you delete fields from your table,
you need to remember to convert your table
using the SE-14 transaction.
The Table Utilities so that the data is
adjusted and the table is made active.
So, let's go through an example of how we
delete fields, and
we will use the Z Employees2 Table.
So, I will go into Change mode, and first
of all I'll just create a field,
I will insert a field before this Include.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And let's call it zawesome.
Don't worry, we're gonna delete this one.
And let's just use a data element, that
we've already set up.
Let's use that title and press Enter.
And you can see it brings across the the
Title attributes.
We'll Activate the table.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then we'll go and enter some data.
So, let's start in the the 10 number
range.
And I'm just going to key in any old
gibberish here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And click Save.
So I'll come back out.
And we'll just have a view of the table,
to make sure the record has been added
successfully.
And there it is, and we can see the data
we entered into the record.
That looks fine.
So now to delete this, we'll click on the
Field,
click the Delete button, and then we will
Activate the table.
So, as you can see the system is
displaying an error,
which we'll take a look at.
Is telling us the table was not activated,
because we deleted the z_awesome field.
So, as I said before, we have to go to
transaction SE-14 and
adjust the table and this will have the
result of losing some data.
So utilities, database utilities.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Going to process it in the foreground, and
we will activate and adjust the database.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
That's done successfully, so back to the
table where we'll view our data.
There's our record.
And as we can see, our field has been
removed, and
we have lost that data from that field.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now, let's see what happens when we delete
a Key Field?
And to do this, I'm going to duplicate
this table.
Just so that we don't affect the current
one, and don't lose all the records.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, we'll create a New Table.
Give this a fix of three.
It's new so
we need to activate it, and the table
should be empty, which it is.
You can also press this number of entries,
and
it'll bring up a dialogue box telling you
there's no records.
So, let's go and enter some records.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Oh, actually,
I'm jumping the gun.
Let's go add another field to the Table
Key.
So, what we will do, is make Surname a key
field.
Come into Change mode.
Make it a key field, activate.
And, remember, we've got no records in the
table now, so
it's activated successfully, no problem.
And now we will go in and enter some
records.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Click Save.
And now, just to do this nice and quick,
I'm just gonna overwrite, keeping the same
sort of data here.
We will keep the Surname Smith.
Tell you what, let's do it this way.
We will keep Employee Number 1.
But because Surname is part of the key,
all we need to do is make this unique, for
us to have a unique record in the table.
So, we will create Smith 2 and leave
everything else as it is.
New Employee Number 2 suffix.
The Surname as Andrews.
Save on as this.
Same thing, leave it as 2.
And we'll do Andrews 2.
Entirely different with a dash.
And click Save.
So, I'll come back out.
Then we'll view the data.
So, we have four records, Smith, Smith-2,
Andrews, Andrews-2.
And we can see our Smiths have the same
employee number, and so do the Andrews.
So now, what we will do is remove the
Surname field,
and we will see what effect that has on
our data?
Because by removing the Surname field, the
only unique key we have is the Clients and
Employee Number, and that would leave us
with duplicate records,
which is not allowed.
So back to the table, let's delete the
field.
I will activate it, and we should be
showing some errors.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we can see the system is just telling
us, the table is not active,
because we have removed the Surname field.
So we will go to the Utilities,
and choose to Activate and
Adjust the Database.
That's been done successfully.
So, now what do you think the effect is on
the table?
Let's have a look.
So there you go.
You can see.
The system has actually removed two of the
records, because we would have been
left with duplicate records, according to
the table key.
And the system has kept the first record
that it encountered.
The second record has been deleted.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So just to summarize, be very, very
careful when deleting fields both, because
you can lose data and your table and
fields could be used as reference fields.
And check tables for other database tables
in your SAP system.