Now we're going to take a look at deleting
complete database tables themselves.
I mentioned when we covered deleting
fields that you don't often have to do
that task, and when we talk about deleting
tables, but that's even more infrequent.
But you may have this requirement so let's
go through it so
we can understand the process.
First thing is,
you will only be allowed to delete your
own customer-specific tables.
You will not be allowed to delete SAP
delivered tables.
Now because we have just created this
ZEMPLOYEES3 table,
we will use this in our example for
deleting the table.
But before that I just want to show you a
technique for checking that everything is
okay for you to delete the table, and you
will not affect other parts of the system.
So what I'm gonna do is go back to our
ZEMPLOYEES1 table.
Because we have included this table in the
ABAP programs we have created so far.
So what I have done, I've keyed in
ZEMPLOYEES1, I'll choose Display.
No.
it looks like, that's the wrong one, must
be ZEMPLOYEES.
There we go, and we'll step back.
And now what I'm gonna do, is go to this
button up here, the Where-Used button.
Now this is really, really handy tool,
that you will become familiar with, and
you will use an awful lot whilst you are
developing, testing,
and just reading ABAP programs.
So if we click the button, the system then
brings up a dialog box
where we go through and choose the objects
we want to look through.
So what this is going to do is check all
the different types of objects that
we have in our system that we select.
For a reference to our table is
ZEMPLOYEES.
Now, we know we have only used this table
in a program before, but
with other tables you may not have that
background knowledge.
So you may want to go through, have a look
at objects such as structures,
database tables, views, and so on, and to
execute it, just click the green tick.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Get a little pop-up, Where-Used Include,
Fields of the Table.
We just choose Yes.
So the system's going away and checking
all of the different objects
that we have selected to find references
to our table.
And there it's come back and
it's shown us, we have two programs that
are using this table.
So immediately we know that if we delete
this table
these programs are gonna become inactive.
They're not going to work anymore.
If you want to look at the specific code
in the table,
all you need to do is double-click.
So by double-clicking on this entry it's
then showing the snippets of code
in our program where the table is used.
And we can see we have lots of selects and
write statements.
And once again, we can double-click on any
one of these lines,
and actually jump straight into the
program.
There we go, and it takes us to the exact
location that we double-clicked on.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Program down here.
Exactly the same thing,
we can double-click and go have a look at
the program.
So this Where-Used button is a very useful
tool, and
I suggest you get used to using it,
because it saves you an awful lot of time.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now, if we try to delete this table now
the system will not let us do
it because we have objects that dependent
on it.
So what you would have to do is find those
programs, take some course of action to
either edit the code, take out references
to the table or remove the programs
completely before you could then come back
and delete this table.
So what we will do is change the table
name.
And we'll use the ZEMPLOYEES3 table that
we created in the previous videos.
And we will choose to delete this table.
As you can see we're presented with a
message box telling us the table contains
data, and we know this, but we just want
to delete the table anyway.
If you click the green tick button, we
will be taken back to the previous screen,
and the table would not be deleted, but
if you click the little trash can, the
table will get deleted.
And there we have the confirmation message
at the bottom,
saying the table was removed.
If we try and display it, we can see it
does not exist.
Now one final note, is that now we've
deleted the table,
we cannot undo this process.
The table is gone completely.
So before you click that trash can button,
make sure you do want to delete the table.