It's now time to take a look at one of the
most important elements of an ABAP program
and that's dealing with internal tables.
Now you've already covered tables in the
ABAP dictionary.
And we've sort of hinted at internal
tables throughout this course but
we haven't really dug deep into what they
are.
How we use them under syntax and that's
what we're gonna do right now.
If you were planning on writing any ABAP
programs at all or
reading ABAP programs and really
understanding them.
You've got to understand internal tables
because just about every program uses
them.
You have to learn both the old method of
using internal table with header lines
as well as the newer method of using
separate work areas.
Why do we have to learn both?
Well, SAP has been around a long time and
there are still a lot of programs
in the system that use the old method of
using header lines with internal tables.
So when you're trying to recode, you've
got to understand how they work.
But when you're creating your own code,
you want to use the newer method of
creating separate work areas.
And this will also make it easier when you
move on to understanding ABAP objects.
Now, internal tables only ever exist when
your program is running.
They're internal to a running program
only.
When you write your ABAP program, you've
specified the structure for
an internal table and you write your
program to make use of it.
And once your program finishes using the
internal table, it is then destroyed.
When you start to use internal tables in
your programs you will see that they
behave exactly the same way as structures
that you define in your program.
And these structures are called work
areas.
The only difference is that your
structures have only one line
whereas an internal table can have an
unlimited number of lines
just like a normal database table.
So let's ask ourselves what is the use an
internal table.
Well, internal tables are used for an
awful lot of things in our programs.
They allow us to hold results of
calculations that we
can use later on in our program.
They allow us to hold records of data that
we can access really,
really quickly instead of having to read
data from database tables over and
over again and a whole host of other
reasons.
And eternal tables are really flexible
because they can be defined
using any number of other defined
structures.
This allows you to have many normal table
structures, grouped together and
placed into one internal table.
If you're familiar with other programming
languages
think of multi-dimensional arrays.
You will see as we work with internal
tables that the basic form
consists of a table body which is all the
records within the table.
And then we have a header record.
Now remember, the header record means
we're working with the older
style internal table.
But for the newer style, we would have the
table body in a separate work area.
Defined exactly the same structure as the
table but it is kept separate and
works separately.
Now flipping back to the older method, the
header line or
work area is used when we read individual
records from our internal tables.
And what do I mean by this?
Well, when we read a record for the older
style table
that record gets placed into the header
record which we can access directly.
For the newer style table, we read a
record into a work area.
Very similar to a header record but
remember it's separate.
And also when we want to add records to an
internal table the older style,
we placed the content into the header
area.
For the newer style, we place content into
work area and
then we transfer the header record or work
area
into the body of the internal table which
results in us creating a new record.
During this course, we have introduced the
table statement which we
used to declare an ABAP dictionary data
table that we wanted to work with.
Now, internal tables are a little bit
different,
in that we have to declare the internal
table ourself.
And whilst we do this, we must declare
if we want to use a header line as our
work area or a separate work area.
As I've mentioned before, you'll find that
old SAP programs often use a header line
with their internal tables but today it's
best practice to use a separate work area.
You see, using a header line has several
restrictions and when
SAP introduced the possibility to work
with internal tables without header lines.
By using our own work areas we were given
the ability to create
multi-dimensional tables.
Which as I mentioned before with the multi
dimensional rays,
it's just tables within tables.
Now we're not gonna dig that deep into
multi-dimensional tables in this course
but just bare in mind it can be done and
you'll find it used an awful lot.
Now, I mentioned earlier that internal
tables can have
an unlimited number of records.
Well, I told a bit of a white lie there.
There are some restrictions, the
architecture of a SAP system
limits the size of our internal tables to
around two gigabytes in size.
You will also need to bear in mind, just
how powerful your specific SAP system is,
you know take into account the hardware,
the operating system, the amount of memory
there is, and so on.
Now even though we can create internal
tables up to two gigabytes in size,
it's best practice to keep them as small
as possible.
Because if you have multiple programs
taking up so much memory in your system,
you'll run the risk of making your whole
system run really, really slow.
And the last thing you want is a basis
guy, coming up to you saying,
why is your program taking up so much
memory?
You're causing everybody else's programs
to run really slow.
The last thing you want is users
complaining because then you start
getting some earache.