Now, I mentioned earlier that internal
tables are made up of a table body, and
either a header line or a work area.
But from now on, just assume we are
talking about the newer style,
internal table.
And that's an internal table, with a work
area.
As a nice, simple example, an internal
table can be made up of just a number
of individual fields, that correspond to
different columns of a table.
Just like when you created the data
dictionary table,
you created the individual fields.
And if you recall, when we set up that
table, we also identified, key fields.
Or the same thing can apply for
internal tables, but, we have a little bit
more flexibility.
When we declared our table in the ABAP
dictionary, we had to use key fields,
to uniquely identify every record in the
table.
Table.
Internal tables are a little bit
different.
As well as identifying unique records, you
can also specify a non-unique key.
This allows us to store any number of
non-unique records.
So, what I mean is, a unique key will
specify an individual record in our table,
that can only appear once.
But a non-unique key allows us to have any
number of duplicate records we want.
The differences don't just stop there.
We can define, different types of internal
tables too.
And this is mainly so
we can access our data, in the most
efficient manner possible.
What I mean is really, really fast.
So, first of all, we have standard tables.
Now, a standard table, gives us the option
of accessing the records,
using a table key or an index.
I'll show you how to define table keys and
indexes, in a little while.
When we access records using a key in a
standard table, the larger
the internal table is, the longer it will
take to read the records we want, and
this is why, we have the option of using a
table index.
Standard tables don't give the option of
defining a unique key.
Which resorts in the possibility of having
identical lines appearing many times
throughout your table.
Now, as I just mentioned previously,
we don't have to have unique records in
our table.
So, a standard table can hold, any number
of records, that have identical lines.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now, although accessing records using a
table key, can take a fair amount of time,
for the standard table with lots of
records, there is a flip side,
in that a standard table can be filled
with records, very, very quickly.
Because the system doesn't have to check
the table key for any duplicate records.
And you'll find that when looking at
programs and
creating your own, standard tables are
really easy to define and work with.
And you will see that they are the most
often used table type within SAP
system programs.
Now, next up, we come to sorted tables.
Now, as you might guess with a sorted
table, we can define a unique key.
This means we can force all records to be
unique in the internal table.
Thus removing any duplication of records.
And like a standard table, we can access
records,
of a sorted table, using the table key, or
using the table index.
Another commonality with standard tables,
is that you can use the table key
to find records, and with standard tables,
I mentioned this can be quite slow,
the bigger your table gets, well the same
sort of thing applies with sorted tables.
But, I must say the performance is a lot
better.
But it still, it's not the best we can
get.
Now, it is preferable to use a sorted
table over a standard table.
One because of the increased speed in
accessing records, but
also because a sorted table, sorts your
records into a specific sequence.
It gives you a performance increase, when
accessing the data.
Now, the final internal table I want to
discuss, is a hashed table.
And hashed tables, do differ from standard
and sorted tables.
In that you do not access the records of a
hash table, using an index.
You will only use a unique key.
Hashed tables, are normally the preferred
internal table, when it comes to speed.
Now, this isn't always the case, but
generally it is.
When you think your internal table is
going to get quite large,
a hash table normally gives you the best
bang for your buck.
And I recommend you use hash tables
whenever you
think you're going to have large internal
tables.
See, these types of tables, use what's
known as a special hash algorithm,
to ensure the response times of reading
records, are maintained,
no matter how many rows of data, your
table contains.
They really are super fast.
Now saying that, you will find that
standard tables and
sorted tables, are used way more, in SAP
programs, than hashed tables.
And because of that reason, we'll stick
with standard unsorted tables,
going forward.