Before we move on to looking at how we
actually create internal tables, you know,
the specific syntax, I want to spend a few
moments regarding best practices.
SAP has been around for
a long time, and as such, there are many
programs that exist.
In the current version of SAP software
that themselves have been around for
many years and conform to using the older
style of internal tables in their code.
When you create your own programs, please
use the newer style.
This will ensure your programs will be
able to be used well into the future.
This does not mean you cant use the older
way of programming.
But if you have a choice, why not use the
newest syntax.
Because everything SAP is developing right
now and
in the future, we will use the newer
object oriented syntax.
And as we work through how to create
internal tables,
I will cover both the old and the new
style of coding, so
that you are familiar with how ABAP has
changed over the years.
And this will enable you to recognize the
old and
new style of coding in the programs that
you come into contact with.
Now that's enough of that.
Let's crack on and have a look at some
code.
[BLANK_AUDIO]