I've created a new
program that we will use
to take a look at how we use
internal tables in our programs.
Now you will already be
familiar with a data statement
that we use to declare fields, but
we use exactly the same statement when
we want to declare internal tables.
Now when we declare internal tables, we
have to define the start of the table and
the end of the table.
So let's have a look at how we do this.
So we start with the data statements, and
then we use the BEGIN OF addition,
and then we specify the table name.
I'm going to use ITAB01.
You will see ITAB
being used as a temporary table
name all throughout SAP programs.
ITAB01, and
then we have to have an occurs addition.
Followed by a numeric.
So what this does,
is the BEGIN OF means we are starting
the definition of something, and
then we specify what we are declaring.
So this is going to be an internal table,
and I've named it ITAB01.
Now the OCCURS clause, are pretty, too.
Now the OCCURS clause tells SAP we
are declaring an internal table,
and we are declaring an internal
table with zero records.
So OCCURS means this table is going
to be made up of a number of records,
but we are going to define
zero to begin with.
And then let the table expand
as we fill it with data.
So, I key in the rest of
our table definition.
Now, I'll create a field called Z_SURNAME.
I'm going to make it based on the field
that we defined in our Z_EMPLOYEES table.
So first of all we specify the table name,
followed by the field name,
which I think is surname.
I'm just gonna save this and
use forward navigation just to
make sure I'm declaring it right.
Set employee surname.
Next, gonna declare date of birth.
I can use the like statements.
I do like to keep everything
lined up as well.
[LAUGH] This should have been a comma,
not full stop.
And then, what we do is specify
the end of our internal table.
So here we use end of and
then specify the table name again, ITAB01.
And that's it,
we've created the structure for
an internal table, and we can now
write code to fill it with records.
Now, as I've mentioned previously, there
are two types of declared end tables.
The old style,
where we use header records, and
the new style where we use
a separate work header.
But just by the fact that we're using this
OCCURS clause, we're telling the system
we are going to create an internal
table with a header record.
Now, just as I've completed this internal
table, I'm gonna change it, because one of
the things I did here was name our fields
in the internal table starting with a Z.
When you start to create internal tables,
you may find it useful to always make
sure your field names are identical to
the field names in other internal tables
or tables from the ABAP dictionary.
Now the reason I say this is because,
well, we've already looked
at the move statement, which allows us
to move data from one field to another.
Well there is another statement called
move-corresponding which we will use
a little later on that is used
quite often in ABAP programs.
And the reason why we use this
move-corresponding is well,
I'll give you an example.
If you want to move five fields from
table one to five fields from table two,
and both tables have same field names,
we can just write one line of code,
using this move-corresponding statement.
Which will automatically search for
any field names that are identical, and
make sure the data contained in
the table one fields are moved
to the corresponding fields for table two.
And the good thing is,
it doesn't matter if these two different
tables have a different structure.
What I mean is the fields can be
in a completely different order,
the move-corresponding works it out.
It matches the actual name
of the field together.
We will take a look at how we do
this a little later on, but for
now, just bear it in mind and
keep your field names the same.
Let's just make sure our
code is all complete.
We will check.
Yes, everything looks good.
So now we've seen how to create an old
style table with header records.
Let's have a look at how
we do the new style.
So remember,
this is the way you want to define
your internal tables moving forward,
because it complies with the new style of
coding and can be used with ABAP objects.
Which is now the standard way
in writing new programs and
you will see lots of ABAP objects code
when you dip into standard SAP programs.
And just so you know we are not going to
dip into ABAP objects programming right
now, we're just gonna concentrate on
how to declare internal tables and
structures using object
oriented techniques.
Because you will see this being
used in the majority of programs,
whether they are object
oriented programs or not.
Now for those that don't know, the whole
thing about object oriented programming
is that we want to keep each part of
our program separate from other parts,
which allows you and others to reuse
all these individual objects throughout
your program and in other programs.
So in our case,
when we create an internal table,
we need to separate out
the individual data objects.
Sort of like tiny building blocks.
We can then put these building blocks
together to create any type of
object we want.
So put another way, we're making use
of modularization and reusability
of data objects to enable us to create
new data objects later on down the line.
Okay, let's have a look at this code.
Now first off we have to define
what is called a line type.
And at first glance when, when you look
at what we're gonna do now, you may think
this is an awful lot more work than
defining a table using the old syntax.
But don't worry, it's quite simple, and
you will quickly see the benefit of using
this when you are dealing with larger,
more complex programs,
by being able to reuse your code.
So we start off with using
the types statement.
And, and think of this as We're
declaring new data types.
So, just as we have integers,
character strings.
Well, we're using types to
declare a new data type.
In our case, we're creating
structures of existing data types.
So, back to the code, TYPES.
And then,
you should be familiar with BEGIN OF.
And then, we specify our own
name to identify this line type.
So, I'm going to use line01, and
we'll put underscore typ on the end.
Then, [SOUND] I'm gonna copy and paste.
[SOUND] Now, with two fields,
exactly the same.
[SOUND] And then,
I will use END OF [SOUND]
line01_typ.
So, it looks very similar
to the old style.
[SOUND] Let's add a comma in here.
[SOUND]
In this statement, we declare the table.
So, that consists of a line,
and also saying to the system,
we're going to store
multiple lines in the table.
Or, here we just define
the structure of one line.
This does not define
the internal table yet.
We will come on to that.
Now, the first thing you'll notice is
that instead of using the data statement,
we're using the type statement.
And of course, there's no occurs edition,
because we're not defining
an internal table at this point.
We are just defining a line of a table.
We then declare our surname and
date of birth fields,
as we did with the old syntax.
And just as with the data statement,
we used the colon to tell the system we
are going to chain statements together,
so we don't have to retype
the word types all the time.
And the last line, we're saying this is
the end of our line by using the END OF.
Now, once we have defined our line,
the next step is to define our table type.
Now again, we're not quite at
the point of creating the table yet.
We're going to say,
we're going to create a type of table.
So, we're just defining
the structure of it.
[SOUND] And again,
we do this with a type statement.
Then, we declare our internal table.
So, just as we did up here.
I will declare an internal
table down here.
[SOUND] And, I'm gonna call this itab02.
Don't forget this is a type
that we are doing, so
I am sticking the underscore
typ on the end.
Then, I add TYPE STANDARD TABLE OF,
and then I specify the line type.
Line01_typ.
[SOUND] Now, again, as I've mentioned,
we've used the type statement
instead of the data statement.
We give our new type the name, itab02_typ.
And then, we follow this with the word
type to indicate we're going to define our
table based on a type that already exists,
which is this one.
Then, we include the term
STANDARD TABLE OF
to indicate we're going to
create a standard table type.
And remember, a standard table can
have multiple identical records.
Meaning, we have no unique key.
So, that means we don't have
to include any unique key
in this table type definition.
We just need to declare it just as we did.
Also in the old statement,
we use the occurs clause
up here to define the initial
size of our table.
And we used zero,
which meant really we don't know
how big the table is going to be.
So, just leave it up to
the system to determine it.
But in this new style, using the types,
instead of using the occurs clause,
we can add [SOUND]
initial size, and
then we can give it a number.
So, it could be zero.
But, this is completely optional,
and if you don't know the exact size
of the table you are creating,
you can just leave this off.
And actually,
you'll very rarely see this in programs.
So, just leave your statement like this.
And lastly,
let's also consider how we can create
a sorted table type instead
of a standard table type.
Now before moving on from this statement,
let's also consider how we can create
a sorted table type instead
of a standard table type.
Well, we can do this by a,
I'll tell you what, I'll just copy this,
this line, so you can see the difference.
So, where we have our type defined,
we just go past the type statement, and
here we can add SORTED TABLE OF
[SOUND] line01_typ.
And then, we specify our table key.
So, because our table is made of
both surname and date of birth,
we can then say, WITH UNIQUE KEY,
and then we add the key.
So, we can put surname.
Just going to two lines, so
let's [SOUND] put it like this.
So, you can see it's very similar but
we're saying, you know,
with the proper words, we're creating a
sorted table instead of a standard table.
And because we're gonna
create a sorted table,
we need to say what we're
gonna sort the table by.
So, we're gonna say we got unique key, and
we're using the field surname
which is part of our line type.
Sorry, which is this one there.
Now, this is just an example because
we know that the table we created and
the records we have in there, we actually
have duplicate records based on surname.
So, later on, when we create a sorted
table, we will specify a unique key,
where we will use more than one field
that defines the unique record.
Just to show you how you can do that now,
all you need to do is
list the fields at the end of
the statement separated by a comma.
So because our table only exists
in two fields, in this case,
I would just say comma, field b.
Okay.
Next up, remember we have still
only declared types at this point.
So next,
we want to declare the table itself.
So, as the comment says,
we're gonna declare our table based on our
Table Type that we just declared up there.
Let's make it so it works so
we'll just comment out, the sorted table.
So up to now we have
defined the line type, and
then we have defined the table type
that is based on the line type.
But all these are just type definitions,
we've just created the blueprints
to make up a table.
We do not have an internal table yet.
So how do we do this?
Well, let's have a look at the code,
and it's really, really simple.
We use the data statement again, then
we declare now our internal table name.
Or by type, and then we specify,
tell you what, let's change this.
And then we specify the type our
table is going to be based on.
So because we've already defined
our line type and our table type,
all we need to do now is use the data
statement to say we're going
to create a new table
called itab02 that is based
on the table type we declared, itab02_typ.
And when declaring
internal tables this way,
we have the option of whether
to use a header line or not.
If you do want to use a header line,
you must specify this explicitly
in the data statement.
So it would read, let's have a look.
Data type, and then you would say,
WITH HEADER LINE.
But remember, I'm saying don't do this.
Cuz if you do, you'll not be able to use
this style of table in ABAP objects.
So the next thing to do,
let's get rid of it.
Now, we're not done quite yet.
The last thing we need to
do is define our work area.
And we will use this
work area in conjunction
with the table we've just defined.
Now before we put the code in,
just note that the work area is actually
not part of the internal table.
We have actually declared the complete
internal table now in the previous step.
But we declared our work area to
work in conjunction with the table.
Meaning we move data to our work area,
we work with it, and
then we update our table
from the work area.
Or we read data from our table into our
work area to allow us to work with it.
The work area is completely separate.
And because it is separate,
if we have multiple internal tables
with the same structure,
we can also use one work area to read and
write data to and from multiple tables.
And that's an example
of reusing your code.
So let's have a look how
we define the work area.
So once again we use the data statement.
And I am just gonna call this now,
wa, stands for work area.
And it's gonna be a work area that
we're gonna associate with itab02.
Now, the association is just in my mind,
it's not anything in the system.
So it's just, you know,
a mental association.
So I'm just gonna say, wa_itab02.
Just so I know what work area
matches what internal table.
Then we use the word type, and
then we have to specify the line type.
Well, we've already declared it, up here.
So, we can just copy and
paste, and bring it down.
And that's it.
That's how we declared our work area.
Use a data statement.
We give our work area a name.
And we specify the type as
the line type we already declared.
And that completes everything we need
to work with our internal table now.
Now I know the first statement
declaring an internal table with a header
line was only four lines of code.
And we had to actually
use seven lines of code.
To use the new style of internal table.
But believe me,
it is much better to code this way.
And just as an example, we want to
create a brand new internal table on
the same structure,
well all we need to do is this.
Itab03 using 02 as line type.
And it can go on and on,
we can create any internal tables,
all based on the same line type.
So that's how we can reuse our code.