When we read and write data to an internal
table that has a header line
we always move unread data from the header
line itself.
So what I mean hear is when we read a
record from an internal table,
the record is moved to the header line of
the internal table, and
we access the header line.
When we want to write a record to an
internal table,
we move the contents to the header line of
the internal table, and
then the header line gets appended to the
table itself.
Let's get straight on to the up up code
and
see how we can populate our internal
table.
So, at the moment, the code we have from
our previous video is not quite suitable
for this example so I'm going to probably
pause the video a little bit here,
declare a brand new internal table, and
then we'll have a look at the code.
Okay, so I've created some new code.
And you'll see it's fairly basic.
I've included a table statement to declare
the table we're going to be accessing.
And then created a brand new internal
table
with almost the same structure as our
zemployee's table.
So we have employee, surname, forename,
title, date of birth.
But I then added an extra field called LOS
which stands for
length of service which will have a
default value of three.
Something like three years.
So now let's take a look at how we fill
this internal table.
And to do this we will use a select
statement.
So we start with select.
And then, you, you can write all on one
line here, but I'm just gonna break it up
so it's little easier to see the
components of the select statements.
[BLANK]
Okay.
So let's break this down.
We have our select statements, and
the asterisk means we're gonna select all
fields.
And then we say from, and then our table
name.
And we're gonna say into, corresponding
fields of, table height number one.
So this means select all the fields from
zemployees and
move them into the corresponding fields
that match by name of our internal table.
Now, this is what's called an array fetch.
So, it picks up the records and puts them
in our table all at once.
So, before you've seen how we use the
select statement as a loop,
where it'll do one record at a time.
Well this way of using it, cuz it's all at
once, that's an array fetch.
You'll notice there's no end select
statements.
So as you can see, it's super easy to move
all the records
from our database table into our internal
table.
Now, our internal table does have an extra
field, length of service.
So what will happen here is that every
record will be filled
with a value of three.
We'll add
one more line of code, just to help with
debugging.
We're not really bothered about seeing the
output, but it will just let us
pause the code and interrogate the
internal table in the debugging session.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay, oops, I pressed the wrong button,
[LAUGH] I apologize,
then we check everything's good to
interpret, sticking to our break point.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[INAUDIBLE] Break point and now I can
click this.
So we're at the line of code, where we're
going to fill out our internal table.
So what we'll do is have a look at the
internal table first.
And we can see this hat symbol represents
a header line, and then
down here you would see all the records as
they get filled into the internal table.
But as we have yet to process this line
there's nothing there.
So I'll just step through the code one
line at a time, and
all we should need to do is execute just
this one line.
And as you can see, let me just come back
up, when we executed that, the system
did an array fetch and populated all the
records into our internal tape.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's change things around a little bit.
Now I want to introduce the append
statement.
Just to give you an idea to another way of
filling an internal table.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Take the break point off, let's change
around these select statements.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
What we will do is create a select.
We've also, because I don't like typing
much,
I'm just gonna bring in my favorite text
editor.
Oops.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
I'm gonna say move.
Z employees- field name.
Sure.
Write over one.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay, saving my fingers.
Oops, that's not where I wanted it.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Well, of course, we don't have that field
in the table, so
I'll just remove that one.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay.
So what we're doing here is a little bit
different.
Where instead of doing an array fetch,
collecting the data one record at a time,
then select loop.
So the first record will be selected and
then we have individual move statements to
move our data field by field to the
corresponding data in our internal table.
So let's activate it.
I'll stick a break point in and then we
can debug the code and
see how it works line by line.
Okay.
So I'm going to step through.
Let's bring up just I table one, and we'll
look at the complete table.
So it's executed the select statement.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And that's just held in SAP's memory at
the moment.
And now we're going to execute the
individual moves.
And as you can see, the first move moved
the value of
the employee field to the header record of
our internal table.
And so on with the other fields.
Now, one important thing is, I mentioned
before when using header records.
The system only works with header records
and
what I mean is it's filling the header
record, but there's no code to then say
append the completed record to the table
and you'll see this as we step through.
We come to the end of the select.
Start the loop again, and now all it's
gonna do is overwrite the header record.
Now this is a real common mistake made by
programmers, and
I still make it today if I'm ever using a
header record.
I'll just sometimes forget to append the
records to the table
because everything looks right.
Is just you've got this extra line of code
that you need to add to say,
move the header record to the table and
then do the loop again.
So assume through the code, come back and
then see what we need to do to complete
this.
Take off the break point.
And it's really simple.
All we need to do to get the header
records appended to the table
is add our append statement.
So just below the Moves, I will do append
I table one.
This will tell the system to take the
values from the header record and
add them into the body of the internal
table.
Let's have another quick debug so you can
see it working.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's step through again, one line at a
time.
Let's look at I tab first.
Now we get to the append statement and
you can see the record was added
to the body of the table.
And note here, the header record still
contains the values.
That's something to be aware of.
Ideally, you want to clear out the header
record
as soon as you've added your record to the
body of the table.
And also,m if we go back and look at
individual
fields of the table, and we'll take a
look,
oops, at the length of service field,
you can see the default value of three has
been appended.
So it can zoom through the program and get
back to the code.