We're now going to take a look
at the MOVE-CORRESPONDING
statement that I mentioned a little
earlier in one of the other videos.
There's not much to talk about, so let's
just get straight down to the code and
show you what it does.
So in our previous example,
we moved the individual fields to the
header record of our internal table and
then used the APPEND statement to
write that header record to the table.
Well, instead of writing
those five lines of code,
those MOVE statements,
we can just use one line.
And that's by making use
of MOVE-CORRESPONDING.
So here's how it looks.
We have the MOVE statement,
and we have dash.
And we specify the table name,
which is our zemployees table,
and we just say we want to
move it to our itab table.
And that's all there is to it, and
we can get rid of these
remaining MOVE statements.
So it matches up the technical name
of each field from the zemployees.
And where there's a matching field in
itab01, it will move the contents.
It's really simple, and
it's a real time-saving statement.
And all you need to make sure is that
the fields that you're hoping to move
are named the same between the two tables.
There is one thing to watch out for,
and that's when you use this statement,
just ensure that the fields
you are moving data to and
from do have the same data type or length.
So even though it'll
match up the field names,
it's up to you to make sure
the field type is correct.
If they do differ in any way, you could
end up with unpredictable results.
Now back to this code.
Let's stick a breakpoint on and
see it in action.
Have a look at our internal table,
and then we'll step through the code,
bang, it moves all the fields.
If we scoot up.
And I just type in the fields here.
Oops, I missed the itab.
itab01.
And you can see it's
actually moving them in.
And it's as simple as that.
And so on, I'll zoom through the program.
Let's get back to some more wrap up.