What I'm going to do now is just go
through another example.
It's the same stuff, what you've seen,
but just different ways of populating
internal tables.
So we'll go back to using an array fetch,
which means we can use the select
statement but without doing a loop.
But lots of data are transferred all
together instead of one record at a time.
And at the same time, we're gonna create a
new internal table as well.
But show you how you can create a new
internal table
using other statements [UNKNOWN].
So what I'll do,
I'll create an an itab2.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We'll keep the occur zero, but this time,
instead of specifying all the individual
fields,
I'm gonna remove those and use an include
statement.
So I'm going to say include structure of
itab01.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Yep, just one little error.
Sorry.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Ooh, two little errors, and also I need
another
data statement because I used a full stop.
Okay.
So notice here I am declaring the content
of our new internal table
using the include structure statement.
This just simply copies the structure we
declared for
itab01 one, and includes it in itab02.
We could also use the structure of a table
that we declared in the data dictionary.
For example, let's do another one.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's do itab03.
And instead of the internal table, this
time, I'm gonna say,
bring in the structure of said zed
employees, if I spell it correctly.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Using this method to declare fields of an
internal table can save additional coding,
and can be enhanced further by including
multiple table structures,
all within one single Internal table.
Let's have a look how we do that.
Let's do another one,
itab04.
So here we have the INCLUDE STRUCTURE of
zed employees.
I can then take, well, add another
INCLUDE STRUCTURE of itab01.
So you can see you can use this include
structure statements to add
various structures you have already
defined or
have already been defined in the system to
build up your own internal table.
Now this, I guess, isn't a great example
because we actually have
employee defined in both of our
structures.
So, you know, make sure your field names
are unique, but you get the idea.
You can just continue adding more
structures.
Or, if you wish, include some more data
statements,
such as employee count of type integer.
Using these techniques you can build any
internal table you want,
and at the same time reuse your own code.
Now let's keep things simple for now.
So we'll remove some of these internal
tables that we created and
stick to our original one.
Now, I'll tell you what we'll do.
We'll go back to the array fetch and
that's the depopulating tables by taking
away this move corresponding.
Well, I'll tell you what, I'll give up
typing
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Here we go.
And notice I'm deleting the append and the
unselect.
It would help if we could spell fields
correctly.
So what I wanna do is just, I want to run
through this again,
because this is quite an efficient method
of filling your internal tables.
You see, using an array fetch,
we are not populating our table line by
line and we are taking away
the loop generated by the select statement
and the end select statement.
Instead, this select statement selects all
the fields from our data dictionary table,
and moves only the fields that correspond
from that table to the fields in the new
internal table.
This type of select statement is much much
faster than using a loop.
And also, now take note that we did not
make use of any header record here.
There was no need to use it,
because we used a block by block array
fetch method to fill our table.
I'll also mention that you can identify
the individual fields you want to move
from your source table instead of using
the asterisk that represents every field.
So for example,
where we have the asterisk, we could then
write out the field names.
Surname, forename, date of birth, et
cetera.
[SOUND]