We will now switch tact and
have a look at how all this works
where we want to use a work
area instead of a header line.
The fundamental difference is that when
we are selecting records from the table,
we are using the separate work area,
instead of using the internal
table's own header line.
Let's go straight to look at some code.
So, what I'm gonna do is define
a brand new internal table.
And found, let me clear out this stuff,
cuz further down in the program,
we got the stuff we declared before.
So, first of all as a refresher,
we have the line type and
that's made up of two fields,
surname and date of birth.
Then, let's put a space in here,
then we declare
the data type which is
made up of the line type,
followed by declaring the internal
table itself, look at this one.
So, this is the declaration
of the internal table and
finally, we declare the work area.
So with those statements in place,
let's move on and
have a look at the select
statement we would use.
It's very similar to how we
define the select statement for
working with an internal
table with a header line.
And then,
we start with a select statement.
And then, what I'm gonna do here
is specify individual fields,
so I'm gonna say surname and
date of birth.
Then we use from to say where
we're gonna select it from, and
we're gonna specify the employees table,
and
I'll just break the statement
onto a brand new line.
Then, we're gonna use into, and
this is where we specify the work area.
So, because our work area is wa_itab02,
that's what I'm going to input.
Now, I'm going to add an append statement
and this is where I'm going to do wa.
So, let's check the code.
That looks good.
So, now let's explain it for you.
So, we have our normal SELECT statement.
We specify it is going into our work area.
Then, we have our APPEND statement and
we're gonna say append the record from
the word carrier to our internal table.
Then, this section of code is ended
with the ENDSELECT to complete the loop.
Let's debug the code and
you can see it in action.
Oops, not active.
Okay.
So, here we go.
There's our work area.
There's our internal table,
and I'll step through,
line by line,
Work area is filled, and then,
we append it to the internal tape,
and then the loop continues.
Now zoom through, fairly simple stuff.
In some of our previous examples,
we looked at using an array fetch, which
in essence, skipped the header record.
Well, the same thing applies here.
Even though we're using an internal
table a without header record,
we can still take a look
at the same type of code.
And see how it works
with this type of table.
So, let's comment out this.
And let's now just code
a simple array fetch.
So, we would have the select statement.
Let's choose all fields.
So select star from zemployees
into corresponding fields
of our table, which is itab02.
We don't need the APPEND or the ENDSELECT.
So, as you can see, an array fetch
works exactly the same as before.
And we can test it out.
Let's first stick a break point in.
It's going to zoom straight through, but
we can see that the internal
table is empty at the moment.
As soon as I press F5,
the program is going to end,
but on the F5 press, the internal
table will be filled with data.
I guess what we need to show that is
then just create a bit of code, and
we will come to loops later on,
so don't worry about that.
Now, let's test it again.
Have a look at itab02.
Press F5, and
you can see we got five records
inserted into the table, all in one go.
So, I'll just zoom through
the rest of the program.
We don't really need to
look at this output.
And get rid of the break points.