So we have learned how to create and fill
a standard internal table.
Let's have a look at how we would use that
data line by line.
Now, our internal tables are just tables
that are held in memory, and
similar in many respects as tables that
were held in a database.
So, let's take a look at how we can read
through the records of an internal table
line by line using a loop.
The way we access the records of an
internal table,
is different to how we access records of a
standard about dictionary table.
Instead of using the select statement, we
will use the Loop and End Loop statements.
The loop and end loop statements are very
similar to the Select and
End Select statements in that we start our
record selection with a loop.
Include any ABAP code we want inside the
loop
to process the records that we have
selected.
And then we end our loop with the End Loop
statement.
So, let's take a look at how this works
with an internal table that has a header
line.
Now, I'll change the screen
to bring up the header line examples we've
used in previous videos.
Okay, we have our original example where
we were using the Select statements,
using the Append statements to add the
records to the internal table.
And then we do have a Write statement just
to help with debugging.
But I'm gonna remove that.
So let's have a look at how we would write
this Loop statement.
And it's very simple, we will start with a
loop.
We say we're looping at our internal
table, which is itab01.
We then add code inside our loop, to do
whatever we want.
Maybe updating records in another table,
or writing out to the screen, and
so on, or maybe just performing
calculations.
And then once that's done, we have the End
Loop.
So when we access records of an internal
table using a header line,
each record gets transferred one record at
a time from
the body of the internal table into the
header line,
so that we can then work with the header
line to do what we want.
As you can see, it's very simple and easy
to understand.
So now we have our loop.
Let's fill some code in.
Just here.
So that we do something with the data.
So we're just gonna write it out to the
screen.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And it's as simple as that.
Let's pretty it up.
So as you can it is very similar to how we
have
used the Select statements a little higher
up.
We select our records.
We process the data.
And then we finished the Select.
Let's have a quick look in a debug session
to see how the header line gets filled and
used within our loop.
So, we'll activate the code, stick the
break points on, and execute.
So the Select statement has already been
processed.
As you can see, we have,
let's see, five records, and
you can see the header line has still got
the fifth record already populated.
But when we process our Loop statement, we
start to loop through with the table
one record at a time, starting at the
first record, and
what will happen is this record will get
copied to the header line.
And then we access the header line with
our Write statement,
to write the individual fields out to the
screen.
Let's go one line at a time.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So as you can see, the first record is
being copied to the header line.
And when we have statements to work with
this type of table,
they will always access the header record.
Have a look at the screen, Amy Jones.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And so on, I'll zoom through, there's the
output.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Real simple stuff.