[BLANK_AUDIO]
So we've looked at how we can loop through
an internal table.
Now let's have a look at how we can update
the records in the internal table
using the modify statements.
I will add in some code, and
whilst I'm writing it see if you can work
out how it all fits together.
It's fairly simple.
And then we'll go over it line by line.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay, very simple change.
You can see I've included an if statement
and also a modify statement.
The if statement allows us to determine if
the employee surname is equal to Jones.
If it is, we are going to [UNKNOWN] date,
with the surname of Smith.Then we have an
endif statement.
In fact, let me change this code.
That shouldn't be there.
It should be there.
There we go.
So if the if statement is true, we then
have the modify statement.
Which will take the contents of the
headline that we have just updated and
update the record in the internal table
that
was originally read into the head record.
Now, the modify statement has some
specific features
when used inside the loop for an internal
table.
So in our case, modify statement only
changes the contents of the existing line
in the internal table that we have read.
It does not create a brand new record.
If the modify statement is in a loop,
it is always the current line that is
changed.
But please note, you should not do this
if you are trying to modify key fields of
an internal table that use a unique key.
If the modified statement is used outside
of a loop, we must specify the record
index number that we want to modify,
because we have got no index number being
monitored by the system automatically like
when we have our code inside a loop.
Now a little note is the way we use the
modify statements in our example here,
we can only it this way with index tables
and tables with header lines.