Let's continue on with this example where
we have modified the table.
And, I want to introduce a new statement
called describe table.
A describe statement can be used to find
out information about the content
of an internal table.
This includes the number of records the
table holds,
the reserve memory space used, and the
type of table,
if it's a standard table, sorted table, or
a hash table.
But in the years I've been using ABAP,
I've only ever seen this statement
used to find out how many records exist in
the internal table.
So let's concentrate on that one.
Now the way we do this is very simple.
We just type describe table, which is the
actual statement,
followed by our internal table, which in
this case is itab01.
Then we want to know the number of
records.
So what we do is use the addition of
lines.
Then we have to tell the system how we
want to store this value,
so let's use a new variable called
line_cnt.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And up here I'll make sure we have a data
statement.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Called line_cnt with a type i.
So, this statement will return an integer
value
that represents the number of lines
contained in our internal table,
and the value will be stored in the
variable we defined.
So, why would you want to know this?
Well, we have covered the append statement
in a previous module.
So you should know that the append
statement only adds lines
to the end of a table.
Now instead of using append, we could use
the insert statement.
And the insert statement allows us to
insert records into any position
we choose inside an internal table, by
specifying the table index number.
If we wanted to insert a record into an
internal table,
record number ten for example, we will
specify index ten,
which would then insert our new record
between the ninth and tenth record.
And we would do this, simply like this.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We declare the INSERT statement, internal
table, we're going to insert record into.
Then we specify the index number of the
record that we want to insert our
new record into.
And this is where we can use our line_cnt
which holds,
in this case, the total number of records
in our table.
Therefore, the result of these two
statements that describe an insert,
in this case,
the system will insert a record before the
last record in the internal table.
So like I said, if there's ten records,
line_cnt will hold a value of ten.
The new record is inserted between the
ninth and tenth record, and
that's why our new record will be inserted
one record before the end of the table.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay, now I've got those [LAUGH] bugs out
of the way.
I'm just going to edit this a little bit,
so this program makes a bit more sense.
What I'm going to do is move this loop to
finish here,
and once we've gone through every record,
we'll then come on to these two
statements.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So I'm gonna set a break point.
And we'll debug it and see how all this
works.
So we've looped through itab.
I'll double-click it and you can see we
have five records still.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And if we have a look at the value of
line_cnt right now, it's 0.
So we'll execute this row of code.
Now it's telling us we have 5 records.
Then we come to the INSERT statement, and
if I flick back to itab01,
we'll just scroll down, so we can see what
happens here.
Now remember, our header record has this
value in it, 1, lots of 0s, and 6.
And this is a standard table, so we are
allowed duplicates.
So when the INSERT statement gets
executed,
hopefully it's going to insert a line
right here.
Now it's gonna be difficult to see because
[LAUGH] the record's
exactly the same as the fifth one.
So what I'm gonna do, is change this
header record.
I'm going to change the value of some of
the fields just a little bit, so
that you can see the record being
inserted.
So, I'll change employee number.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Oops, to seven.
Oops, I pressed the wrong one, by the
looks of things.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
There we go.
And let's change surname.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
To Stevens.
Okay.
Back to the fields.
Have a look at the table.
Go to the top.
Now we can see our header record has the
1,
lots of 0s and 7, and the surname is equal
to Stevens.
So now we will insert this header record
into the table at position five,
which if you remember, is the total number
of records in our table.
So, we'll execute it.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Silly me.
I didn't have anything after
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's run it again.
Do apologize for that.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So once again, there's line_cnt.
Go one line of code down.
It now contains five records.
We'll have a look at itab01.
We'll go in and amend the header record
again, choose this one.
So, if I just come down here and
say itab01-surname,
itab01-employee.
I'll change that to BLOGS.
[COUGH] And this one I'll change to 7.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Oops.
7, there.
So if we have a look at the internal
table,
there's our header record with the new
data we've just added.
Scroll down, and then when it executes the
INSERT statement,
we should have another record inserted
here, and
this record should be moved down one
position.
There we go.
That's the INSERT statement.