The loop statement is great for looping
through all the records of our table.
But there is another statement we can
use to access the records of an internal
table.
This statement is called the read
statement,
this statement allows you to specifically
read individual records from a table.
So in our case, because we are using a
headline, when we use the read
statement the record will be read into the
header line of our internal table.
When you use the read statement in your
program,
you've got to be aware of how your
internal table has been declared
because that will affect how you write
your read statement code.
And what I mean is, what type of internal
table are you working with?
Is it a standard table, hash table, etc.
If you're working with a standard table
with a non-unique standard key,
then you would write the read statement
like this.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
Read table, and we specify the table,
which is itab01.
And we can specify the index number.
This means we're reading the fifth record
of our internal table
into our header record.
The beauty of using the read statements
is it is the fastest way to access the
records of an internal table.
And using the index specifically is the
fastest form
of this read statement itself.
This type of access is about three times
faster than using a hash algorithm,
which as I mentioned previously,
is our best-performing internal table when
dealing with lots of data.
As well as being three times faster than a
hash algorithm.
It can be up to 14 times faster than using
a normal table key.
But the problem is,
we don't always know what the index number
of the record is that we want to read.
And that's why we nearly always end up
using table keys.
So let's add an internal table to our
code.
And define some key fields as our table
key.
So the way we write a read statement is in
a table key.
[SOUND] Is again, read statement so I go
pretty top.
[BLANK AUDIO].
Okay.
We have read table and we specify our
table name.
Instead of using index and the index
number,
what we do is type with key and then we
specify our key fields.
So I'll just go onto a new line.
We'll indent it a little bit.
And because our itab01 is made up of, of
these fields up here,
we will say, our key field is employee.
So we'd say, employee, equals, and then we
specify an employee number.
Simple as that.
You're not just limited to using a unique
key.
You can use other fields as well.
But the problem there is that it is
difficult to know exactly which record
you will be reading, because let's say if
we use the surname field and
we add three people called Smith.
Well you wouldn't know which record has
been read.
Is it the first, second or third?
Well with a non-unique key,
the read statement reads sequentially
through your table.
So actually you'll get the first record
that appears in your table
that matches your key.
Again, you won't have a clue if there are
any more records
that match without adding extra code to
carry out some extra checking.
You know, such as check to see if the
record was found, if it was found,
read the next record and again, see if
that record was found.
You know, that type of thing is the only
way you'd know if there are more records
with the same key.
Now, this read statement we've just seen
can also be used for
sorted tables and hash tables.
When you specify the key fields to use in
your search.
The system will run a binary search for
sorted tables and
use a hash algorithm for hash tables.
If the fields you choose to use are not
key fields, the system will
carry out a sequential search for both the
sorted out hash tables.
[BLANK AUDIO].