Next, let's take a look at how we can
delete records from our internal table.
And it's really simple, we just use the
delete statement.
And we can use the delete statement to
remove individual records or
groups of records from our table at any
one time.
The fastest way of achieving this is by
using the table index.
Just like we did with the read statement.
But note this only applies to standard
tables and sorted tables not hash tables.
Only these two types of tables have an
index.
So let's have a look at the code.
So we start off with the word delete,
we specify our internal table, and then we
just give it an index.
It's pretty simple.
We make no use of the header line here.
Instead, we just directly address the
recording dates
of the record we want to delete in the
body of the internal table.
And with the delete statement,
we can also use it inside the loop,
they're exactly the same type of syntax.
So for example, let's copy this loop.
I'm gonna paste it out here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
What we can do, is if we have some logic
to identify a specific record,
in this case.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
If our surname equals Smith, we can then
say,
delete a record from my top 01.
We're gonna use the index, but instead of
specifying the number, we can use a system
variable called sy-index, and when we are
inside the loop,
this variable gets updated automatically
by the system, so if we are in the fifth
iteration of a loop, this variable will
contain the number five.
Which will equal the fifth record in the
table that we want to delete.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
One thing to note is that you shouldn't
use the delete
statement without the index addition.
If you went outside the loop, you will be
given a run time error,
which in turn will cause your program to
crash.
If you are inside the loop, you need to
make sure the index
addition is included to be compliant with
future releases.
The ABAP syntax.
I want to introduce the where addition to
the delete statement.
Because there are times when you don't
know the actual
index of the record that you want to
delete.
When your table has a non unique key, you
need to use some other logic, as we've
already discussed, to determine which
record or records you want to delete.
And this is where you can use the where
edition.
Now you use the where clause to construct
a logical expression
that contains the various conditions that
will help you identify the record or
records you need to delete as uniquely as
you can.
Now always try and
be as specific as possible when trying to
identify records you want to delete.
Because the last thing you want is to
delete data that
you shouldn't have deleted.
So let's have a look at the code.
It's real simple.
And what we're going to do.
Let's copy this statement here.
[UNKNOWN] down, and we'll edit it.
So we have delete, and we have the table.
But instead of using the index, we're
going to say where,
and let's use surname again, where surname
equals Smith.
You can see it's very straightforward,
and we have just included one logical
expression
that attempts to identify any records with
the surname Smith that we want to delete.
When a record is found that does match our
logical expression,
the record will be removed from the
internal table.
If the system finds multiple records,
all the records will be deleted that match
the expression.
[BLANK_AUDIO]