Our next topic is all about sorting
records in our internal table.
So it's probably not gonna be a shock to
learn that the statement
we use to sort our data is actually called
sort.
And the basic format is really, really
simple.
Let's have a look.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Well it consists of a salt and then the
table name.
As you can see the syntax is super easy
and in this case,
because we have got no additions to the
statement, our internal table
will be sorted in ascending order based on
the defined table key.
Now this works for sorted tables and hash
tables.
If we are using standard tables then you
are required to use the buy addition and
that will look like this.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We just add the word BY followed by the
fields we want.
In this case, I'm just specifying one
field and by specifying
the field name the internal name will be
salted in accordance with the contents.
Now don't forget, SAP caters for all sorts
of languages and
we need to take that into account if we're
working on programs for
a company where their systems are used
throughout the world.
So to ensure your internal table is sorted
according to language specific criteria.
Use the AS TEXT addition directly after
the name of your internal table.
So then we build up the sort statement
just a little bit more by using AS TEXT.
Now our source statement, you know,
is just using one field right now but
you're not just limited to one.
You can list up to 250 fields to use in
your source statement.
[LAUGH] I've never seen anywhere close to
that being used but
just to show how we can extend it, we can
say sort by surname and then by forename.
And note, there's no need for a comma
separator, all we do is a space and
then list our field [UNKNOWN].
Now just one extra thing is, we specified
AS TEXT
in our source statement and because of
where we placed it within the statement.
This country specific sorting is going to
be applied to all fields that we specify.
If you only want the AS TEXT edition to be
applied to specific fields,
you need to repeat this addition after
every field in your list.
So let's say we just wanted AS TEXT to
apply only to the forename.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We would remove it from this point and
then place it after our forename field.
Now let's [UNKNOWN] with the, just
a one sort of statement we have in our
example and let's discuss the sort order.
Now the default is for our sort statement
to sort our records using ascending order.
But we can if we wish specify ascending or
descending within the SORT statement
itself.
And we do this by SORT itab01 and
then this is where we would specify
ascending or descending.
So if we wanted it in reverse order,
[SOUND] we would include the word
descending.
Nice and easy.
And that's about it for the SORT
statement.
[BLANK_AUDIO]