So now we have gone through how to fill,
modify data,
delete data from our internal
tables that have a header record.
Let's now swap over and look internal
tables that don't have a header record,
the ones we want to use going forward, and
they're the ones where we
specify our own work area.
Now we're not gonna go
through every example again.
But what we will do,
is go though the differences.
So first up,
let's have a look at reading data.
When we have a loop statement,
that loops through our internal
table that uses a work area.
The loop reads each record
from our internal table,
into the work area instead
of the header line.
Now because we have the ability
to specify the work area
completely separate to our internal table,
we must specify
that work area we want to use within
our loop to read the data into.
So let me clean up this code and
have a look at some examples of using
the work area with loops and so on.
I have loaded up the code that we have
used in a previous example when looking at
work areas.
And we already specified how to
use a work area in an example but
we did not go into great detail.
So let's do that now.
So here is where we add an array fetch.
We're not too bothered
about that right now.
Let's remove it.
I'll tell you what,
no we'll keep it in because [LAUGH]
that fills out our internal table.
Let's concentrate on this
piece of code right here.
So as you can see, the standard
loop statement, we're looping our
internal table but we're going to
instead of using the hex line,
we're gonna read our records into
how our own predefined work area.
And then when we want to work with any
data that belongs to the work area,
we reference the work area directly.
So our write statement says WRITE
the surname field from our work area,
not the internal table