Now to modify records,
the modify statement again has to
reference the work area.
So, I'll bring in an example from using
the header record, than we'll modify it,
to use the work area.
So we're using iTab02 in this case.
So if the surname is Jones oops.
Sorry, I need to specify the into.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, we would then say
if_wa_iTab02surname equals Jones.
And then we would modify
the work area record to say SMITH.
And then the actual modify statement
itself would be MODIFY iTab02,
and then we would say FROM our work area.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So to summarize, we are telling the system
to modify our Internal Table
using the record we hold in our work area.