Now the Insert statement follows similar
lines.
Let me bring in the code from the header
record example.
Here we used a Describe statement
to find out how many records
in the internal table and
hold that value in line count,
which I will declare again [SOUND].
And it looks like I got the last example
wrong because I specified the work
area incorrectly.
That'll teach me to check my code.
So back to the insert,
the Describe statement holds the number of
records in the Line Count variable and
the Insert statement would say insert
a record from our work area, into our
table,
using the index position held in Line
Count.
So the syntax is a little bit different
from standard where we actually say,
first of all, insert our work area record
into our table
rather than specifying the table first
like we did with the Modify statement.
The work area is second.
[SOUND] But nonetheless it's still
relatively simple.