Let's now take a look at the restatements.
And as you can probably guess, the
restatement follows a similar logic in
that we must use our work area with our
restatements.
And if we go straight to the code, we can
have a look at how we write it.
So we would say READ TABLE and
then we specify the table we want to read,
which is itab02.
We specify the index of the record we want
to read.
But instead of leaving it there with a
full stop, we continue on to say and
store the record into
our work area.
[SOUND] Now just like in previous
examples,
quite often you do not know the index
number of the record you want to read,
so you would use the with key addition.
So the way we write that is instead of
using the index again, we do retable,
internal table which is itab02 into our
work area.
And we specify with key, and then we
specify the key we want to use.
So in our case let's use surname equals
Smith.
So just as before when we specify the work
area we want to read the record into,
the same thing happens here.
The record is transferred to our work area
based on our key to
allow us to continue with the rest of our
program.
Now I mentioned previously, when we were
discussing the read statement.
With internal tables that have headlines.
You need to keep in mind that tables
without unique keys
can have multiple records.
That match the criteria that you specify
with your read statement.
[BLANK_AUDIO]