This next topic is gonna be quite small,
and it's important that you know about it.
And this is Deleting Internal Tables.
First of all with header lines, and then
with work areas.
When working with Internal Tables, you
will see that there are many occasions
when you want to delete all the records of
the Internal Table in one go.
And this obviously depends on the specific
task you are trying to
complete with your program, and
whereabouts in the program flow you are.
As an example, if you were to fill in the
Internal Table
whilst you were inside that higher level
loop, more often than not,
you will need to make sure your table is
empty at the start of the loop.
So that when the next iteration of the
loop comes around,
you are not left with any records from the
previous iteration.
Now there's a certain sequence of tasks
that you should really adhere to,
when deleting the contents of a table with
a header line.
First, you have to make sure you clear out
the header line.
Then make sure you clear out the body of
the Internal Table.
So, let's have a look at the code and see
exactly how we would do this.
So I've loaded in one of the previous
examples, where we fill an Internal Table.
And it's very simple.
There's our Internal Table.
We have a select statement to fill in, and
a simple write statement to help with
debugging.
So now, once we've used our Internal
Table, we want to clear it out.
So first of all, clear out the header
line, and we use the clear statements.
Very simple.
And all we do is say clear, and then the
table name.
And this will clear out the header line
only.
By specifying the Internal Table after the
clear statement, the header
line will be wiped clean, meaning all
fields will be set to their initial value.
Then, to deal with the table body that
contains all your records.
We use the clear statement again but this
time,
we used two square brackets at the end of
the table name.
So what we do is this, followed by two
square brackets,
and this results in all the records from
the body of the table being deleted.
Now there is another way clearing out the
records of a table, and
that's by using the refresh statements.
And the syntax is super simple.
All we do is say Refresh and the table
name.
And by using this statement, you delete
all the records in the table,
but you still have to keep in mind your
header record still contains values.
It is untouched by the refresh statement.
So, just remember to use the clear
statement that we defined first.
Now before moving on there's actually
another statement and
this one is called the Free Statement.
And as you might guess this syntax is
super simple again,
all we do is type Free.
And then the table name.
Now, not only does this statement empty
out the records from the Internal Table,
but, it also frees up the memory being
used by your program.
It doesn't mean your Internal Table no
longer exists,
it just means that it's been emptied out
of memory.
So if you need to access the Internal
Table again,
maybe to fill it with records, then you
can do so.
It's just that the program when it does
that,
it needs to reserve the memory space
again.
So the free statement does, you know, the
same job
as the clear statement with the two square
brackets and the refresh statement.
But, it has the added benefit of emptying
out the memory used from your program,
it clears it out.
So, it releases the memory to be used by
some other process.
And just like with the other two
statements, the header line is unaffected.
So don't forget to use the clear
statement, to clear your header line.