Now let's take a look at deleting internal
tables where we are using word carriers.
Word carriers are fundamentally different
structures that we set up in our program.
Therefore when we write some code that
affects the internal table,
it will never affect the work area at the
same time.
And also, the reverse is true.
Whatever code we write that affects the
work area structure
will never affect our internal table.
When we're using internal tables with no
header lines, some of the statements
we've just been through will work a little
bit differently.
The clear statement, when used on a table
without a header line,
actually clears the whole table contents.
We saw it make sense because I specified,
make sure you clear the header line, then
you clear the table contents.
But the syntax will work a little
differently here.
So if I show you, see, if I say,
with header line here and I'll copy this
lot, and
show the differences with work area,
so here to clear out the header line
we would actually use this thing.
CLEAR then the table name.
We don't need the square brackets.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
But then, we've gotta keep in mind our
work area is separate, so
we have to clear that out as well.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So all you need to do is use the CLEAR
statement again and
then specify your work area.
Let's say our example, our work idea is
set to custodial wa_itab01.
As we make our way down to the other
statements,
here the REFRESH statements exactly the
same stuff applies.
We would have REFRESH itab01 to clear out
the table,
which is exactly the same as with the
header line.
But you've gotta remember, treat your work
area
differently because it's a different
structure in its own right.
And the same applies for FREE.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
FREE statement will clear the internal
table from memory and
then we would have to separately clear out
our work area.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now this just about wraps up what we will
cover on internal tables.
We have been through all the major key
topics that you'll need to
work with internal tables, both creating
them, filling them up, and
then destroying them afterwards.
So take some time, practice and get used
to these commands because
you will use them again, and again, and
again in the programs you create.