When we are writing our programs using
open SQL,
we need to bare in mind the concepts of
authorization in an SAP system.
Now an SAP system has its own security
tools to ensure users can only access the
data they are authorized to see.
This includes individual fields as well as
individual records.
The way authorizations are set up can also
limit how the data is used.
Whether a user can only display
information or whether they can modify
the data such as adding, changing, and
even deleting records.
And all these rules that make up a user's
authorizations
as stored as authorization objects.
Now we're not gonna dig deep into
authorizations here, but
as a general rule a user is assigned a
relevant authorization profile or
composite profile against there user
record.
Which for informational purposes is
managed through transaction SU Z01.
This authorization profile
then gives the user the correct rites to
carry out their job and SAP
delivers lots of predefined authorization
profiles with their bay system.
The system of administrators can use and
enhance to apply to their users
for example, there are standard developer
roles or HR administrator roles.
The system administrators more than likely
take these delivered
authorization profiles files, tweak them a
little bit to ensure they work
just how their company wants them to work,
and then apply them to individual users.
Once a user is assigned a role, and
tries to execute a program, depending on
the authorization role of the user,
they will be allowed to execute the
transaction or not.
And a typical example is being able to run
transaction SE38.
The ABAP editor.
A user can be given a role to allow them
to access that transaction, but
also it can be tweaked so that yeah, they
can access it, but only in display mode.
Or in a live system maybe, they can access
the transaction in display mode.
And be allowed to debug the program in the
live environment, but
not be able to make changes to the code
itself.
So coming back to our ABAP programs, where
specific authorizations have
not been implemented we can get our
programmers to carry out an authority
check using the ABAP statement authority
check.
This has to be used if the transaction or
the ABAP program itself is not
sufficiently protected
by the standard authorization profiles
already set up in the system.
Now, we won't go any further into
authorization checking in this course
because it is a massive topic in itself.
But you do need to be aware of
authorizations.
And make sure any programs that you create
take into account authorizations
already set up by the system or, if
required,
implement your own authorization checking,
as just mentioned.
[BLANK_AUDIO]