So far we've learned how to read data from
database tables.
It's now time to take a look at how we can
modify and delete data using ABAP.
There are some important concepts to keep
in mind when going through this module
including the architecture of our system.
Now as a reminder, we have a three tier
architecture, we have the client who uses
the tool such as the SAP GUI to request
data from the application server, our
second tier, which in turn communicates
with the database server, our third tier.
Now when we create our programs, we have
to keep in mind that there could
be tens,100, maybe 1000 of users all
accessing the same data at the same time,
and we need to ensure the programs that
we create do not cause any problems with
the rest of the system, and
ensure we access the most recent version
of the data.
Held on the database when our program
runs.
Because think about it.
If you've got 1000 of users, you've got
records probably being updated every
single minute of every single working day,
and you need to make sure your programs
can read, add, and update data that is
current in the system.
Now fortunately for us an SAP system takes
care of a lot of this work for us.
And the ABAP programmer doesn't have to
worry about the underlying technology
of how records are locked and being used
by other programs at the same time.
And one of the key tools that we'll use in
our programs is what we call open SQL.
And no doubt many of you have heard of
SQL.
It's standard query language.
SAP, I've introduced what's called open
SQL
which acts like an interface between our
program and the database.
By using Open SQL, we can read the
modified data, and
also buffer data, on the application
server, which in turn
reduces the number of database accesses
our system has to perform.
And it's the database interface which is
also responsible for synchronizing
the buffers with the database tables at
predetermined intervals.
And when we are creating programs we've
got to keep in mind that if data is
buffered and we are reading this buffered
data it may not always be up to date.
So when we create tables, we need to
create them in such a way that
we tell the system that buffering can be
used or it can't be used.
Or maybe it can only be used in certain
situations.
And when we created our example table in
the system in the earlier module.
We touched on this, and we told the system
that for our table do not use
buffering and by using this setting that
meant every time we read
data from our table we we will always read
the most up to date records.
We will not be accessing data that was
read from
the table say five seconds, ten seconds or
even a minute, five minutes ago.
Now, buffering can be great for tables
that hold master data and
configuration settings because data in
those type of tables
don't get updated on a regular basis, but
when we're working transactional data,
its a whole nother ball game, because if
you've got 1000 of users
telling the application server to process
transactions on transactional data.
But when we read that data, we want it to
be as up-to-date as we can,
so we don't want buffering set on
transactional data.
And if you are dealing with transactional
data, whether tables are configured
to use buffering, you have to insure your
program can take this into account.
And make sure the buffer gets updated with
brand new data at the time you need it.
Now back to open SQL.
Remember, I said that open SQL
acts as an interface between our programs
and the database.
When we use open SQL statements in our
program
we are only allowed to access tables
through the ABAP dictionary.
This is our interface.
We don't actually access the database
tables directly.
Through our programs now there's no need
to worry
about how we go about doing this because,
in our programs,
we use open SQL statements just as though
we were accessing the database tables.
Directly.
We don't have to think about it.
Open SQL as an interface manages the
database access all by itself.
All we need to do is code our statements
just as though we were accessing the
tables.
But we will have the underlying knowledge
that by using open SQL we
are accessing the data through the ABAP
dictionary,
which has a built in level of safety, to
insure our ABAP code does
not have a direct effect on the SAP
database system itself.
[BLANK_AUDIO]