Let us now consider locking concepts.
And when we talk about locking,
I'm referring to locking data in database
tables.
And there are two basic types of locking
data that we need to bear in mind.
First of all is database locks which lock
data in a physical database.
So what I mean is when we update a record.
A lock gets set on a record.
We can update it and then the lock is
released.
The lock is there to ensure that once we
set it, only we can update the data and
once we release the lock, that data can
then be accessed by for the people.
Now these locks are not sufficient in an
SAP system.
And they are generally only used.
When our record is being modified in a
single step dialogue process.
Now, what I mean by a single step dialogue
is that if
we have a screen that contains all the
data that we need to work with.
And we click a button to update the data.
And because everything is held on one
screen it can be updated in the database
in a single step.
Therefore the database can set a lock,
update the data in the table and
release the lock all very very quickly.
As you will with SAP systems,
you will realize that database locks are
not sufficient.
And this is because transactions in an SAP
system often occur over multiple steps.
So let's say if we add an employee record
to the system,
we may have to fill in ten screens of
data.
The first step may be the name and
address,
the second step would be the position that
they would fill in the system, and so on.
And the user when they enter this data.
Only want the record to be added to the
database at the very
end of the transaction when all the data
in all the screens has been input.
So think about this.
If we tried to save the data that was
entered in the first screen into
the database, then moved onto the second
screen and
saved that, what happens if the user quit
halfway through?
Entering all these ten screens of data.
We would have an invalid record in the
database.
We may have updated a few tables, but we
really require,
yeah, maybe five other tables filled in
with data, for us to have a valid record.
So this is what I mean by using database
slots with multi-step
dialogue processes is not sufficient.
So SAP of introduced it's own locking
concept that
is completely independent of the database
system.
SAP have created lock objects that enabled
the system to lock data records
in multiple database tables for the entire
duration of the SAP transaction.
Provided that they are linked, in the ABAP
dictionary by a foreign key relationships.
That we have already looked at.
As we're not covering dialog programming
in this course, we won't go into detail
explaining the step by step procedures to
follow for creating database locks.
But we will continue with a brief overview
of the topic before moving on.
So as I previously mentioned,
SAP lock objects form the basis of the
lock concept.
And they are completely independent of
database locks.
Now a lock object allows you to lock a
record for
multiple tables at the same time.
Fo the entire duration of an SAP
transaction.
And for this to work, the tables involved
in the transaction
must be linked together using foreign
keys.
If you remember.
We introduced foreign keys in an earlier
module.
Now we used the ABAP dictionary to create
lock objects.
And they contain the tables and key fields
that make up a shared lock.
When we create the lock object, the system
automatically creates
two function modules which we will come to
in a later module.
These function modules are just simply
modularized ABAP programs,
that can be culled from other programs.
Now the first function module has the
action of setting a lock,
and the second one releases the lock.
And it is the programmer's responsibility
to insure that these function modules
are called at the correct place within
their programs.
When the lock is set a lock record is
created in the central lock table for
the entire SAP system.
Now all programs must adhere to using the
SAP lock concept to ensure their programs
set, delete and query the lock table that
stores the lock records.
For the relevant entries.
We're not going to go into lock objects
anymore than this.
And for the rest of the course we will
just assume that the programs you create
and the tables you access are going to be
exclusively used just by yourself.