Let's now start looking at some of the
open SQL statements
we can use in our ABAP programs.
Now in a previous video, I mentioned that
open SQL statements we use in our programs
allow us to indirectly access or modify
records held in the database tables.
Many of the examples we have used in this
course so
far have used the select statements.
So you should be familiar with them.
The select statement is very similar to
the standard
SQL select statements that is used by many
other programming languages.
The beauty about open SQL is that we can
use these type of statements
in our ABAP programs, no matter what the
underlying database is.
Our system could be running an oracle
database,
Microsoft SQL database or any other.
By using Open SQL in our ABAP programs In
conjunction with using the ABAP dictionary
to create and modify our database tables,
we can be 100% certain that
our ABAP code will not have any issues in
accessing the data held
by the specific type of database our SAP
system uses.
Now cast your mind back to when we created
our first database table.
We included the field Mandt, M-A-N-D-T,
which represents the client number and
forms part of our database table key.
If you recall,
when we created our database table we
included a field called client.
Let's take a quick peak as a reminder.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Here it is.
Now this field represents the client
number and
forms part of our database table key.
So in our ABAP programs, you would think
we would have to use this field
when we're using our open SQL statements,
but actually we don't.
This is like a hidden field.
All our transactional tables and the
majority of our master data and
configuration tables include this field in
them.
And the SAP system has been built in such
a way that it will automatically
apply a filter on this field based on the
client id.
The user is using.
So if I'm logged in to client 100,
the SAP system will automatically filter
all the records held in the database
on this client key, and only return me the
record for client 100.
This is done all automatically.
So when we use open SQL in the programs
that we create,
the system will manage this for us.
Meaning we never have to include this
field in any selection or
any update statements we use in our
programs.
This also has the added benefit of giving
a security.
In the knowledge that any SQL statement we
execute in our program.
Will only effect the records held in our
current clients.
[BLANK_AUDIO]