So, there are five basic OpenSQL
statements,
that we will use all the time in our
programs.
And these are, select, insert,
update, modify, and delete.
So, first of all, there's select
statements.
And, you should be familiar with this
already,
because we've used it in quite a few
programs.
And, the select statement,
allows us to select records, to use in our
program, from database tables.
Next up, we have the insert statement.
This allows us to insert new records into
a database table.
Then we have update, and
the update allows us to modify records
that already exist in the table.
And then, we have a modify statement,
which does the same, but
there is a slight difference, that we will
come to, and lastly, the delete.
And yep, we can delete records from a
table.
Now, whenever we use any of these
statements in an ABAP program,
I want you to get into the habit of
checking to see if the action that you
have executed, has been executed
successfully,
because if we try to insert a record into
a database table, and
it actually didn't get inserted correctly,
or maybe it didn't get inserted at all.
Then we need to know this, so
that we can take the appropriate action,
in our program.
And you do this, by using a system field,
that you have already seen, when we took a
look at DBook in our program.
And this is Sy-Subrc.
And when one of our statements is executed
successfully,
this field will contain a value of zero,
so
all we need to do is check for a value of
zero, and then continue with our program.
But, we need to check if it doesn't
contain a zero.
If our statement was not carried out
successfully,
this variable, will contain some other
value, and
depending on the individual statement, the
value can have a different meaning.
Therefore, you must make sure you
understand what the different
return codes are, for the different ABAP
statement you were using.
You will find that in practice, it becomes
second nature, and many of the standard
statements, use the same return code, to
represent similar results.
But don't count on this.
Make sure you know how, to check the
individual return code for each statement,
and you know what each of the individual
return codes, means.
That way, you can code your program
accordingly,
to take the right action, depending, on
the results.
Now let's move on and start using some of
these statements in a program.