We've already seen the select statements
in action, so let's skip that one for now.
And we'll focus on the next statement
down, the insert statements.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
First of all, I'm just gonna comment out
what we have here.
Oops.
There we go.
And we'll take the scenario that we want
to insert a brand new
record into our zemployees table.
So in its simplest form what we will do is
write insert
followed by our table name with a full
stop at the end.
As you can see this is super simple.
But one little thing to note is if you use
this form of the statement,
you always must specify the table name.
You cannot use a variable instead.
Now next, as I mentioned,
get into the habit of checking sysubrc,
and
I just noticed I made a mistake, [LAUGH],
it's sy-subrc.
So once we have our INSERT statement,
then you would write some sort of check
statement if sy-subrc,
not equals zero, it can just be zero.
Then we would do some statement, so
that will ensure we capture any errors
that happen within such statements.
And we can take the appropriate action by
including some code right here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now let's step back just a little bit and
go through this statement again in a
little more detail.
And the reason we're doing this is because
we don't want to use this form of the
statement.
It includes some bad practices by today's
standards.
And it's a throwback to some of the older
ABAP programs
that you will no doubt come across when
working with an SAP system.
So what do I mean?
Well, take a look at the statement again.
All we say is, INSERT table name.
INSERT zemployees.
You might wonder, what are we actually
inserting?
Well this is where we need to introduce a
concept called a work area.
In the ABAP statement we have just written
expects a work
area to exist that was created when we
declared an internal table.
And this type of work area is often
referred to as a header record.
So let me bring in Microsoft Excel to try
and explain a header record and how
it's attached to an internal table, and
compare it against a standalone work area.
Okay, so I'm going to try and represent a
normal table here.
What we would normally have is record one,
and we would have field one, field two,
field three, etc.
Then we would have record two, record
three, record four, record five.
And they would all contain their
individual fields.
So we would have an entry for record, for
field one, for field two,
for field three, in every record.
Now, if this is our table,
let's give it a nice border.
Then when we work with an internal table
with a header record,
we have this additional record up here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And this little guy is what gets
populated when we reference.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The table just by its table name or in our
case where we chose
the insert so what would happen is
whatever was existing
on this header record when the INSERT is
executed,
this record would be inserted into the
table body.
This header record only exists in memory,
whilst our program is being executed.
It doesn't contain a record held in the
table itself, it's just a place for us to
work with a current record, and that's
where the term work area comes from.
We just used it to hold the current record
we are working with.
So when we are working with the data in
our program, we're always
referencing this header record just by
using the table name.
And it can become a little bit confusing.
Because you think you're referencing the
table, but actually no,
you're working with a record held in
memory
that has the same structure as the table.
The fact that the table and
its header line have the same name leads
to confusion.
Now, with the introduction of ABAP
Objects, which we don't cover in this
course, but I highly recommend you take a
course covering ABAP Objects.
This method of using this type of work
area is no longer valid.
ABAP Objects will not allow you to
reference a table
by using its header record.
So, like I say,
this is a bit of a throwback to how ABAP
was coded many years ago.
And with the changes in the language that
have come about over the last,
I was going to say few years, but, boy, it
must be, ooh, six years, seven years.
This way of referencing a work area for a
table is no longer used, and
you shouldn't create programs yourself
using this type of work area.
So to avoid any confusion, when working
with internal tables,
you should make sure your programs work
with separate work areas.
And what do I mean by this?
Well, it is similar in a way to what we
have here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let me pop it down here.
If I do an insert.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So this example is a table with a header
record.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
This one
is an internal table without header
record.
But we have a separately defined work
area.
We'll call
this WA.
And this is our table.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So when we write code, we can reference
the table by itself.
And, when we reference the work area where
we want to work with a record in memory,
we reference a completely separate work
area.
It will have its own name, so it will be
clear
that it does not belong to the table
exclusively.
It's a separate structure that we will
create in our program that sits by itself.
So let's go back to our program code and
have a look at how we can declare a work
area.
So you should be familiar with the data
statement, and
that's exactly what we do to declare a
work area.
Because, you know, in reality,
it's just like a normal structure, all we
do is data, and
we'll give it a name, let's say
wa_employees.
Then we need to give it a type.
Well, remember, we're working with a
table, so
I'm not gonna use the type statement and
declare, you know, a character field.
I'm gonna declare a bunch of fields that
make up the table.
And the easiest way of doing this is use
the like statement.
And we're going to say our wa_employees
work area is
like zemployees, which is our table.
So our wa_employees work area will take
the same
structure as our zemployees table.
But it won't be a table as such,
it will be a record structure not a table
structure.
So our work area will only store one
record.
So once we declare our wa_employees work
area, we can then change our INSERT
statement to use the work area to insert a
record into the table.
And we do this by editing the INSERT
statement,
instead of saying INSERT zemployees.
We will say INSERT zemployees FROM
wa_employees,
which is our work area.
It would help, if I could type.
There we go.
Now also, with this
form of the statement, we could, actually
use a variable here to identify the table.
So instead of doing INSERT table name, we
can do INSERT and put a variable
there that we may have populated earlier
with our zemployees table.
And the only thing to remember is,
if you do use a variable, you have to
enclose it in brackets.
So, our INSERT statement would look like,
would look like this, INSERT,
our table name in brackets.
I'll remove that for now,
and we'll concentrate on the basic form.
So now, we've declared our work area.
We've got an INSERT statement.
One thing that I need to do,
[BLANK_AUDIO]
fill our work area with some data.
So let's do that in this example.
I'm going to remind myself of the
structure of zemployees.
I could use forward navigation, just
double-click.
But I'm just going to open up a brand new
session.
And I'm gonna copy these fields.
Paste them in.
Remember, copy and paste, it's a coder's
best friend.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Oops.
So what we will do is fill out a work area
with a new record,
and I'm just going to check what data we
have in
the table first, forward navigation this
time.
Okay, we have used up to one, zero then
five.
So let's fill in a record.
Six.
I tell you what let's give it a proper
surname.
Whoever WESTMORE
is, BRUCE.
No he wasn't born in 2000.
Let's see 1992 12 13.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So now, we have our data statement
declared in our work area.
We are filling our work area fields with
some values.
We're then going to in insert our work
area field into our table.
And check that everything works
successfully.
And for this check,
lets have a write statement.
Change this to an equals.
So, if it dos equal zero, write this
statement out.
Else.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We have a return code of sy-subrc,
and don't forget to use the chain
statement.
Just make sure everything looks good.
Give it a check.
And then we should be able to execute our
program.