Before we do execute it, I've noticed a
mistake or two.
[NOISE] Got way too many zeros, oops.
[NOISE] I think it's six,
because I think it's an eight character
field.
Let's go and check.
Yes, it's eight characters.
And also, now I think I think
it's it's definitely my keyboard playing
up, it's not me not being able to spell.
Honest.
[LAUGH] Okay, so
now we'll check the program.
Everything's good,
make sure it's saved, then we'll activate
it, and then we'll test it.
So, if I bring up the database
table as it currently is [SOUND] and view
the data.
There are the current records we have.
So I'll move it over to the side.
We'll execute our program.
Record inserted successfully.
So, I'll come back over here and we'll do
a refresh,
and there's our new record at the bottom.
So, let's now, just for practice, let's go
through this in d book mode.
Now, we'll change the contents.
No we won't, we'll leave it lying down.
What we'll do is delete the record from
the table.
So whilst we're here, highlight that one,
table entries and choose Delete and it's
gone.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then, I'll put a break point.
[NOISE] Oops, cursor was
placed on the wrong place,
do apologize.
Just do the breakpoint there.
Okay, now we'll execute the program and
we'll step through it one line at a time
and check the value of the SY sub RC
field.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay so we're in debug mode.
So press F5 which is the single step.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And you can see here that we're going to
fill our work area.
So what I'll do, I'll double click on the
work area structure up here first.
Now you can see the work area, and
they actually, if we hover over, you can
see it's completely empty.
But what we'd like to do is display the
whole structure.
So see the individual fields, So, I'm
going to double click it.
And now it's jumped to the structure view,
where we can
see each field within our structure.
Now, due to the limitation in size here,
we can always get very small preview of
the code.
Well let's go to the actual line of code
we're working with.
So we have executed this one,
and you can see we have filled the
employee field.
The next field, surname, gets filled, and
so on for
name, title, date of birth and now we have
the insert statements.
And what I'm gonna do is go back to this
fields view and
I'm going to bring up the xy sub rc field.
But I say bring up, here it is down here.
It's always on the screen.
So at the moment, it has a value of zero,
and as we execute the insert
statements If there were any problems at
all this would change to a four for
a warning and then an eight for an error
or to say it was unsuccessful.
So, let's execute the insert statement.
We can see the value is still 0 so,
everything has worked correctly.
We're now going to clear the sy sub rc
then write out the message
and then the program will finish.
Step back to come out
and then we'll do a refresh on the table
and there we have it.
The new record has been added.
So that's the insert statement, using a
separate work area.
Now, as we move on, there is a separate
module looking at internal tables
where we will discuss internal tables with
header record and
internal tables with separate work areas.
So we will come back to the work area
header record topic a bit later on.