Now at this point, I want to introduce a
new statement called the clear statement.
And the reason why I want to do this is
because,
in our other programs, you won't just see
programs that start at the top,
fill data like we have just done, do the
insert,
check that it was successful and then
process another record.
You would have loops set up and things
like that so
that you can write just a small section of
code, that maybe could insert 100 records.
And to do that, we're going to reuse
variables and
structures in our program over and over
again, so
the clear statement, enables us to clear
out a field,
a variable or structure, so that we can
reuse it and make sure that
none of the data that currently exists in
the structure Get supply to a new record.
Now you will see the clear statement being
used in awful lots of programs.
Because every program that makes use of
existing fields within that program,
time and time again.
So in the scenario we have here, we fill
our work area with data.
Let's take off this break point.
And this one up here that I set
accidentally.
So, our program fills our work area,
structure,
then inserts the data into the table, and
then we do some validation checking.
Well, now if we want to insert a new
record, in this case all I'm going to do,
is just copy the code.
Add just a little break there just to show
that we've got something new.
Change the employee number.
So now to do this, well, let's say, this
didn't exist.
If we did an insert statement, again at
this point, our work area
contains all the values from our previous
insert and we wouldn't want that.
We want to clear it out.
So once you finish working with a variable
or structure.
Use the clear statement and specify what
you
are going to clear out.
You have a couple of options.
If we use clear WA employees, is gonna
clear the complete structure, so
every field within the structure would be
wiped clean.
Alternatively, you can specify individual
fields.
[SOUND] So let's bring back in the fields
we commented out.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Just so oh, we'll just leave them like
that.
And then we'll, we'll run our program in
[UNKNOWN] mode.
So you can see the clear statement in
action.
So first of all we'll check the program.
Everything is good.
And we'll activate it.
Set a break point.
And let's go.
So instead of, well, I'll do it again.
I'll double-click zed employees, which is
the whole structure, but this time,
let's do the individual fields.
I'm just going to double-click each field
and as you can see,
it's added to the list at the bottom.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we'll wipe this one out.
Oops, sorry, wiped them all out.
Start again.
Let's do these four.
I could do a fifth, but we'd have to page
down.
So see the date of birth, so I'll just
keep it at four.
I'll do F5 to go step by step and we can
see everything being inserted,
and the insert statement, the record gets
written into the database.
Now, we still have the original record in
the database, and check this out.
Our SY sub RC has given us a return value
of 4,
indicating we've got some sort of error.
So now our WRITE statement will write out
the return code to the report,
telling us about the error.
And this is because the record already
exists.
So we're trying to create a brand new
record with the same key.
And, and this just won't work.
Our table requires unique records.
So the system here is saying uh-uh,
the insert statement didn't execute
properly We have a problem.
It's giving us the return code, we are
checking for
it, and then it's going to write out this
comment to the report.
And now we come to our clear statement.
This is what I wanted to demonstrate, not
so much the error.
But we're going to execute the clear
statements on this individual field.
And it's going to clear out employee only.
There we go.
See it's been initialized to zeros.
We don't have the clear statement for
surname and forname.
But because we are filling all the fields
again, there's the employee number.
Everything will work.
But in practice, I should of cleared out
the whole stretcher not
the employee, so we go along.
Insert, this time we do have a unique
record,
because we changed the employee number.
So we can see SY sub RC0 and
this time it will write out a row saying
record inserted correctly.
And that's the end of our program.
And there we can see the first one.
We have a return code of four and
then record inserted correctly.
So, before I forget, I'm gonna wipe out
these records.
Right now.
If I do a refresh, yeah we'll see the
seventh one.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
There we go, we're back to where we were.
Let's move on to the update statements.