Okay, first of all I'm going to
tidy this program up a little bit.
What we will do is now take
a look at the update statements.
Now the update statement
allows us to modify one or
more existing records in
our table at the same time.
Now in this example, we're just
gonna focus on updating one record.
But to update multiple records,
the same sort of thing applies.
So just as with the insert statement.
We first of all would declare a work area.
We would then fill our work area
with the data that we want to update
the record with, and then proceed to
execute the update statement which
would take our data,
update the record in the database.
And then give us back
a return code to tell us
if the update was successful or not.
So as we have already
got a table structure.
Or work area structure should
I say to the y employees.
Let's use them, so
we don't have to declare it again.
But what we will do is
change these contents.
So we will let this insert
statement run through.
Insert the record, and then we will
update it with some new values.
And instead of Westmore,
let's use Eastmore, and
we will change the guy's name to ANDY.
Now very similar to the insert statement,
and I'll copy this checking as well.
What we will do?
Is instead of insert, we will use update.
And just like the insert statement,
the simple form would be
just update z employees.
And that would update
using the head of record.
But as we don't want to do that,
because it's the old way of doing things,
we want to use our separate work area.
So back in our program,
[SOUND] we would say update z
employees from our work area.
So that's it,
we don't need to do any more coding.
Let's just test this out.
So I'll Save the program.
Let's make sure it compiles okay.
Oop, we do have a problem.
Let's have a look.
Missing period.
Oh!
Just off the endif.
There we go.
Everything looks good.
We'll put a break point in.
And run through.
So we're going to insert our record,
check for
the SY sub RC on the insert.
Yes, it's zero so everything is good.
And now we're gonna get to the update.
So the first thing, which I forgot to do,
but it doesn't really matter in this case,
is I should have used the clear statement,
and cleared out employee surname and
fullname, but
because we're updating every single
field again, it won't really matter.
So I'll step through.
The employee is exactly the same.
Our surname will change to EASRMORE.
Fullname to ANDY.
Mr. date of birth,
now the next one is the update statement.
So first of all while we're here,
let's bring through the other section.
We'll do a Refresh,
there's our new record.
Let's go back and execute this update.
SY-SUBRC is 0, so
that indicates everything is good.
Oh, and look, I didn't update the actual
comment to say, record updated correctly.
Never mind.
But, because the update has been executed,
if I do a refresh,
we should see each Eastmore changed to,
sorry,
we should see Westmore changed to
Eastmore and Bruce changed to Andy.
There we go.
And now just press F8 to zoom
to the end of the program.
And there's that output.
Represent that breakpoint and just for
completing this I am going to change this.
And it would be nice to put these
these are menu line on it.
There we go.
You know, what data is it?
For the update statements.