For our next topic we are going to look at
the modify statements,
now the modify statement is like a
combination of the insert statement and
the update statements.
You can use it to either insert a brand
new record, or modify an existing one.
But in general, you want to use the insert
and update statements where you can.
Don't be lazy and always try and use the
modify statement.
The insert and update command, offer
greater clarity to those
people reading your code, and it's clear
to you when you're writing your code.
You know exactly what the code is doing.
Now there are times when you have to use
the modified statements,
because sometimes you will be writing
code, that either has to insert or
update a record, depending on certain
situations.
And the modify statement is fine to use in
that regard.
So let's have a look now what the modify
statement looks like,
and I'm sure it'll be of no surprise to
you.
It follows the, similar syntax of the
other statements.
So again, I'm gonna copy some code.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we'll first of all take a look at that
basic syntax.
Oops, shouldn't have double clicked.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And this is it, a simple modify zed
employees and as with the other
statements, this will use the header
record of the internal table.
But we do not want that.
We want to use the work area.
So,-
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Our modified statement looks very similar
to the others where we will
modify our table, then employees from our
work area.
Now when the modified statement is
executed, the primary key fields
from your work area, will be checked
against those records held in the table.
If a record exists,
that record will be updated with the
content held in your work area.
If the record doesn't exist,
then a new record will be inserted at the
end of the table.
And that's with the other statements, if a
modified statement is unable to execute
either of these two tasks, the SY sub R C
field, will return with a value of 4,
but if it's a successful, it will contain
a value of 0.
So let's go ahead.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[LAUGH] And let's stick with this theme.
And actually call this guy Northmore.
[NOISE] First name of Peter.
So this should update the existing record.
[NOISE] Change this to modified.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Outputs on a new line.
And then what we will do.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We will look at the second scenario,
where the record doesn't currently exist.
So it should insert a record.
[SOUND] These are really bad names I'm
choosing, but nevermind.
[SOUND]
There we go.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So let's recap the code.
Tell you what.
Let's do what I should've been doing
anyway, and set the CLEAR statement.
[SOUND] There we go.
So now we'll recap.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So the program will insert a record first
of 06.
It will then update 06 with a surname and
forename.
Then, we will get to our modify statement,
where because we are using the correct
key, the action performed will be the same
as the update.
We will update the surname and the
forename.
Then we'll come down to the modify again,
but this time,
because it's a unique key, a brand new
key, we're going to add a new record.
So let's do a syntax check.
We'll pretty it up first, yeah.
Syntax, and we'll activate.
Let's check our data in the other session.
We'll get rid of 06 first.
[SOUND]
Refresh.
Oh, it's already refreshed.
So we've, we've got to oh five.
So let's debug our code.
[SOUND] F8 and now we
will step through.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
There's our insert statements.
Everything is good.
Do a quick refresh.
There's our record, Mister Westmore.
Now we will do the update, change his name
to Eastmore and Andy.
Everything is good with the SY sub RC.
Let's do a refresh, there's Eastmore.
And now we get onto our modify statement.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We'll do the modify.
SY- sub RC0 so everything is good.
Do a refresh, we've changed to Northmore
and Peter,
and the last one, this is where we will do
the modify statement again,
but it should insert a brand new records.
We've executed the clear statement, white
everything out,
generating a brand
new record, Modify.
SY sub RC 0.
White out the success statements of the
report.
Do a refresh.
And there's our brand new record.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's move on.