The last statement we are going to
look at is the delete statements.
There are no prizes for
guessing what this statement does.
As I mentioned previously, you must be
careful with this statement, because if
used incorrectly, you can end up wiping
out the content of your entire table.
Don't let this put you off
using the statement, though.
You just have to be aware of how it
should be used within your programs.
So let's go and have a look.
So if we focus on the program again,
we will create a new section for
our delete statements.
And as usual, I'll do the copy and paste.
I'll leave in some of
the [INAUDIBLE] statements.
And delete what we don't want.
Okay, before I change anything else,
let's just discuss this delete statement.
And in contrast to the other SQL
statements that we have looked at already,
the delete statements only needs to
take into account your primary key.
So what I mean is when we want to
delete a record from our table,
we only have to tell the system what
the primary key of the record is for
that record to be deleted.
So in our case all we need to do is first
of all, let's clean out our work area.
So it's completely empty.
Then we will fill our employee field which
forms part of our primary key with
the last record we have created.
So in this example,
we will just delete the one record to ask
the employee number of one,
zeros and a seven.
Let's take a look at our table again.
As a reminder of our primary key.
Now you can see the key's
made up of two fields.
The client field and our employee number.
Now remember, the client field is
handled automatically by the system.
So our programs never need to feed our
rescueL statements the client field.
It's all automatic.
All we need to do in this case is
specify the employee number that we want
to delete.
So let's go back to the table view and
pop it to one side and back to our code.
So once we specify the employee number,
we then just need to create
our delete statement.
The syntax for
the delete statement is this,
we have the DELETE,
followed by the table name,
followed by the from addition,
followed by how a work area.
So this delete statement will say
DELETE zemployees FROM wa_employees.
And wa_employees contains
the table key 1 with 0s and
7 to ensure only that record
identifies specifically in the work area,
will be deleted from our table.
And as per the other SQL statements,
we need to check the SY sub RC field to
make sure the record was
deleted successfully.
And we might as well leave this
clear statement at the bottom.
I'll do a pretty print to
make sure it all looks good.
And a check, and
then we'll activate and debug.
So as it stands at the moment,
we have all these records in the system.
This is where 07 is created.
This is where 06 is multified.
And we update it there,
and we insert it there.
So.
What we will do is clear out 6 and
7 from the table.
So they get deleted, sorry,
they get created once again.
[NOISE] Oops.
I didn't do something.
Oh, maybe it's a refresh.
Yeah.
Okay.
So now we can debug.
Let's stick a break point on and test.
One second, I need to react.
There we go,
now I can put the break points on.
And the code is run through to our
break point, so it should have created
record six and seven automatically for
us, which it has done.
And then we'll keep an eye on SY sub RC.
And we'll just bring up
these fields to monitor.
So the clear should
clear out these fields.
And we'll populate the number.
Now remember this table had the O6 and
the O7 records, still there.
We will execute this next
statement SY sub RC, is still 0.
That means everything worked correctly.
We go back to our table and do a refresh.
We can see 7 was deleted successfully.
So then the code should carry on and just
output record was deleted successfully.
And there we go.
How simple can it get?
Now, before moving on, let's have
another look at the delete statement,
but use a slightly different form.
We're not just restricted to
filling in the table key and
deleting records that way.
We can also use logic to determine
which records we want to delete.
So, for example,
let's let's create some more code.
And what we're gonna do,
is just copy this section once again,
We don't need that separate one.
And we're gonna write the delete
statements as follows.
We're gonna get rid of this filling
in the key, but we're gonna say,
delete from employees, but this time,
instead of from, we're gonna do where.
Then we specify a field.
So let's have a look at our table.
And we can choose to
delete records on surname.
So if we say delete where
surname equals Brown,
then it should delete any records
that have a surname of Brown.
Now just to show that our example
we'll delete more than one record.
Let's create a new record
that has a surname of Brown.
So let's step accounts and
then we'll do the oops.
Utilities table content create.
Use a number of let's,
let's make it ten just to jump a few.
We'll create Brown, give it
an excellent first name of Qwerty, and
there's a Mr., and
let's choose 1st of January 77.
Save that record.
One step too far.
And [INAUDIBLE] our data.
There's a brand new record,
with the surname of Brown.
So now let's get onto our code and
delete all the Brown records.
So here we delete zed employees.
Where, specify the field, which is
surname, and we'll say equals Brown.
And we'll check to see if the records
were deleted successfully,
and we know in this case we're
going to have two records.
And I'm going to leave the clear in
there just in case we need it later on.
Pretty up the code.
Check the syntax.
Oops.
Oh, I do apologize,
I've got the syntax wrong.
The statement, in this case,
we actually say delete from ZED employees.
So delete from table name where the field
equals In the contents of the field.
Double check, and
we activate, and then let's do a test.
Now we already have, let's look six.
So we'll delete that.
Because how a program will recreate it.
Scoot that across to the side, set our
break point, and now let's test our code.
Let's bring the table in, refresh.
There's our 6.
We have the 10 and the 1.
We will go step by step again.
So see here.
Our Z employees.
Need to get the field name correct.
Kind of course, it's z employee,
so [NOISE] [INAUDIBLE]?
To be employees,
zed employees, is employee.
Oh, let's have a look.
I'll scoot up a little bit and make sure
I get the field correct WA employees.
There we go.
So, if we step through, this one record,
sorry this one statement,
should have deleted both records.
We know it was successful
because that's why subIC is 0.
Come back, have a look at our table,
do a refresh, hopefully 1 and
10 will disappear.
And they do.
And I will just zoom to
the end of the program.
And there we have our output.
Take this break point off.
So that's the second form
of the delete statement.
Where you can use logic.
And the last thing I just want to mention,
is that if you used the delete
statement in the following form,
here we go, delete from z employees.
This form of it is what I said
earlier you need to be careful about.
Because this will delete all
the records on our table.
That wraps up the delete statement.