This module will introduce the ABAP
debugger, and
we'll go step by step through some of the
main tools
we can use to ensure our programs function
as we intend them too.
And we will also see how we can highlight
bugs within our program
that are not captured by the syntax
checker.
So the first thing we're going to do is
load up a program
that we have used previously that accesses
the database table we created
containing employee records.
So the program we'll use is Zed employee
list 01.
So we'll just go into the program itself
and have a look at the code, so
we are familiar with the logic that we
want to debug.
So the program basically reads data from a
table called z_employees and
we have multiple select statements that
act as loops, so
it'll read the first record, write out the
record to the screen,
then end the loop, and it'll keep going
round until all the records have been
read, and output to the screen from that
table.
Underline.
And it does the loop again.
Loop again,
with some slightly different output to the
screen, by introducing new lines.
And so on.
Step back just to the main screen of
S-E-38 and we can
start debugging this program in a number
of ways, and the first way we'll see
is we have an option here on this toolbar
called debugging, which is SHIFT F5.
As long as we have the program and
the program import box, we can click the
debugging window and it will take us
into a debugging session at the first line
of code within our program.
So here we go.
We've entered the debugger, and
you can see we've got a blue arrow
pointing at the report statements.
And that's the first line of code within
our program.
Now I'll step back and show you an
alternative way of debugging.
If we go and look at the code itself, now
we have the option of setting what I
called break points on our code.
And we'll come to break points very
shortly, but for now I'll just set one.
So I'm gonna place my cursor on the line
of code, and click this stop icon.
And that will set a break point on this
line of code, which will force the program
to stop executing our code and take us
directly into a debugging session.
So if we execute the program, you'll see
it's very fast.
The program started to execute, and then
as soon as it got down to the line of code
where we set a break point the debugging
session kicked in and we have
the blue arrow identifying the line of
code that we can start debugging from.
And I'll say, this is actually my
preferred way of debugging a program,
because more often than not,
you don't want to start at the very start
of your program.
You have a good idea of where the issues
are, so
you'll normally set a break point, let the
program zoom through to it, and
then start debugging line by line from
that point on.
Now I briefly mentioned rate points there.
And I will just explain there are two type
of rate points
that you can set in your program.
Static rate points, which we will come to
in a little while,
and dynamic rate points.
And that is what I set just there.
An important point to keep in mind about
dynamic rate points
is that they are only valid for the
current session.
So if you come out of your sub-gui and
go back in at a later date, your break
point will no longer exist.
So just step back to the program
[BLANK_AUDIO]
I've just mentioned that, here is another
way of setting a break point.
And that's within your debugging session
itself.
You can just double click on any statement
and a break point will be set.
So for example, I'll just double click
here, [SOUND] And
you'll see a break point is set.
To remove your break point, just double
click the stop sign.
[SOUND] And it's gone.