Now let's take a look at the top end of
the screen.
You'll see here we have some buttons on
the top.
Fields, tables, breakpoints, watchpoints,
calls, overview and settings.
Now these buttons allow us to enter
different modes of the ABAP debugger.
And at the moment we are in fields mode.
And this is the default mode when you
start the ABAP Debugger.
To change the different modes, just click
on the button.
So for example, tables, great points,
watch points and so on.
So we'll stay with field,
and just start to explain the buttons that
you see just above those mode buttons.
The first one we have is single step.
Nuts, I short clicked key of F5.
What this allows us to do is go through
our program line by line to in essence,
a single step at a time.
With the press F5 key or press the button.
And you'll see that we are executing the
program line by line.
Now, the next button we have is the
execute button with the [UNKNOWN]
key of F6, and the execute button allows
us to execute Independent
sections of code that our program may
call.
So for example function module or forms.
This option is very handy because if our
program uses existing
sections of code already created in a SAP
system and we know them to be correct.
And there's no need for us to actually
debug them.
We would just want to execute them and
then carry on debugging our program
to find out what the specific issue is in
our code.
And moving on, we have the return
function.
That's where the short cookie of F7.
Now the return function is somewhat of a
lifesaving function
if you forget to use the F6 execute
function.
So for example, if we.
Step by step go through the lines of our
program, and
we'll use the F5 key to step into a
working function module
that may contain hundreds, if not
thousands of lines of code.
But because we know this function module
already exists,
It's probably the case that we don't want
to debug it.
So we don't want to be sat there pressing
the F5 key going step by step
until we finish that section of code and
get returned to our program.
So by pressing the F7 key, the return
function,
it allows you to execute all the remaining
code within that specific function.
And then you will be returned to the line
of code
within your program that calls that
function.
And once again you can continue then going
on debugging your own program.
So remember the return function, it saves
you awful lot of time when you make that
mistake in stepping into a function module
that already works.
The next option we come across is the
continue option.
And this has a short cookie of a F8.
Now the continue option allows you to
basically continue your program without
going step by step, line by line.
If I was to press this button now which I
will, you'll see the programs
zooms along and it executes the whole
program and shows us the final results.
Let me step back and get into the debugger
again.
Now I ask one of the function,
which is, as well as zooming through the
whole program,
you can also get it to just zoom to the
line of code where you place your cursor.
So, for example I'll place the cursor here
in this select statement.
And if I press the F8 key.
You'll see the execution, a zoom down to
where the cursor was, and
then pauses there for us to then choose
what to do.
So we can go step by step or press the
zoom continue function again,
and it completes the program.
[BLANK_AUDIO]