So, let's get back to our debugging
session again the next option
you see is the display list option and
that's Control+F12.
If we press this button, you can see it
takes us to the output screen
as it currently stands within our debug
session.
So at the moment we have executed the code
to output the results of the first select
statements in our program.
We can press the F3 key to go back to the
code.
And if we start to execute some more
lines, and press it again,
[SOUND] we can see it outputs another two
lines.
So it allows you to go see the results of
your reports whilst the program is in
midflow.
And the last option we've got is
watchpoint.
And we will come to watchpoint just in a
little while.
Now the fields mode of our app debugger
allows us to check and
modify the contents of the fields as we're
debugging our program.
You can double click on the field itself
in the code section of the screen, or
type in the field name in the lower
section of the screen.
So for example,
if I navigate to a place in the code where
we're dealing with individual fields.
I can double click on the field, and
you can see it's copied the contents down
to the lowest section off the screen and
it shows the actual field name with the
field content alternatively.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
I can type the name or in my case because
I don't like pressing too many
keys I'll copy and paste the name into the
lower section of the screen.
And press Enter.
You can see it has exactly the same
effect.
And just to note, because I'm dealing with
a table here,
I have to qualify the field name with the
table name first.
So it's table name dash field name
whichever method you choose,
the field name will always be on the
left-hand side of this grid,
and the contents will be displayed on the
right-hand side.
And this allows you to continue debugging
your program, and watching
the contents of the field that you have
specified in the field names list.
So if I do a single step, we're going
through our code line by line, and
then the next select statement, we should
see a change of surname and forename.
There we go.
So now it's changed to Brenda Nichols.
I'll do it again.
Execute the select and there we have a new
employee coming in.
You'll notice there are only four rows
available here but
you can actually monitor below that
amount.
You can use this button to go down line by
line.
Or, you can use the Next Page button to
see fields five to eight.
And, quite often, when you're debugging a
program,
you'll want to manually change the
contents of a field.
And, you can do this by clicking on the
field in question, in this case surname.
Typing in your new value, and then click
this change button.
Now the contents of the surname field have
been changed to Johnson.
This is very useful when you're debugging
your program
because it saves you a lot of time.
Quite often you don't want to come out of
your debugging session,
enter some new values in a variable, go
back into your debugging session again,
and pick up where you left off.
This function allows you to change the
contents of the field so, you can
dynamically check the logic within your
program using whatever values you like.
[BLANK_AUDIO]