Now you'll also see at the bottom of the
screen.
We have three fields, SY-SUBRC,
SY-TAPIX, and SY-DBCNT.
And you'll note that the actual value
boxes are gray down.
Which means we can't change the values of
these fields ourself.
These fields are system fields, and
actually belong to a table called S-Y-S-T.
This system table actually contains a
whole lot more system
fields that get filled in at runtime.
These system fields are updated
automatically
while your program is executing.
Most statements within ABAP cause the
system fields to be filled with zero
when they are executed successfully.
But it's important to remember that these
fields are completely statement dependant,
meaning that they will contain different
values,
depending on which statement is executed.
And we will take a closer look to the
system return codes and
system variables later on in this ABAP
course.