Let's now take a closer look, at the table
mode.
Just click the Table button, and you'll
see the screen changes.
We still have a code section, but then the
lower section,
has now changed to show an entry for an
Internal Table and then a single row.
We haven't covered Internal Tables yet in
this ABAP course, but for
now you just need to be aware that, an
Internal Table is just a table or
records that are stored in memory while
the program is running.
The table mode option, allows us to
interrogate the records and
fields of each record of an Internal
Table.
As we did with the fields mode section,
you can either double
click on an Internal Table that has been
defined in your ABAP code, or you
can enter the Internal Table Name directly
into the internal table input field.
So for example, I can double click on this
Z Employees Table,
and we can see the screen changes to show
a Table Name, and
below it the individual fields together
with their contents.
So as you can see it's very similar to the
fields mode.
And that you'll see the Field Name and the
Field Contents.
Table mode allows us to see a whole
Internal Table.
Now in this example, things do look a
little different to normal,
because I'm actually dealing with a table
structure right now.
We haven't declared an actual Internal
Table itself.
And the program is just using table
structure, which results in a table list
like this, showing the individual fields
listed one to six with their content.
When viewing Internal Tables, you will see
a slightly different layout.
Where you'll see, a number of records for
each internal table, with the content,
and then you can double click on those
Records to then show this layout,
which shows the individual fields for each
record.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
As we move along in this course, we will
be debugging our programs, and
looking at proper internal tables, and
you'll see the screen layout then.
As we did with the Field List section, you
can now navigate up and
down the Field List.
And interrogate the contents of the table
and the individual fields, and
you can continue debugging your program in
table mode,
and see how your program code changes the
table contents.
Now, I don't often do that myself, because
as you'll notice,
the screen that's your code section, has
become very small.
You only get what one, two, three, three
lines of code that are visible.
So as you step-by-step go through your
code,
you can see, you don't actually get to see
much about code.
Only the couple of lines surrounding the
statement, that it's currently executing.
So more often than not, I'll have a look
at the Table, I'll have a look at
the Contents, find out the information I
want and then switch back to fields mode.
[SOUND]
And
you can switch between these different
modes of the debugger, any time you like.