Let's have a look at breakpoints in more
detail.
The Breakpoint button allows you to see a
list
of individual breakpoints that you have
set within your program.
And by double-clicking on any breakpoint,
entering the table, it will remove the
break point.
This breakpoint table is very handy.
When you're in a large program, and you
have to set lots of breakpoints to
keep track of the different variables that
are being used.
And the table allows you to review the
breakpoints sets,
and when you don't want them, you can just
choose which ones you want to remove.
It's important to remember the lifetime of
your breakpoint and
watchpoints which we will go on to.
It's only for the length of your current
debug session.
When you leave your debug session, your
breakpoint will be deleted.
There is an option that allows you to save
the breakpoint.
And watchpoints before closing your debug
session.
So that your breakpoints remain active for
the next time you come to debug your
program.
This allows them to be set in place, and
saved, so you don't have the hassle of
recreating them.
Now to do this, choose the Breakpoint
menu, and choose Save.
These breakpoints will remain intact,
until you manually remove them or
until you end your current SAP session.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
If you are in the ABAP Editor, you can
choose the Utilities menu,
Breakpoints, then Display to see an
overview of all
the dynamic breakpoints you have set
within your program.
You can then use the options available to
delete your breakpoints.
By double-clicking you will navigate to
the location of the breakpoint
in your program.
Earlier on you may recall I mentioned
static break points.
This is where you enter a line of code
within your ABAP program itself.
Forcing the program to enter debug mode at
the specific line you choose.
To do this, you need to insert the
statement BREAK-POINT.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
If you try to run your program, you will
see your program will enter debug mode,
and your cursor should be positioned at
the line of code where you entered
the breakpoint.
Now by embedding this statement into your
programs, it is active for all users.
As you can imagine, this is undesirable
for
anyone else that tries to run your program
that doesn't need to debug your code, so
be careful with this, and ensure you don't
leave this statement line,
lying around in programs that will get
transported to other systems,
such as your q and a, and your live
environment.