But we'll now take a look at watchpoints
so first of all,
click on the watchpoints button and you'll
see that the screen changes
so that we see the program code in the top
section and
then we see a watchpoint table in the
lower part of the screen.
Now we have previously discussed break
points.
And you will no doubt understand how
useful break points are when debugging
your program.
But there are often times when break
points are not the ideal
tool to use to pause our code so we can
interrogate the contents of
individual fields and internal tables and
to analyze the logic of our program.
Imagine our program was processing a table
containing 1,000 records.
And we wanted to debug the logic in our
program.
But only when a certain condition occurs.
And this condition is dependent on the
data held within the records we're
processing by using break points.
We would have to debug each record
individually, which could take us a long,
long time.
And this is where watchpoints come in.
We can actually tell our program to stop,
just like a break point, but instead at
a specific line of code, we can tell it to
stop based on the value in a field.
So we, now, an example.
If a specific value we wanted to analyze
only occurred
on the 200th record within our large
table, setting a watchpoint
would allow us to skip the first 199
records and
focusing specifically on that 200th record
that is of interest.
So let's take a look at how we can create
a watchpoint.
First thing we need to do is make sure
you've pressed the watchpoints button,
and then go up to the create watchpoints
button in the toolbar.
You can also use the Shift F8 shortcut
keys.
Once you press the button, a dialog box
will appear, and
it will already have the program name
filled in.
And what you need to fill in is the field
name that you want to watch.
So in our example, let's say we want to
watch the employee surname.
So the first thing I need to do is key in
the table name which is Z employees.
Followed by a dash and then surname.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We then need to set the relational
operator.
In our case we'll look for surname
equalling a value of Mills.
So we would use the equal relational
operator.
I'll show you the drop down box just so
you can see all the different values you
can choose.
We'll chose the equals sign.
And then I'll key in the bottom field the
value of Mills
now one note here is you don't have to use
a specific value here.
You can get your watchpoint to compare
your field
against another field in your program.
All you need to do is click this
comparison field and
fill in the field name.
But in our case we'll just stick with the
specific value of Mills.
Once you've done this, click the create
stroke change watchpoint button.
And then you'll see your entry has been
added into the list at
the bottom of the screen.
Now just keep an eye on this section at
the bottom down here.
Where it says current field contents of
the last watchpoint reached.
It's currently empty, but now when we
execute our program, the program
should then pause when the employee
surname contains a value of Mills.
So just before we execute the code, we'll
take a quick look at
the output to see whereabouts in the
processing we are up to.
And we can see the second site loop has
just completed.
So the next select statement should select
the record Stephen Brown.
It'll then need to cycle through
additional records until it gets
to the fifth record of Alex Mills, and
that's where the program should stop.
So let's step back and we'll press the F8
button to continue.
And now you can see the program has
paused.
The blue arrow is pointing to our next
select statement, and
if we have looked at the outputs, it
should have output four records and paused
before it's outputting the fifth record
which should contain the surname Mills.
And that's exactly what it's done.
So this is the start of the next select
loop we can see it's output four records,
the next one would be Haleys Mills but it
is paused and just to double check that
in the fields mode let's key in the actual
field and
have a look at the contents so key in Z
employees dash
surname press enter and there we can see
the actual value at the moment in memory.
Does equal Mills and
also if you click the watch point button
again you'll see those fields right
down at the bottom of the screen actually
contain the values we are looking for.
Watchpoints are a real handy tool that
can save you a lot of time debugging your
code.
When your test data contains many, many
records.
[BLANK_AUDIO]