This brings us to the end of the debugging
module.
And, before we wrap things up, I just want
to discuss how to stop the debugger.
Now, it may seem fairly simple, but
there are two ways you can stop debugging
your program.
The first way is by pressing the F8 key,
and
letting your program run all the way
through to the end.
But, keep in mind, if you have any grey
points or watch points set,
the program execution will most likely
pause, and you'll have to press
F8 key again, and maybe keep doing it in a
cycle until the program finishes.
And, you need to bear in mind that you are
counting on your
program executing successfully.
If your program causes any runtime errors,
your debug session will terminate, and
you'll be returned to the SAP menu screen,
which can be just damn annoying.
Because you just want to get back to a
C38.
The alternate way of stopping the
debugger, and my preferred method,
Is very simple.
Just come to the debugging menu, and chose
restart.
That way, no more program code will be
executed, and
you'll be returned to the SE38 front
screen.