In this module, we're going to focus
specifically on the data dictionary.
Now the data dictionary is the main tool
that we use to look at, understand,
and enhance the database and database
tables that are used by our SAP system.
We can view standard tables that are
delivered by SAP using this tool.
We can create our own tables and
we can even enhance the existing tables
delivered by SAP with new fields.
There are many other features involved in
the data dictionary, but
we are going to stick with the basic ones
in this module, so
we can then build on our knowledge later
on when we are creating our ABAP programs.
So the first thing we're going to do is
create a database table.
And this will involve creating fields,
data elements, and domains.
You'll get to learn what each one of these
is and
why they are necessary when building your
tables.
Once we are building the table,
you'll become familiar with the tools to
check your table for errors.
Once your tables are error free, we can
then activate our tables so
that they can be used within the system.
We will then have a look at maintaining
the technical settings of the table
that we create that will allow us to enter
data into our table.
And lastly, we will take a look at the
data that we have entered using some of
the standard SAP transactions that are
available to us in the SAP system.
Let's move on and start creating our first
table.