So here we are with our SAP GUI open and
the first thing we're going to do is find
a data dictionary in the SAP menu.
So open up the tools menu,
choose the ABAP workbench.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Under Development, you'll then see SC11,
for the ABAP dictionary.
Double click it.
And you'll then be presented with the
first screen of the ABAP dictionary.
So let's go through the different options
that we see on the screen.
The first one we see is Database Tables.
This is where we can enter an existing
table name,
followed by a display to have a look at
the technical components of the table.
Then we have views, a view is similar to a
table, but
all it is, is a table structure, it
doesn't contain any data.
Then we have data types.
Data types are what can make up our
database tables, and
we'll have a look at those soon.
We have type groups, domains, search help,
and lock objects.
Let's focus on creating a table, first of
all.
So what we want to do, is click on the
Database Table option.
And in this exercise we're going to focus
on creating a transparent table.
There are other types of tables such as
Calista tables and pool tables.
But you don't need to know about those
just now.
All we want to do is create a transparent
table.
And when we create our table,
we need to ensure our table name adheres
to the customer defined namespace.
And this means we need to start our tables
with the letter Zed or the letter Y.
Most commonly, you'll see the letter Zed
being used.
So for our example we're going to create a
table
that will list employees within a company.
In the database tables field, enter Zed
employees.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And click the create button.
This new screen appears and the cursor is
on the short text field,
all we need to do here is enter a
description for our table.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Just type in employees.
Now under the short text you can see
various tabs.
And the one that's highlighted at the
moment is the Delivery Maintenance tab.
For the delivery class, click on the
field, and
click the drop down button.
This shows you a list of delivery classes
that you can choose for your table.
Have a read through, but the one we want
to choose is Application Table.
Because we're gonna hold master data or
transaction data in the table that we are
creating.
And in the Data Browser/Table View
Maintenance field,
click the drop down again, and choose
Display Maintenance Allowed.
This will allow us later on to enter data
directly into the table.
And before we go any further, click the
save button.
[NOISE] Now this window pops up,
Create Object Directory Entry.
Now what this is all about, is any
development we do within the SAP system,
quite often we do the development in our
development environment and
we have to move the development through to
our quality assurance environment,
and then through to production.
And this window allows us to choose the
development class which has config
behind it, the actual transport routes
that we want to use for our development.
But in our case, we're just running
through this example scenario,
and we don't want to move our developments
into another system.
So what we need to do is click Local
object.
And what will happen is you will see
dollar temp up here as the development
class, and that means to the system, this
object is only to exist
in our development environment and we do
not wish to transport it any further.
So click the Local object button, and we
can see
down at the status bar at the bottom of
the screen, our table is being saved.
And if you go to the Go To menu and choose
Object Directory Entry,
we can then see the Change Object
Directory Entry pop-up box,
which is very similar to the previous one
and
we can see that the development class has
been changed to $temp.