So the next thing we want to do is start
entering the field names for our table.
There are a few guidelines that we need to
keep in mind
when creating fields within our table.
Firstly, our field names can start with
any letter at all.
They do not have to begin with a Z or a Y
like our table names themselves.
The field names can have a maximum of 16
characters.
And our tables must have at least one key
field.
This is used later on for searching and
sorting of data, and
they identify each record as being a
unique record.
You can assign an initial value to a
field.
Let's say in our example we had an
employee class.
I say the majority of our employees are
going to be regular staff,
so let's say we have an initial value of S
for staff, but
we do have some employees that are
directors.
Maybe they have a code of D.
So we can say our initial value would
always be an S but
allow the user to change the value to a D
later on.
Every field that we use in our table is
made up of what we call a data element.
And the data element defines specific
attributes of each field.
One word of warning here,
data elements must adhere to the customer
namespace again.
So they must, for anything new that we
create, begin with the letter Z or Y.
So let's start off with entering our first
field, and
the field we're going to create is a very
important field within an SAP system.
It's the field that identifies the client
that our records are associated with.
So in the field name enter client.
In the data element we will enter
M-A-N-D-T.
Now the data element already exists in the
system.
And when I press enter after entering it
you can see
the system automatically filled in the
data type, the length,
number of decimals, short text for the
actual data element itself.
Now, very important,
we need to ensure that the client field is
made a key field within our table.
The next field we're going to enter is
going to be our own created field.
And this is going to be employee.
Again we're going to make this field a key
field,
and we're going to use a brand new data
element called Z-E-E-N-U-M.
Once you have done this, click the Save
button.
I always like to save the table as we go
along.
Now the next thing is Z-E-E-N-U-M does not
exist.
So we have to create the data elements.
So even though it's letters, enter it
here.
If we try to activate the table or
just check the table, we should see an
error message and we do.
So basically because we haven't got a data
element
called Z-E-E-N-U-M already existing in the
system,
it's telling us we cannot activate this
table and use it within our system.
So press F3 or the back button.
And then we're going to use forward
navigation to create the data element.
Another way of doing it is to open up a
brand new session.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Go to SE 11 again,
And start creating the individual objects
this way.
But we don't want to do that, we want to
use forward navigation.
And we do this just by double clicking our
brand new data element.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So we get this window that appears called
create data elements and
it's telling us the element does not exist
do we want to create it, answer yes.
Then we get taken to the Maintain Element
Window,
similar to the first screen that we saw
when we created our table.
The Data Element window is asking us for
some short text, so let's enter in here,
Employee Data Element.
Now under the short text you can see four
tabs.
And the one that's highlighted says Data
Type.
We can see here the Elementary Data Type,
called the domain,
needs to be defined for our data element.
Now this is important.
Domains must adhere to the customer name
space.
Now we're going to create a brand new
domain using
the same name the we use for the data
element.
Now don't get confused.
This doesn't mean there's some sort of
magical relationship between
the names, there isn't.
We're just using the same name because,
that's what I've decided [LAUGH].
So enter Z-E-E-N-U-M.
And once again we're going to use forward
navigation to create the domain.
So double click the entry.
It's telling us our data element has
changed and
do we want to save it before creating our
domain.
Choose yes.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We get the create object directory entry
window appearing again.
And just as before,
we want to save this development to the
door temp development class.
So you can either just click the save
button,
or just click the local object button.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, now because we've used forward
navigation,
it's telling us that the new domain we are
trying to create does not exist.
Choose yes to create the domain.
And once again,
enter some short text that describes what
the domain is going to be used for.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So we will just enter employee domain.
Under the short text, we can see three
tabs and
the one that's highlighted says
definitions.
The fields available to us, the first one
says data type.
Click the drop down on data type.
You will see lots of generic data types
already exist within the ABAP dictionary
and we can use one of these for our
employee field or domain.
We're going to choose NUMC, which is a
character string with only digits.
So double click the entry and that fills
in the data type field for us.
In the number of characters, enter eight
which
means this field is going to contain a
maximum of eight characters.
And we want zeros for decimals, which is
the default anyway for a NUMC field.
Select an output length of eight.
And just hit the enter key.
We can see here that where we have entered
the NUMC, it
has brought back the description of this
field, which tells us it's a valid entry.
And the next thing we want to do is take a
quick peek at the value range tab.
Now this tab is all about setting a valid
value ranges for
the domain that you are creating.
If you set a value range and
a user enters a value in a field outside
the valued value range that you set up,
they will be shown an error message and be
requested to enter a valid entry.
Now there are three options for the value
range.
The first we can see says Single Values.
And this is where you actually enter a
list
of individual valid values that a user can
enter.
The next is intervals, so if you have
quite a lot of values, but they
are all related or all in a sequence, you
can enter the lower limit and upper limit.
For example, a lower limit of one, an
upper limit of nine,
and that saves you entering nine
individual single values.
The user can only enter a value that falls
within the ranges that you specify.
The last option you have is value table.
When you have a large number of possible
entries, it's quite common to use a value
table instead of a value range or list of
single values.
With a value table you specify a complete
valid value table entry list.
But please note that if you use this
option,
you must also introduce foreign keys to
your table to ensure the users
entries are tested against the value
stored in the value table that you create.
We don't need to enter any value ranges
for this domain, so
we all need to do is click the save
button.
Once again we are presented with the
object data entry pop-up box and
we want to assign this object as a local
object, so click the local object button.
Now the next thing we want to do is
activate this object.
Even though we have saved it,
it doesn't mean we can actively use it
within our table yet.
We need to set the object as active,
which means our other data elements can
actually use this domain going forward.
So on the toolbar, you'll see a little
matchstick icon.
You hover over, it says activate.
And you can also press the Control and F3
key.
Click the activate button and then you're
presented with a pop-up box
which lists three different objects that
are currently inactive.
You can if you wish try and activate all
the objects together.
But I strongly advise you do not do this.
When you are working in a typical
development environment,
you have got a number of other people
creating developments all the time.
And it's quite often you will see their
objects appearing in this list.
Or maybe you've got a number of
development projects undergo for
yourself and you could see inactive
objects that you've created
yourself in other projects that you don't
want to activate just yet.
So for now, we only want to activate the
domain.
So our top entry object type D-O-M-A.
You can see ZEENUM.
It is highlighted at the moment, so what
we need to do is click the green tick.
The system goes away, checks all the
entries we have made for
the domain itself, and if everything is
okay, it will then activate the object.
And if you look at the status bar at the
bottom of the screen, everything's okay,
so we can now proceed on with creating our
table.
Now remember, we used forward navigation
for generating our domain.
So what we need to do is step back.
So click the F3 key, and
you are taken back to your data element
maintenance screen.
Now because we have created and activated
our domain,
we can now see the text for our domain has
actually come through and
been placed, assigned the ZEENUM entry
that we entered before.
And this has brought back individual
domain properties that we created.
Now the next thing we need to do is define
the field labels.
So click on the field labels tab and here
we need to define the short,
medium, long and heading field labels for
our data element.
Now a little shortcut here.
We've already answered the short text, so
if you highlight that and
use your control-C key to copy the entry
to the clipboard, then you can come
down to each individual field label and
just paste it in one at a time.
Now we can see for
the short field name Our Employee Data
Element does not fit into the field label.
So then just go ahead and tailor it so it
all makes sense.
Now remember, the field labels that we
enter here
are going to appear as field labels on our
table.
So we don't actually want it to say data
on it.
We just want it to say employee, or
employee number.
So in this case, I'm going to choose
employee n, employee number, and
copy that to the remaining Field labels.
Now you'll see on the left hand side
there's a length field which I have
on purpose not filled in.
Cuz once you put the entries in the field
label, and press the Enter key,
it will automatically calculate the length
of the entries that you have typed in.
Once this is complete, save the data
elements and then activate it.
Again, we get a window showing the
inactive objects.
This time we are only left with two
objects and
remember we only want to activate the
object we are working on right now.
So highlighted, we can see object type
D-T-E-L, which is the data element.
So just click the tick button.
And if everything works out okay,
the status bar at the bottom of your
screen with show objects activated.
Now again, we used forward navigation from
our table to create our domain.
So what we need to do is press the F3 key,
or press the back button.
And we step back to our table maintenance
stream.
And you can see right now, The Employee
field that we were creating.
The data element entry that we keyed in
has got the appropriate data type,
length, decimals, and
short text brought back into our group to
indicate everything is working okay.
Now we have just gone through the sequence
of creating a data element and
domain that we then use for our field.
We are going to use the exact same
practice for
creating four additional fields.