But the next field we want to create is
the surname field.
So key in surname.
We don't want to make this a key field,
and
the data element let's create an element
called Z surname.
We'll use forward navigation.
So double-click on Z surname.
Choose yes to save the table, choose yes
to create Z surname.
As a data element.
Key in the short text, and we'll just key
in surname.
[NOISE]
Data,
elements.
We will create a brand new domain and
we'll use forward
navigation again, so double click said
surname.
Choose yes to save the data element,
assign it to the local object.
Choose yes to create the domain, and then
key in some short text.
We're going to choose a data type of
character this time.
[SOUND] So it's the second one, so use the
drop-drown,
bring up the data types in the AppUp
dictionary drop-down box.
Choose char, which is a character string.
We want to set the number of characters to
40.
[SOUND] And output length to 40 as well.
Hit the enter key, to make sure everything
is okay.
And choose, the activate button.
Now notice, I haven't clicked the save
button first,
because when we click the activate button,
it will save the object for us.
Again, choose the double tent development
class.
Choose the object that we want to activate
which is a surname domain.
And check the status bar to make sure
everything is activated correctly.
And if it has.
And press the F3 key or hit the back
button to go back to the data elements.
Make sure that the main attributes have
come through, which they have here.
We can see surname, character, length of
40.
Go to the field labels tab
I'm going to enter surname into every
single field label.
Click enter or press enter.
The length is automatically filled, then
activate your data element.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Your data element will be selected in the
Inactive Objects Window again, so
just click the Continue button.
Then check the status bar along the bottom
to make sure everything
has activated correctly.
In this case, it's ours.
So, again we'll press the F3 key to step
back.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we can see the surname data element,
and
domain attributes have been brought
through into our table entry.
The next field we want to create is
Forename.
And we'll choose ZForename for our data
element.
Then we'll click the data element, to
create the object.
Click yes to save the table.
Yes to create the data elements.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Enter some short text for the Forename
data element.
In this case I'm choosing Forename data
element for the domain.
Enter ZForename.
Double click the domain, choose yes to
save the data element.
Assign it to the local object, development
class.
Choose yes to create the domain.
Enter some short text for the domain.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And similar to the surname field we
created,
we're going to choose a character data
type C-H-A-R the length of 40.
And an output length of 40.
Now activate the object.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Assign it to the local development class.
Make sure your object is selected and
the Inactive Objects Window and choose the
Continue button to activate the domain.
And, when activated successfully,
press the back button to go back to the
data element.
Ensure, the domain properties have come
through.
Which, they have in this case.
And now, I'm going to the field label.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And, I'm going to enter the word Forename
into all four field labels.
Press enter to automatically fill in the
length.
Reach field label.
And then click the activate button.
Select your data element in the Inactive
Object Window and
click the Continue button.
Check the status bar.
Everything is been activated successfully,
so
press the F3 key to step back, to see our
table.
And again we see the data element and
domain properties have come through for
this field, so we know everything is
working correctly.
The next field we're going to enter is one
called Title.
[SOUND] We'll create a data element called
Z Title.
Double click the data element using
forward navigation to create it.
Choose yes to save the table,
yes to create the data elements, enter
some short text for the Title.
[SOUND] I'm choosing
Title Data Element.
In the domain, again creates a brand new
domain.
Call it Z Title.
Double-click it using forward navigation
to create it.
Choose yes to save the data elements.
Assign it to the local object.
Yes to create the domain.
Fill in the short text.
Now enter the word Title In Data type,
we want to use character string again.
But this time, just a length of 15.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then output length of 15 also.
Activate the domain.
Assign it to the local development class.
Ensure, your domain is highlighted in the
Inactive Objects Window.
Click the Continue button.
Once everything is activated, press the F3
key to step back to the data elements.
Click on the field label and enter the
word Title to each field label.
Press Enter to automatically fill the
length of each fill label field and
activate your data element.
Once again, select The object in the
Inactive Objects window and
click the Continue button.
Almost everything is activated
successfully.
Press the F3 key to step back to view your
table.