The last final field that we are going to
create is date of birth.
So I am going to key in DOB for the field.
I will create data element z, DOB.
Use forward navigation to create it.
Save in the table along the way, and
choosing Yes to create data elements.
[SOUND] And the date of
birth data element for
the short text, for
the domain once again,
Enter z DOB.
And use forward navigation to create the
domain.
Choose Yes to save the data element.
Assign it to the local object.
Choose Yes to create the domain.
Enter some short text.
I will enter Date of birth
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now for the data type, date of birth is a
date field.
So we want to choose the appropriate day
field from the drop down box.
So press the F4 key to bring up the drop
down box and
choose the entry that says DATS.
Now press the Enter key, and you can see
an information box has popped up,
just to tell us the attributes of the DATS
field have been assigned to this domain.
So just click the Continue box, and it's
filled in the number of characters for
us, and the output length.
Now the output length is different to the
number of characters because it will
actually insert the back slash to separate
the days, month and years of this field.
So activate the object.
Assign it to the local object development
class.
Ensure your domain is selected, in the
inactive objects window and
choose Continue, and
check the status bar to ensure everything
is activated and saved successfully.
Press the F3 key to step back.
And on your data elements field, go to
Field label.
And, we will enter Date of Birth in every
field.
But, the whole text, Date of Birth, does
not fit in this short description so,
I'm just gonna key in DOB.
Press Enter to automatically fill in the
field label length and
activate your data event.
Once the object has been activated and
saved successfully, press
the F3 key to step back, and
there we can see all our fields have been
entered into our table.
All the short text and individual data
element and
domain properties have come through onto
our screen.
So that indicates everything is working
just fine for us.
Now the next thing we want to do is just
click the Save button.
So we can just save our progress up to
now.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Then we're going to move on to maintain
the technical settings for our table.
Now, SAP needs to know a little bit more
information about the table that
we are creating, before it can create the
back end database tables, itself.
So you can either, now, click on the
Technical Setting button, on the tool bar,
I'll go to the Goto menu, and choose the
Technical Settings option,
which is Control+Shift+F9.
We now need to tell our system what
development class we want to use.
So if you click the drop-down button,
you'll see that we have five options to
choose from.
And if you just read the descriptions,
you'll get a flavor of what this is all
about.
We want to choose the first entry, which
is A-P-P-L-zero.
Which identifies this table as holding
master data in a transparent table.
Double-click that entry and
then for the Size category field, click
the drop-down again.
And here we are just estimating to the
system itself
how many records we are going to be
holding in this table and
it will use these values to make an
educated guess of
how it should actually create the tables
in the underlying database.
We're not gonna be holding a lot of data
in our table, so
just choose the first option which is size
category zero.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Once selected, now we'll move down to the
Buffering options.
And, we want to ensure that Buffering not
allowed is selected.
And what this mean is basically, do not
load the table contents into memory for
reading, and this prevents the table from
being read in advance of
us selecting the records in our programs.
So you may be thinking it would be more
advantageous to hold the data in memory
for speed efficiency.
And you'd be quite correct, but now in
that example we don't actually need that.
If speed was an issue for the development
that you were working on
you would most definitely want to be using
Buffering switched on,
which would ensure the data is read into
memory.
So if you have large tables that are being
read very often, but
only being updated infrequently, choose
this option.
That's all we need to fill out on the
screen.
So you can click the Save button, and then
press the back key.
Now if all goes well we can activate our
table and move onto to entry and records.
So click the little match stick icon to
activate your table.
And check the status bar at the bottom to
ensure everything has worked successfully.
In this case, it has.