Now we have created our table it's time to
enter some data.
So to be able to enter
data into our table, go to the utilities
menu, go
down to the table contents option and
select create entries.
This will now take you to a data entry
screen,
that has automatically been generated for
us.
Now before we enter some data, you'll
notice,
the field names of the actual technical
names of the field that we declared.
For each field, we entered some field
labels.
So I'll show you how to change the look of
the screen so
the field labels appear instead of the
technical names.
Go to the settings menu and select user
parameters.
Now this option allows you to tailor how
tables look specifically for your user ID.
Every user can do this.
And what we want to do right here is say
show us the field labels.
So click field labels radio button and
click the continue key.
Now you can see the field labels have come
back just as we define them and
create in the table.
So now let's enter some records.
So the employee number is an eight
character field, and
we defined it as num c, so it can only be
numeric characters.
So here, I'll enter one lots of zeros and
a one.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So I've entered the five fields and I'm
gonna press the enter key.
And just watch what happens to the fields.
Notice the surname, forename and title
field have been changed to upper case.
And the system automatically validated
every field
to ensure we entered the correct values.
So just click the save button.
Check the status bar at the bottom and
you can see the record has successfully
been saved.
So what we're gonna do now is just click
the reset button and
it'll reset these fields back to their
default values.
And we'll enter our second record.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] Now this time with date of birth,
I'm not going to enter the periods.
I'll just enter the numeric value.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So now when I press the enter key.
The system automatically validates all the
fields and
does any conversion that it needs to do.
In this case the date of birth field, it
put the correct formatting for us.
Click the save button.
Let's enter another record.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Click the save button.
And two more.
Oops, sorry I didn't press the reset
button.
But nevermind, I'll just overwrite.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
One more.
[NOISE] Now, just here, I put this slash
in,
let's see if it gives us an error.
It does.
You see it tells us to enter the correct
date format.
[INAUDIBLE] Take that out and press enter.
Eh, doesn't like it.
There we go.
It's accepted the data.
I click the save key, and that's it.
We've entered five records.