So, now we have entered data into our
table,
we'll do the last few steps in this module
and view the data.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, let's press the back key.
We're back to the database table creation
screen.
And to view our data it's very simple.
We'll go back to the Utilities menu,
to the Table contents and choose Display.
Now whenever we view a table through SE 11
or SE 16,
SAP automatically generates a selection
screen for us.
So if we don't want to view all the
records initially,
we can enter some filter values so
that the system will only show us the
records that we want to focus on.
Now in our case, we only entered five
records.
So there's no need to do that.
But what you can do, if we did,
is let's say we want to focus on one
specific employee number,
you can key it directly into here, or key
arrange the start and the end.
All we want to do is view all the records.
So just click the Execute button or press
F8.
And there you can see all five records
that we entered.
If we had many more fields on the table,
the screen would scroll to the right hand
side.
Which means you wouldn't be able to see
all the fields on the screen at the same
time, but one thing you can do is either
double click on the field
and the screen will change to just focus
on that one record.
Alternatively, if you click the little
check marks
here we'll select three records.
You can then press the Choose button,
which is F2, and
the system will then allow you to cycle
through the three records that you chose.
So you see now, we've got this little Next
Entry button that's appeared.
So if I click it, we go in to the second
record and
we can see a back and a forward.
We click it again, hopefully it will show
the fourth record we entered.
And there we go, the fourth one.
Press back and back again to go to the
start.
And to go back to the default view, the
grid where it shows all our records
just press the back key and we're back to
where we started.
Have a play around with the screen because
you'll notice that,
all the buttons that appear on the toolbar
that will allow you to filter and
sort the records however you wish.
So as an example, if we wanted to sort
this
data in let's say alphabetical on
forename.
Just click on the Forename field and then
click the Sort ascending button.
Now you can see it's reordered records for
us.
There are lots of things you can do with
this table view, and you'll find that
over time, it becomes a real useful tool,
when you want to check on the data
within an SAP system, without going to the
actual transaction screens themselves.
So that's it for this module.
You've created a table from scratch,
you've added fields.
And with the fields you've added data
elements and data domains.
You've defined specific field labels for
each field.
You've ensured you've generated a key for
your table and configured the necessary
technical elements to ensure it can be
saved in the back end data base.
After that, you entered some data and now
you're viewing the results.