So we're going to discuss the technical
architecture of a typical SAP system.
Then we're going to move on do landscape
architecture and
just discuss why we break our landscape
into multiple systems.
Here we have a slide showing a 3-Tier
Client Server Architecture
of a typical SAP system.
At the top we have the Presentation
Server, the presentation server is
any input device that we can use to
control an SAP system.
So here we're showing the SAP GUI.
But we're not limited just to using a SAP
GUI.
We can a web browser, mobile device or any
other form of input you can think of.
The presentation layer communicates with
the application server.
And the application server is the brains
of an SAP system.
This is where all the central processing
gets done.
You can see here,
we're showing the application sever isn't
just one system in itself.
Your application server can be made up of
multiple instances
of the processing system.
Now the application server in turn
communicates with the database layer of
the 3-tier architecture.
The database is kept on a separate server,
a separate system in itself,
mainly for performance reasons, but also
for security as well.
It provides a separation and
that's why we got these three different
layers in this whole SAP system.
The presentation server communicates with
the application server.
The application server does all the
processing,
it makes calls to the database.
Data is passed back to the application
server,
more processing is done before the results
are then sent to the presentation server.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now let's quickly discuss a typical
landscape architecture.
Now, I say typical, but you'll find that
when you work with SAP, there is no
typical in inverted commas landscape
architecture that most companies use.
What you do find that's very common, is
you'll find the development system,
you'll find the testing system and then
you'll find a production system.
Now why do we have these three systems?
Well, it's fairly straightforward.
All the development work and initial unit
testing that we do
in our SAP work gets done on a development
system.
This ensures we do not affect any other
system that is being used by the company.
Once our developments, we think, are good
enough to be tested by maybe an external
source or someone else within your company
whose role it is to carry out testing.
We move our developments using what's
called a transport system
to the next system.
Which, in this case, is the testing
system.
On the testing system normally, no
developments is done at all.
It's just used for
testing what developments were carried out
in the developments system.
If everything works out and everything
passes in the test system.
Within user transport system again to move
our developments or
our program changes into the production
environment.
When code goes into a production
environment,
that's when it's turned on and that's when
it's used within the business itself.
Now our landscape architecture is not
separated just for development purposes.
Your company can have other reasons.
They can be the quantity of data that a
normal production system holds.
It can be too great to actually be used in
the development environment
because normally your development system
and
your testing system are not as large as a
production system.
You only want a subset of data to test on.
There is also the security element that
you need to look at.
More often than not, companies do not want
developers
to see live production data for data
security issues.
You know, you got employee data on the
system.
You've got sales data.
And you don't want people who're not
involved in those specific areas
to actually see the live data.
So normally,your development and testing
systems have a different set of data that
they can develop and test on.
I would say the three systems we have here
are normally a minimum.
You know, you normally got your
development system,
testing system then our production system,
but it can increase to four systems.
Maybe you want a training system, maybe
you've got multiple projects
running at the same time, so maybe you've
got two different development systems.
You can then have two different test
systems you know, and then maybe
a consolidation system before this is
passed to the production environment.
This is all dependent on the company that
you're going to be working at.
But one thing that is common is that each
system that you do have in your landscape
architecture will have it's own
application server and
it's own database server.
This then ensures we have platform
independence.