Now let's move on and have a look at the
environment our program's running.
We're gonna discuss the work processes and
then we'll move on to the structure of an
ABAP program.
Within an SAP system or
at least what we're looking at we have two
types of programs.
We have report.
And we have dynpros.
Now reports, is pretty obvious.
Reports are just, [LAUGH] what it says on
the [INAUDIBLE].
Reports are just programs that generate
lists of data.
Or maybe they've got a little bit of
interactivity in them.
But basically they supply data to the
front end databases
the [UNKNOWN] and so on.
When a user runs a report, they typically
get a selection screen.
Once they enter their selection parameters
and
execute the report, they normally cannot
intervene in the execution of the program.
The program runs and then displays the
output.
Dynpro's are a little bit different.
Dynpro's are dynamic programs.
They allow the user to intervene in the
execution of the program and
they work by processing a series of
screens that we call dialogue screens.
The user determines the flow of the
program itself
by choosing which buttons or fields to
interact with on the screen.
That action then triggers different
functions that have been coded
within the flow logic of a program.
While we're creating a report we will be
generating interfaces
that clusters dim prose for all our
selection criteria.
Now don't fret,
because most of the work that ABAP people
do is actually inside report programs.
And even though these programs are classed
as reports,
they don't always generate output.
The report programs are there to process
all the logic,
reading and writing to the database.
Try to make your systems work let's have a
look at word processors.
Every program that runs an NSAP system
runs on what we call
word processors, and these actually run on
the application server.
What processes themselves work
independently
of the computer's operating system and the
database that it interacts with?
This gives us that program independence
that we discussed earlier when
looking at the technical architecture of
an SAP system.
When an SAP system is initially set up
your basis consultants.
They're the guys who actually install SAP
and keep it running, you know,
manage all the memory and so on.
They configure SAP in such away that it
automatically sets the number of work
processes your programs use when they
start, and that's the equivalent of like,
setting up a predefined number of channels
or
connections to the database system itself.
Each of which tend to have their own
different properties and
different functions.
You might come across something referred
to as the dispatcher.
Your SAP system has no technical limits
on the number of users who can actually
log on and use an SAP system.
Generally the number of users that can
access an SAP system is a lot larger than
the number of available work processes
that your system is configured for.
This is because not everybody is you know,
sending instructions to the application
server.
At exactly the same time.
It's a bit like the old mainframe time
sharing scenario.
And because of this.
Users cannot be assigned,
you know, a certain number of processes
while they're logged on.
It is the dispatcher that controls
the distribution of the work processes to
the system users.
The dispatcher will keep an eye on how
many work processes are available and
when a user triggers a transaction, the
dispatcher's job is to say, here you go.
Here's a free work process.
Go and use it the dispatcher
tries as much as possible to optimize
things so that the same work
process receives the sequential dialogue
steps of an application.
If you can't do this, lets say because the
user takes a long
time between click in on different aspects
of this screen.
He will then, have to select a different
web process take carry on with
the processing of the dialogue program.
Is the work process that executes an
application, and it's the work process
that has access to the memory areas that
contain all the data and
objects that an application uses.
It also makes three very important
elements available.
The first one is the Dynpro processor.
All Dynpro programs have flow and
processing logic.
And it's the Dynpro processor's job to
handle the actual flow logic itself.
It responds to the user's interaction and
controls the further flow of the program.
Depending on the users interaction.
What I'm trying to say is it's responsible
for dialog control in the screen itself,
but one important thing to remember is it
cannot perform calculations.
It's just there to manage the flow logic
of a program.
The next important element is the ABAP
processor.
And this is responsible for the actual
processing logic for our programs.
It receives screen entries from the Dynpro
processor, and
transmits the screen output to our
program.
Now it's the ABAP processor that can
perform the logical operations and
arithmetical calculations in our programs.
It can check authorizations and read and
write the database over the database
interface, and
it's the database interface that is our
third important element.
Now the database interface is actually a
state of ABAP statements
that are database independent.
Now what I mean by database independent is
that we can use a set of ABAP
statements that in turn can communicate
with any
type of database that is being installed,
when our system was set up.
So whether it's, you know, a Microsoft
Sequel server or an Oracle database,
we can use the same ABAP statements, that
is actually called Open SQL to
control our database reading and writing
over the database interface.
Now the great benefit of this means that
our ABAP code, our ABAP statements have
encapsulation which means our programmers
don't need to know which physical
database system the actual SAP system that
they're using actually supports.
Now there are times when maybe you do want
to use a specific
SQL statement that is native to the
database that is installed.
So SAP have designed ABAP in such a way
that if this
type of coding is necessary you do have
that facility.
You can directly access the database
through your programs using native SQL
statements.
But its not encouraged.
You know, if you gonna be programming ABAP
make sure you use the open SQL.
Because then, everybody else that comes
and sees your programs afterwards,
they'll totally understand what you're
trying to do.
And I'll just add that, normally, [LAUGH]
when systems are set up,
your systems administrator normally
forbids this practice
mainly because of the different security
risks.
Stability risks to the system that you may
introduce to your programs.