It's now time to take our first look at an
SAP ABAP program.
We're going to fire up the SAP system and
open up the ABAP Workbench.
Now just before we do this, let's quickly
discuss the structure of an ABAP program.
As with many other programming languages,
ABAP programs are normally structured into
two parts.
The first part of the program, is what we
consider to be the Declaration Section.
This is where we define the data types,
structures, tables, work
area variables and the individual fields
that we want to use inside our programs.
This is also where we would declare global
variables.
That will be available throughout the
individual subsections of our program.
When we create a ABAP program, we not only
declare global variables,
but we have the option to declare
variables
that are only valid inside specific
sections within our programs.
These sections are commonly referred to as
Internal Processing Blocks.
The Declaration part of our program is
where we will define
the parameters used for our selection
screens for our reports.
Once we have declared tables,
global variables, and data types in the
Declaration Section of our program
We then come on to the second part of an
ABAP Program itself.
And this is where we will write all the
logic for our program.
This part of an ABAP program is often
split up
into what we call Processing Blocks.
The Processing Blocks that we define
within our programs,
can be called from Dimpro Processor that
we discussed in previous videos,
depending on the specific rules we create
within our programs.
These Processing Blocks are nearly always
just small sections of
programming logic that allow us to
encapsulate our code.
Let's log onto our SAP system and take a
look at the ABAP Workbench.
We're finally having a look at the SAP
system itself.
When you open this up GUI, you may have a
different menu on the left hand side but
I've set it just so that I've got the
minimal sort of menu options
that we want to have a look at during this
ABAP training course.
So the first thing we're gonna do,
is have a look at the ABAP Workbench.
Now to get to the Workbench,
we can just use the menu system on the
left hand side here.
If we open up the sub menu, and
choose tools, then you'll see the AppUp
Workbench.
Open that up, and then you'll see four
different options within.
Now the first thing we want to look at is
just
a very quick overview of how we run a
transaction in SAP.
Now hopefully you are all familiar with
this.
But I'll just show you the two ways.
First of all, you can open up the menu and
when you have an item
that was not look like a forwarder, that's
an actual transaction you can run.
So in this case, let's run the object
navigator.
I'll just double click, then we'll see
down here at
the bottom of the screen it said starting
the transaction, and then it opens it up.
To come out of the transaction just press
the back button and
the other way of running a transaction
is coming up here to the transaction input
area and
you can key in the technical name of the
transaction itself if you know what it is.
Now a little trick so that you become
familiar with all the different SAP
transactions and to make it so that you
don't have to go through the menus
all the time is to have a look, or
navigate to the extras menu.
Go to Settings.
And the dialogue box that comes up has
four options.
Choose the bottom one that says Display
technical names.
Click the little continue icon with the
green tick.
And now, it's refreshed the menu, and
when you navigate inside, we'll go back to
the overview menu again.
You can now see the actual transaction
codes that as you start working with
the SAP system, you'll become familiar
with them and you'll be able to enter them
directly into the input box.
So, let's close this overview menu.
And then we will, step-by-step, go through
the different options and
I'll highlight the four to five major
pieces of the ABAP Wordbench,
that you will become familiar with and you
will use as an ABAP developer.
One thing that most of our programs will
have in common, is that they will read or
write data to and from the database tables
within our SAP system.
The ABAP Workbench has a transaction to
allow us to create database tables and
also view the fields that make up the
tables themselves and
browse the data inside.
This is called the ABAP dictionary.
And you can find the ABAP dictionary by
going through the ABAP workbench menu,
then go down to Development, and
there you'll see it, ABAP dictionary and
its transaction code SE11.
The next and probably the most used
part of the ABAP Workbench is the ABAP
editor.
And this is where we will spend a lot of
our time in this course.
The ABAP editor is where we create all the
code, it's where we build all the logic.
And by using forward navigation
which is a function within an S-A-P system
that we will touch on later.
You can actually define function modules,
jump forward to the ABAP dictionary, and
also create screens.
The ABAP editor can be found under the
development menu again.
And it's transaction code SE38, the next
most important part of the Workbench is
the Function Build.
The Function Build is very similar to the
ABAP editor but
it's main function is to actually define
specific task,
that can be called from any other program.
You create interfaces in the Function
Builder,
where you define the different data
elements and the different
types of tables that can be passed to and
from the actual function that you build.
We will touch on the Function Builder a
later on
when we encapsulate our programs into
function modules.
The Function Builder can be called from
transaction code SE37.
And, it can normally be
found just under the upper ABAP editor
option on the SAP menu tree.
Now the next item we want to look at is
called the Menu Painter.
And if you have a look at the user
interface folder, open that up and
you'll see transaction code SE41.
The Menu Painter is a tool that can be
used to generate,
if we look up here we can see menu
options, and we can see buttons.
so menu bars.
We can create buttons, icons, menu bars,
transaction
input fields and all these can trigger
events within our program.
You can define whether the event is
triggered by a mouse click, or
by simply pressing a shortcut key on your
keyboard.
An example would be here on this menu bar.
We can see the log off button and we can
see,
this can be triggered by using the shift
and F3 key together.
So the Menu Painter is for building menu
items,
menu bars, then the next item on our list
is the Screen Painter.
And that's transaction code, SE51.
Now the Screen Painter as you might guess,
allows you to define the user input
screen.
So you can define text boxes, dropdown
menus, list boxes,
and input fields, timed areas of the
screen and so on.
It lets you define the whole interface
that the user will use.
And behind all the different fields,
buttons, dropdowns that you put on your
screen, you then
define the individual functions that get
called when the user interacts with it.
Now we've saved the best to the last.
The last item that we're going to look at
is called the Object Navigator.
The Object Navigator is a fantastic tool.
It brings all the other tools together
under one roof.
And gives you a very efficient environment
for you to develop your programs.
When you're building large programs that
have many function modules, many screens,
the object navigator is the ideal tool to
use.
So that you can navigate all around your
development.
You can find the Object Navigator, under
the overview menu
under the ABAP Workbench and it's
transaction code SE80.
So that more or less covers the main
features of the ABAP Workbench
that we will interact with in this ABAP
course.
You will see in the SAP menu tree there
are many,
many other transactions that can be used
to help develop your programs,
but the ones we have just covered I would
say cover 90 to 95%
of the development tools that you will
use.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
That brings us to the end of module one.
I hope you have found this introduction to
the SAP development environment useful.
And in the next module, module two,
we're going to start off by looking at the
ABAP dictionary.