It's now time to get going
with some more addup.
And we're going to focus on working with
other data types that we haven't yet
come across.
So far, we've looked at using pneumatic
fields for performing calculations.
And we have taken a look
at character strings and
the different type of
character manipulation
that we can do with the various in built
character string up, up statements.
But now, let's move on and
take a look at date and time fields.
So before we start, let's go into the up,
up editor and get ourselves
a brand new program to start with.
So we will execute from section SE38.
That's the previous program that we
used in looking at character strings.
So let's copy this.
[NOISE] And we'll call this
zed other data types.
Now it's been copied,
we'll click the change button.
I just updated the comments
And let's get rid of.
Lots of this code.
Date and time fields are not
defined as numeric data types but
are instead defined as
character data types.
They're really just character strings
that can be used in calculations.
And this is made possible by the inbuilt
automatic data type conversions that
we've already discussed in a previous
module and just like any other data type
we use the data statement to
declare these date and time fields.
So, if we focus first on the date field.
We will use a data type of D, which is
always defined as eight characters,
with the first four characters
representing the year,
the next two the month,
and the next two the day.
So we would write it,
we give it a name, my date type d.
That's it, pretty simple.
One thing to note,
when we don't define an initial value,
the system automatically
assigns zeros to the field.
When you do want to an initial
value just like any other field
we used the value addition.
So, 2012 [SOUND] 0, 1, 0, 1.
[SOUND] And don't forget,
like any other field,
we are not just limited to
using the time statement.
If we already know a field
defined as a day type and
we want to reference that field.
We can use the line statement.
So what's this one, SY datum?
Well, this is a system variable that
always holds the value of the system's
date, so the my date two field, we're
defining it the same as DSY datum field.
Now let's move on to time fields.
As you know I don't like excessive typing.
So time fields are very
similar to date Eight fields.
But instead of being eight characters
long, they are six characters.
And they have the format of hour hour,
minute minute, second second.
And just as with the date field,
the initial value is always zeroes.
[SOUND] To define the time type,
instead of D we use T.
So we can say 11 hours, ten minutes,
five seconds is the value.
And the same.
When we want to reference
an existing field,
We will use the system time field,
which is S, Y, dash, U, Z, E, I, T.
So let's now output some of these,
date and time type fields to the screen so
we can see the output format.
So we just make a comment.
And then we'll use the write statements.
Chain command.
So we now put the first date, and
on a brand new line, day number 2,
and my time on a brand new line, and
my time2, And then we'll finish
it with an underline statement.
[NOISE]
There we go.
Run a quick check.
Oops, a little problem.
Let's go fix that.
And the u line is a command all it's own.
There we go
That's better,
we'll activate and then test.
So the output is showing us four fields,
the first one contained the value
of the date that we keyed in and
the date declaration part, and
we can see it's the 1st of January, 2012.
But remember how we keyed it in,
in a reverse order.
We did 2012, 01, 01, but the write
statement applies its own formatting,
and as we discussed in one
of the previous modules,
you can format the output as you
like with the write statement.
A second field is a date field as well.
But we didn't define any
value to that date field so
this system has output
the initial value and
it's used the automatic formatting by
inserting periods between the day, month,
and year, and it's using the formatting
that associated with out user log on.
The third and fourth, very similar again,
we can see they are both time fields.
The first one has a value and
the second one doesn't.
So, now let's move on and see how we can
use a date and time field in calculations.