Now that we've seen how to declare date
and time fields,
let's perform some example calculations
with them, to show how they can be used.
Now, you probably know that using date and
time fields within calculations is common
practice in programming business systems,
because you often have to determine
differences between two dates.
Generating dates such as invoice dates,
delivery dates, salary payment dates, and
so on.
So let's go through some examples of how
we can use dates within calculations
to both generate new dates, and find out
the difference between dates.
So first of all, let's tidy up this
program a little bit.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay.
So what we're gonna do is define an
employee date.
Still tidying up.
[LAUGH] Okay, so we'll
use the data statement,
and we'll define a start
date for an employee.
See, what, let's not assign a value
straightaway, we'll do that in the code.
So there we have
the data statements.
And we will assign a value to the
variable.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
A start date of May the 15th, 2009.
And remember, date fields are character
fields.
So, we have to enclose the dates in single
quotes.
Now let's define another field.
I'm gonna call this one today's date.
And for today's date,
we're going to assign
the system variable.
To pick up the date of the system right
now, we will then
add a calculation to determine the length
of service for this employee.
So we will create a new variable called
LOS.
[BLANK]Together with
a simple calculation.
And I must remember to add in length of
service.
We'll make it an integer.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And the last action.
We will just write out length of service.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay, it looks pretty straightforward.
Let's just execute the code.
So as we can see, the length of the
service is 1,160 days.
So the calculation has given us length of
service in the number of days.
Let's do another example where we want to
add 20 days to today's dates.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So it's quite simple.
[BLANK]Let's just copy some code.
We will use the same today's dates
variable, and
assign it to the system date again.
We'll print a new variable called days
count,
and we'll assign it a value of 20.
Don't know why I'm using quotes, it's
going to be an integer.
And we'll create a new variable called
future date.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Oops.
Which will tell the calculation of today's
date plus,
the day count variable, which will contain
the value of 20.
And then we can write out the future date.
Let's go
out to data
variables.
[BLANK]Have I made
a spelling mistake?
Oh dear, am I going blind?
Here we go.
[LAUGH] Oh dear, look at this.
I can't type.
I do apologize for this.
There we go, that's better.
So now, we should have 20 days added to
today's date, and see the output.
Here we go.
So 20 days on from today, will be the 7th
of August, 2012.
If you remember, in a previous module,
we worked with sub-fields.
Well, all the same logic applies when
working with sub-fields that are based
on date and time fields.
So let's create an example to change one
of our date fields to represent the 20th
of the current month.
So again I'll copy some code.
We will leave today's date
equaling the system date.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
What we will do, is make the day sub-field
a valid date equal to 20.
Now currently it's the 18th of July, so
the system date we'll do the 18th
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We can update the last two characters of
our date field with the value of 20.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And what I'll do, just to save our, save
on a tiny piece of processing
is include the value 20 in quotes, to make
it represent a string rather
than an integer, and all we need to do is
write out today's date.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
My apologies.
Oops, tiny error.
Let me just correct that.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
There we go.
And we'll test the program.
And as you can see, the output now says
the 20 July, 2012.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
For completeness let's just output the
system date as well.
So the system date is the 18th of July,
and our output date is the 20th.
Now in our last example, in this section,
we will show how we can determine the last
day of the previous month.
So again, let's be super lazy, copy and
paste, delete today's date, and
what we're gonna do, is set the day to the
first.
Then we're going to show how we can
subtract a value from today's date.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We'll subtract the value of one.
So today is the 18th of July.
So then, this row of code here,
will make our date equal the 1st of July
and
then when we take the value of one away,
which means one day,
we should end up with the last day of
June.
Let's stick an underline in the last
section.
Pretty it up, check it, and then test.
Now we can see, we found the last day of
the previous month.