Let's move onto working with Time Fields.
Just like using calculations with Date
Fields,
we can also do the same with Time Fields.
All of the same principles apply, so let's
get straight onto it,
and look at some examples.
In these examples, we'll look at the
fictitious employee clocking-in and
clocking-out times.
So, first of all, we're going to declare
the two times, clock-in and clock-out.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So back up to our data section.
Let's create a new little block.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Just make it a little easy to read.
So let's declare a clock-in.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And a clock-out time.
And while we're at it let's declare some
more.
Let's do a seconds.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, this is gonna hold the difference in
time in seconds,
it would help if I spell it right.
And as you might guess, we'll do a
minutes.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then hours.
Line it up, just so it looks a bit easier
to read, and we'll do the same over here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And a bit easier on the eye.
Now, go down to the Code.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And let's start filling some of these
fields with values.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, our
clocking time
is equal 07:30.
That will equal 4 o'clock in the afternoon
for the clock out.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then, let's work out the difference in
seconds.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's see, if I got everything correct.
Almost, missed off the fields.
There we go and finally let's write out.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
I'm gonna make it a bit more descriptive
eh?
[BLANK_AUDIO]
There we go.
That should do it.
So, we're going to write out a bit of text
to say the clock-in time was and
then the clock-in, the clock-out time was,
and the clock-out and
then show us the difference in seconds.
I do apologize, I don't know what I'm
doing here.
[LAUGH] I don't know why I've made the
seconds diff
equal to this, this should be a
calculation [UNKNOWN] before we run it.
See, it's clock-out minus clock-in.
There we go.
So this should be 16:00 hours minus
07:30 giving us the difference in seconds.
Pretty it up.
See if I made any mistakes.
As a bonus, now we'll test it.
So there we can see.
Clock-in time clock-out.
The difference is 30,600 seconds.
Now, is that correct?
Let's have a look.
So, we have 8 hours and 30 minutes.
So 8 times 60 plus
30 times 60 is 30,600 seconds.
Let's not continue and work out, the
minutes difference and
the hours difference.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
It's a simple calculation for the minutes.
Remember you must save your precious
fingers, so Copy and
Paste as much as you can.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
All we need to do is reference our
seconds.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And divide by 60.
So now we should see 33,600
seconds divided by 60 giving us I can't
remember what that calculation was.
Five, ten, was it?
Something like that then we'll write out.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The difference in minutes this time.
And while we're at it,
let's do the hours calculation.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And why not pretty it all up.
Okay.
Pretty Printer.
We'll do a check, to see if I made any
mistakes.
And it looks like I did.
So, what did I call hours_diff?
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay, I made a mistake up here by the
looks of things.
There we go, just 1s.
Okay, everything is good this time.
Now let's test.
Oh, no doubt you've seen the mistake.
Here we want to output the minutes not the
seconds.
I guess this is what happens, when you
copy and paste too much.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay.
Test it out this time.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
There we go.
So seconds through 30,600, minutes 510 and
hours 9.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And I see I even made the spelling mistake
there too.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, if we have 510 minutes difference, and
hours wasn't 9 exactly,
but can you see why why we were given 9 as
the answer?
Hopefully, you recognize that the hours
diff was an integer.
If we'd made it a decimal, we would have
got a decimal result.
Giving us eight and a half hours
difference.
But, because it was an integer it was
rounded up to 9.
You want to check it out, let's change
that integer to a decimal.
So what we need to do, is moved to the
data declaration part, and
where we have an integer, let's change it
to a pac decimal.
And remember, we need to specify how many
decimal places we want.
We'll put 2.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Everything looks good, we'll activate it
and then test it out.
And as you can see, the results now is 8.5
hours.
[BLANK_AUDIO]