We will now focus on quantity and currency
fields.
And in ABAP these fields are treated just
like PAC number fields, and
as such you need to declare your currency
field as a PAC number.
When you do this, always bear in mind how
many decimal places you want.
Just as we did with the hours diff field
in the previous exercise.
Now in a real life scenario the number of
decimal places has a great impact
on the accuracy of your calculations in
your program and
quite often, your program will use a much
higher number of decimal
places in your calculations than those
actually show in our list reports.
Now quite often in your programs,
you want to create your own variables for
quantity and currency fields.
But you'll find it's a lot better to
associate your fields with
the data type of fields of a table in the
ABAP dictionary.
And the reason why I say this is because
the ABAP dictionary already has the field
lens and number of decimal places already
defined for individual fields.
Take our salary field in our employees
table.
We defined two decimal places, so if we
declare a currency
field in our program to match that of
salary in our employees table,
we would normally have to refer back to
the table itself, find out how many
decimal places there were, and then define
that manually in our ABAP program.
Now there could be a scenario where the
number of decimal places in the table
would change, but our program, because we
define it by ourselves using a type p for
parent decimal, we could then have an
incorrect number of decimal places
in our program if the field is supposed to
always reference the field in the table.
So my preference is to always use the like
statement.
So when declared in my packed decimal
fields for currencies and
quantities, I will always reference the
table whose data I'm going to
be reading into my variable, or passing
data from my variable to.
So let's take a look at how we would
normally define a currency field in our
program.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Here we go, so you can see I've used the
data statements, created a field called my
salary, and I'm using the like statement
to reference our Zed employee's two table
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And the specific field, salary.
Now because we link our field in our
program with the field in there about
dictionary, the system must always make
sure that the data types are kept in sync.
And there are two aspects to this process,
the number of decimal places and
the associated currency or quantity keys.
So as we saw when we set up the salary
field in the ABAP dictionary,
a currency field corresponds to an amount
field of [UNKNOWN] d e c, decimal.
Let's have a look.
So let's pop over to the ABAP dictionary
have a look at our table and here we have
the salary field.
And we can see it's currency type nine.
If we double-click on the data elements,
we can see that the domain is currency
nine.
We'll double-click that.
And then let's do a drop-down in the data
type here.
And it gives us a hint that the currency
field is stored as a decimal.
And something else we can do.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
If we just double-click on the currency
type here, we get a screen that shows us
the internal format for our ABAP programs
uses ABAP type p for packed decimal.
And don't forget, when we set this salary
field up We had to reference
a currency key field, which we declared as
e-currency.
So these two fields always go hand in
hand.
A currency field always references the
currency key, which is of type c u
k y which in ABAP world have a data time
per character.
And have a fixed length of five, which we
can see here.
So what this all boils down to is when you
are declaring your field in
ABAP reference fields that they associate
with in your table.
And always bear in mind that every
currency field will
have a currency key that, more often than
not,
you have to take into account when
outputting results to a report.
And then for quantity fields the same sort
of thing applies.
But instead of having a data type of
currency, quantity fields, let's see if we
can show this, have a data type of Q-U-A-N
here we go.
And instead of having a currency key, they
will have a unit associated with them.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's step out of this and go back to our
program.
Let's go on and create an example to
calculate an employees tax
and net pay amount so here in the data
declaration section of the program I've
already defined my salary.
So what I'm gonna do, is also declare a
tax amount.
And the tax amount is going to be a very
similar field to salary.
And that is a currency with two decimal
places so
I'll just reference the same
field in our table then,
[SOUND] let's declare a net pay.
Same again, we'll reference the same
field.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we'll declare a tax percentage.
And pretty it up.
So spell decimals correctly so now we have
our fields
defined let's go to the bottom of this
program and start coding.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And what we're going to do is select
records from our table,
calculate the tax, our net pay, and
then output the results to a report so to
save some time, so
you don't have to watch me make spelling
mistakes I've all ready coded this out.
I'll just paste it into the program and
then also, we need one more statement
at the top and then I'll explain it.
Okay.
So because we're going to read data from a
database table using a select statement.
We're going to declare the table at the
top of our program, Zed employees two.
Then we'll go back down to the bottom.
And I've written a select statement from
the table,
then we're going to write out the employee
surname.
Their salary and the currency.
Let me bring
this stuff up.
The next thing, we're going to calculate
the tax amount,
and that's by taking the tax percentage.
Multiplied by the employee's salary.
So then the net pay amount, is the salary
minus the tax amount.
Then we're going to output the results
onto the screen.
But there's one thing we haven't done.
And I believe that's tax percentage.
Actually, worked out what the percentage
is or should I say.
We haven't declared what the tax
percentage is so
in the data declaration path.
I'll tell you what.
Let's do it down below in the code.
So we're going to say our
tax percentage is equal to
20 to represent 20%.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Oops.
There we go.
[SOUND]
Okay.
Now just before we run the program, let's
have a quick peek at the data.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now we have two, four, we have six records
but
as you can see only three have salary
information in currency.
So let's change that.
Let's edit these records and key in some
values.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And what should we choose for the last
one?
Fiji Dollars.
Okay, let's step back, and
now we can see these records have values
in the salary and currency field.
All looks good.
So let's close that window, and we'll test
a report
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So here we are the first record Smith.
In salary he's one one one one and we have
the currency code.
Then we output the tax amount and the tax
currency,
and the net pay amount, net pay currency.
So the tax amount should be 20% of one,
one,
one, one and that looks about right.
And that should be taken off the salary to
think of it as net pay Just to
make it a little bit tidier.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's include some descriptive text.
Run it again.
And there we can see.
But let's tidy up a bit more.
I am picky.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's skip a line.
There we go, so Smith the salary currency,
the tax amount is this and the net amount
is this.
All with the currencies in there.
And that wraps up this module.