We're now going to move on, and discuss
Character Strings.
When we're creating our programs,
we nearly always have to use fields
defined as Character Strings.
In SAP there are two elementary data types
used for Character Strings.
These are data type C, and data type N.
We'll first have a look at data type C.
To do this as we go along,
I'll create a brand new program called
Zed_Character_Strings.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The data type C, used to hold alphanumeric
characters, and it has a minimum length of
one character, and a maximum length of 65,
535 characters.
So first of all we'll define
a field of data type C.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And when we define this data type, once we
key in the field
name we then, without any spaces, use open
brackets.
Put in the length of the field, so this
will be ten characters.
And then we declare the actual type, which
is type C.
Now this is the long form, of declaring a
field of type C.
And what I mean by that is, because this
field is a generic data type,
the system has some default values that it
can use,
to save us from typing out the full length
of the declaration.
So for example, if we declared a new
field.
Let's call this mychar2, and I want this
field just to be one character,
well the default value of the size of the
field is actually one character.
So, I could get away without declaring the
size in brackets.
And because the character field is the
default type, used
by the system to declare the field I can
even get away without declaring the type.
So, I can end this declaration of this
variable just by keying in the field name.
So this has the same effect.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
As declaring the field just like this.
So, let's remove this.
And if you recall, we created a table
called Z Employees, and
in that table we declared various fields
of type character.
One of these fields was add surname,
so if I create a table statement, and
key in our Z Employees Table, I just use
forward navigation Now we can see is that
surname is type char with a length of 40.
Well, we can replicate that declaration
within our ABAP program.
So I'll step back, and here instead of
myChar2 I
can create a field called Z Employees with
a length of 40, and a type C.
Oops and that has exactly the same effect.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And if you remember also back to one of
the previous videos,
a short form of doing this.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Is just to use the like statements.
So this will declare Z Employees like
actual field we declared in the table.
Let's do this too, so it checks correctly.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
I've already, do apologize.
So now, you know, how to declare a field
of type C.
Let's look at the other generic Character
String data type, and that is data type N.
So thinking back again to when we declared
our table,
we created a field called Z Employees,
which was the employee number.
So if we go to the table and have a look
at this.
Actually it's just called employee, but
you can see we declared the field of type
NUMC with a length of 8.
Now NUMC, or the number data type,
is a special data type in that it is
treated just like a character type.
But, there is an inbuilt rule to only
allow numeric characters.
And when data is moved into this field, it
is right aligned,
just like a normal numeric type field.
This data type is ideal, when we only want
to use numbers within the field.
And we have no intention of carrying out
any type of calculation.
So let's go back to the program, and see
how we would declare this field in ABAP.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So as usual, it starts off with data.
And we'll call the field Z Number 1, with
a data type of N.
And just like previously, in this example
up here, we could use the like statement,
and refer back to the actual field in our
table, and
it would end up with the same effect.
Now one additional point,
is this field does differ a little bit
from the data type C.
In that the initial default value of this
field is 0 instead of space.
And that's it.
There's not much more to declare in these
types of fields.
So, let's move on and see what we can
actually do with them.
[BLANK_AUDIO]