As with many other programming languages,
ABAP gives you the functionality to
interrogate and manipulate the data held
within character strings.
And here we're going to go through some of
the popular statements that ABAP provides
to carrying out these functions.
So here's what we're going to look at.
We're going to look at concatenating
strings together,
condensing finding the length of a
specific string,
replacing characters within a string,
searching for specific characters,
using the shift statement to move the
contents of the field left and
right, splitting character strings and
using the sub field functions to access
specific characters within a string.
So let's first of all take a look at
concatenating strings together.
And the first thing I'm going to do.
Just so our program doesn't fail,
is just turn this group of statements into
comments.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's tidy the code up a little bit as
well.
We don't need these things up here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The concatenate statement allows us to
join two character strings
together to form a third string.
And, it's fairly easy to understand and we
start off by using the word, concatenate.
And then it goes in the form of field 1,
field 2 and we can carry on with field 3,
field 4, field 5, et cetera.
And then we choose a destination, that we
want the output string to go to.
So then we can have destination one.
We can also add in an additional term
called Separating bar, to allow
us to insert a specific value in-between
each field into our destination field.
So it would be.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Would help if I could spell, there we go.
And then we would have a, a separated
field.
Now some things to note, cuz if the
destination field
is shorter than the overall length of the
input fields,
the character string will be truncated to
the length of the destination field.
So make sure when using the concatenate
statements,
you are using string data types.
Which as we have already discussed can
hold more than 65,000 characters.
So let's have a look at a specific example
of some ABAP code using the concatenate
statements.
So you can see I added some code and
I've commented out the definition that
we've created just a moment ago,
and we'll go through the code line by line
so you know exactly what's going on.
So the first statement we've got, is the
data statement.
And because we've declared in five fields
all together,
I'm chaining the data statement together,
so
we don't have to keep writing the word
data out multiple times.
So the first field is title, we're
declaring a length of 15 characters.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
It is of data type C, the value of Mr. And
we have surname.
40 characters long.
And the surname will be Smith.
And we have forename.
40 characters again.
First name of Joe.
And then we declare a separator field
here.
I've just called the SEP and you'll notice
I haven't declared the length and
I haven't declared a value or the type.
So this will take on the actually default
that the system uses,
which is a character string with a length
of one character.
And the last field is destination and
I've just declared it 200 characters long
on data type C.
Now we get onto the code, and the first
thing I'm going to do, just so
you get into the habit of this yourselves,
is bring up the ABAP help for the
concatenate statement.
So here we can see actual syntax used.
And as we declared earlier, in the
definition just up here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Video concatenate F1 to whatever number of
fields you want to concatenate into G.
And you can see, the separated by
is an additional option that we can use
with this this statement if we want to.
So I'll close it down.
So the first line of code we've got we're
gonna cut an [INAUDIBLE] title,
surname and fore-name into the field
destination.
And, we're going to write out the results
of destination with an underline
underneath.
So, I'll do a check and we'll test the
program out.
And, now, we can see, MrSmithJoe with the
underline.
So you notice a couple of things here.
All the characters have been concatenated
together so we got no space and
it's left a line, the result.
And that's because we defined the result
as a character field.
If we used a data type of n, a number
everything would have been right lined.
So we'll step back.
Now to tidy this up, we can use the
separated by addition.
So in this case, we'll add in a blank
space
between each field when it gets populated
into destination.
So, I have an example of that below.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
There we go, so you can see the same
statement but
we've got the additional separated by SEP
at the end.
And we'll write out destination again and
underline it.
Do a check, and a test.
Now we can see it's inserted the blank
separator between our three fields.