[BLANK_AUDIO]
The next statement we'll take a look at,
is the condense statement.
So let me bring these up here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Our other programs quite often have to
deal with long text fields
that contain unwanted spaces.
So this is where the condense statement
can be used to
remove these blank characters.
The definition of the condense statement
is very simple.
So first if we start off with typing out
the condense statement,
we can then have a look.
I'll just search help and see the basic
form.
So here you can see condense and
the field name, and there's just one
addition we can add, which is the no gaps.
So I'll key in a line of ABAP code and
we'll go through it and
test the program out and see the output.
Okay.
So I've added some coding here.
I just pointed out I put the top in the
data statement.
I've extended the number of fields I've
defined by
creating a new field called space name.
It is 20 characters long.
And you can see I've given it a value of
Mr. Joe Smith.
And you'll notice I've put many spaces
between the three individual words.
Then coming down I've added a comment just
showing the definition of the content
statements with the optional no gaps,
which we'll come to in a second.
And then the basic output.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now add in, just a bit of code to
write it out to our report window.
And we're done.
So it's very very simple.
The condense statement will take out the
blank spaces
between our three words but not fully what
it will do.
It will leave one space between each word.
So we should end up with Mr. space Joe
space Smith.
Let's save the reports.
And test it out.
You can see Mr. Joe Smith with one space.
Now the addition,
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Is no gaps and no doubt you can work out
exactly what this is going to do.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's make it look nice.
So this one will do exactly the same, but
where we were left with one space between
each word it should then bring everything
together so there are no spaces at all.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And as you can see.
A very simple statements.
Nice and easy to code.