Now moving on.
Let's have a look, at finding the length
of a string.
Now to do this, we actually use a function
instead of a statement.
And this is a very simple function, called
string length.
So, I will add some code, and then we'll
go through the statement,
and output the results.
So the first thing to do, is to declare
the new data field.
We'll call it LEN for length, and the data
type of I just to hold the integer
value that will represent the length of
the string you're trying to interrogate.
Then down to the code, we can have the
following three lines,
and you'll see it looks very simple, we
have the field we have just defined and
that will contain the length of the
surname field.
And it is this string function, the string
length function,
strlen, that will look at the surname
field,
move the length of the string into the LEN
field we've declared.
If we take a quick peek at the surname
field.
You can see it currently holds the word
Smith.
Which is five characters in length.
So when we execute this report the LEN
field will contain the number five.
And that will be output at the end of this
write statement.
So I've included some text and then the
LEN field at the end.
So let's check the report for syntax
errors.
Everything's good.
And we'll execute the report.
And then we have the length of the surname
field is five.
Very simple.