Now, let's take a look at replacing
character strings.
I'll go ahead and add some code, and go
through the explanation of how it works.
So, the first thing we need to look at is
the new data statement I've declared.
And this is surname2, and it's going to be
a length of 40 characters.
And note, I haven't used the type
declaration here
because the system will use the default
type c.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now, down to the logic itself.
The first thing I'm doing is moving a
value into the surname2 field.
And this is Mr comma Joe Smith.
Then, we're using the replace statement,
and
we're doing a replace the comma with a
full stop into our surname2 field.
And we'll write out the results.
First of all, let's pretty the code up.
And then test it out.
And there you can see, the output is Mr
full stop Joe Smith.
Now, one thing to note here is, with the
replace statement,
it will only replace the first occurrence
in the string.
And what I mean is, if our string had Mr
comma Joe comma Smith,
only the first comma would be replaced.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
To show you that, let's test it out.
And there, you can see.
Only the first occurrence in the string
has been replaced.
So, how do you replace all the
occurrences?
Well, that's where we could use something
we will come on to a little bit later on,
when we have a look at loops.
You could use a while loop so that our
replace statement can be executed multiple
times, dependent on a specific piece of
logic that we add to our loop statement.
I'll show you very quickly here,
[BLANK_AUDIO]
But we won't go into too much detail on
it,
because we will cover it later on.
Oh, sorry, done it in the wrong place.
There we go.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's pretty it up.
So, in this case, when we execute the
program,
we can see the comma has been replaced in
both positions within our text.
And that's because the replace statement
was actually executed two times.