We will now take a look at searching for
specific character strings within fields.
We use the statement search to do this
unsurprisingly, and
it has a very simple form.
So we can key in the word search, and we
enter the field we want to search.
So in our case let's use sur name again.
So name two, and then you specify four,
and then the actual search string itself.
Let's say one, two, three, and a full
stop.
Now this type of statement is a little
different to the others,
in that we're not specifying a variable,
to hold any result.
What actually happens with the search
statements,
is two system variables are used.
The first one S-Y-S-U-B-R-C,
which identifies whether the search was
successful or not.
In the second system variable is S-Y dash
F-D-P-O-S.
And if the search was successful this
field is set to the position
of the character string that we are
searching for in surname two.
We'll go ahead and
add some code that will hopefully explain
this a little bit better.
And we'll look at different variations
that will introduce how these
system variables can be used to determine
the success of the individual search.
So if we stick with our surname
two field, obviously we're not going to
find a string of one, two, three.
So let's change this.
[NOISE] And we'll say, search for the
literal string, Joe.
Now, while I remember [NOISE] because
surname2
[NOISE] does get changed in the statements
above.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's reset it right here.
We'll change the content so it's just Mr.
Joe Smith.
So our first search statements just looks
for the word Joe and
it should be successful.
So what we will do is start to trace a
small report section that shows us
the values of the system veritable.
I'll just pause the recording to do this.
And once complete we can step through it
line by line.
So first off,
we're using the surname 2 variable as
before.
I'm just writing, I'm just writing out a
line here to show the actual search
string, that we are using.
And then we come to our first search
statement.
So this is SEARCH surname2, FOR and we've
got Joe with some spaces after in quotes.
So what this is saying is, we wanna search
for the word Joe, but the trailing
spaces with the way we're using search
here, ere going to be ignored.
And then the output would show literal
string, for what we are searching for.
And then, we're going to output the system
variables.
sy subrc.
Natural value, and sy-fdpos.
And the actual value.
So in this case, we should get a subrc
equal to zero.
Which means it was a successful search and
the position of the search string will
show the position offset in
accordance with where it appears within a
surname two field.
And the next one, we have a very similar
search term,
but this time the system will not ignore
blank spaces.
So the system will actually search for Joe
With,
I think it's four spaces after the letter
E.
And if we look at our surname2 field,
there's only one space after the letter E.
So it should return subrc equal 4,
which means an unsuccessful search.
And because it was unsuccessful, then the
SYFD positive value will be zero.
Then the next search, this is using a
wildcard.
And the way we have the search defined
here, it will search for
any word within the string.
That ends with I-T-H.
Now because we have Smith, and
it ends with I-T-H, H should be a
successful search, and
we should get the offset position, and get
the pause system variable.
And the last example, It's another wild
card search, but
this time we're going to be searching for
any word starting with Smi.
And the variable we are searching does
contain the word Smith.
So we should get a successful search.
And again, the sy-fdpos system variable.
Will be filled with the offset value
relating to the position of the word.
So, let's run this test.
And will have a look at the output.
That'll become, and hopefully you'll be
able to see exactly what I'm explaining.
And you'll see the results in the sy
fields.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So we can see the search results.
Here we show an actual search string, and
the first search example we
can see it was a successful search because
sy-subrc is set to zero.
And the f d pulse value is set to three.
Which relates to the third character in
our string.
That's the offset.
So the search term, Joe, would start one
character after the offset value.
And the next example, we were searching
for Joe again, but we included spaces.
Notice the surname 2 field did not contain
enough spaces.
It was a failed search and the sy-subrc
field is set to fall to indicate that.
And because it was failed, sy-fdpos is set
to 0.
The third example with the wild count
search where we're looking for
any word ending in ith.
It was successful and it's showing the
word starts after the value 7 offset.
Terrific.
So if we look at the search tab,
we can see the offset value number 7, it's
the space after the letter e of Joe,
telling us that the next word in the
string is what we were searching for.
And the last example, very similar, but
this is showing words starting with SMI.
Exactly the same.
Successful search, indicated by subrc
equals zero, and
the word Smith is the word that contains
SMI, and again, it's the same position,
starting one connector after the position
seven offset.
That's four different variations of the
search command.
Very useful throughout your program when
dealing with long character strings.