Let's now focus our attention on the ship
statement.
This statement is quite simple.
It allows you to move the contents of a
character string left or
right, character by character.
So as an example, let' see how we can move
the contents of a field to the left,
deleting leading zeros.
So first of all I'll declare a new
variable.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's call this one employee num, for
employee number.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We'll make it 10 characters in length.
[SOUND] And the first thing we'll do,
we'll set the contents of this field to,
[BLANK_AUDIO]
0000654321.
So we'll fill in every character of the
field.
And what we're going to do with the
example is remove the leading zeros.
And shift everything else to the left-hand
side.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So to do this we just type the statement
shift.
[SOUND] And our field name it will define
we
want to shift the contents to the left.
[SOUND]
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Whilst deleting the leading zeroes
Now before we run this I'll bring up the
search help for the shift statements.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And you'll see there are various variants
showing that you can shift to the left,
to the right, by a specific number of
places and so on.
Let's go back to our example, tidy up the
code.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Create a statement to write an output.
[SOUND] Do a check.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Oops.
My mistake in the data statement there.
[SOUND]
Okay.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So let's now test the code and we'll see
the output.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Here you can see the actual output has
deleted the leading zeros and
moved everything to the left-hand side.
By clicking on the field here, you can see
it is left justified and
we do have spaces at the end of the field.
I encourage you to try different
variations of
the shift statement because there's a lot
you can do with a statement.
It does become very handy tool when you
have to deal with strings of data.
Just before we move on, I'll just do
another few examples.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
This one, I'll show the shift statement in
its simplest form.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now what we will see here, because we
haven't specified anything after our
variable name it will use the default
value of moving from right to left.
And the default number of spaces is 1.
So it will move to the left one character.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So on the test, you can see we've only got
three zeros in the output, and
it's moved all the contents to the left,
and left us with one space at the end.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The next example, we will use the addition
circular.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And what this does if we leave it with the
default values,
it'll move everything to the left one
character.
But the character that is pushed out will
be reinserted
at the other end of the string.
So we should see 0006543210 in the result.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And here you can see exactly that.
That the 000, and then the leading 0 that
is being pushed out,
is being inserted in the far right column.
[BLANK_AUDIO]