Next up, we're going to take a look at the
split statement.
You use the split statements if you want
to separate the contents of a field
into two or more fields.
The statement is fairly simple to use, so
I'll go ahead and create some code, and
then we'll go through it line by line.
Okay.
I've created the code, and the first
section you'll see is that I've created
some new data statements, called mystring,
and
then a1, a2, and a3, and sep2, which is a
separator.
So, let's go through it.
The mystring variable is 30 characters in
length and the a1,
a2, a3 is 10 characters in length and the
separator is 2 characters and
you can see I've assigned a value of
double asterisks.
And, that's just going to be used to
identify
where we need to separate our string.
So, I'm gonna move the data statements
into position at the top of the program.
So, we keep it all in order.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
There we go.
And now, we'll take a look at the split
statement itself.
So, I'm going to show you two examples,
and the first one is,
I'm populating mystring with a value of a
leading space and what you can see.
1234 asterisk, asterisk, ABCD, asterisk,
asterisk, 6789.
Gonna write out the string on the report
just so we can see it in the results, and
the blank line, and then, comes the split
statements.
Now, this statement starts with the word
split, and
then you add the string that you want to
split.
So, in our case, we're going to split
mystring.
Then, we have the addition AT, and
following AT we have a separator.
Now, this could be a literal.
Sorry, I could do this, but
in this example we're just going to use a
pre-defined variable,
sep2, which contains the double asterisks.
Then, we got into, and
then, these are the fields we want the
split contents to be written to.
So, what we'll end up with if we go
through it, I've specifically made
the string look a little bit odd, making
sure we have a leading space and
we have an asterisk then space and we have
a space before the asterisk.
So, you can see how the split statement
actually populates the fields the data
wants to go into.
So, I'll execute the code and we'll go
through the results.
So, here we go.
So, our split statement is splitting a
leading 01234,
asterisk, asterisk, and it's gonna split
at the first double asterisk.
So, we can see, our first A1 results field
does contain the leading space.
It is then being split at the, the double
asterisks, and
you'll note the result has filled in blank
spaces for the rest of the field.
We then have the second field filled with
from
the blank space all the way to the blank
space before the next double asterisk.
This is A2, and also is filled with
trailing spaces, and the last result
is 6789, and you'll see there's no space
after the double asterisk.
So, that has gone one column further to
the left and
filled the remainder of the field with
blank spaces again.
So, that's quite straightforward.
Let's go back to the code, and what we'll
do this time is
take a look at this, this second example,
and the way this differs is I've added
another set of double asterisks for
our separator, and then added some more
characters at the end of our string.
So, what I'm trying to show here is we
want to split the contents of mystring
into three fields, but when we look at the
contents, because we're using the double
asterisk as a separator, we've actually
got enough to fit into four fields.
So, what the system does in this case, is
for the last field that's going to be
filled, it will actually contain the
remainder of the string as well.
So, we'll execute the code.
I've altered the results, and hopefully
all will become clear.
[SOUND] Here we go.
So the difference here is, our third field
is gonna be filled with 6789,
but because we have double asterisk again,
we're trying to split the remainder of my
string into another field.
Well, we haven't declared a fourth field,
so this becomes the remainder and
it gets appended into the last field we
have declared.
So, it's important to keep in mind that if
your separator would result
in more splits than there are fields
available for
the contents to be moved into and the
remainder will be put into the last field,
if the last field isn't big enough, then
it will be truncated.
One last point, just a note that if the
field you are trying to split does not
contain a valid separator string, then the
whole contents of that field
will be moved to the first field that you
are trying to split the contents into.