It's now time to have a look at what we
called sub-fields.
Now we have the option, within ABAP,
of referring to specific characters within
a field.
This is referred to as processing
sub-fields,
whereby we reference a specific character
position within the field itself.
Let's have a look at an example.
And we'll go through it line by line.
So you become familiar with how to use
this.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So I've added some code here.
And the first section shows we're
declaring three new variables.
International telephone number, country
code and telephone number.
And you can see the different size of each
field.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And the first line we have, I am assigning
a character string to international
telephone number, write in the results to
the screen, followed by a blank line.
And then we come down to the actual
sub-field processing itself.
So our first line of code shows that we
are filling the country code field
with the first three characters of the
international telephone number field.
That's quite straightforward.
Let's have a look at our second line.
In this example, we can see the field
telephone number,
is going to be filled with 13 characters
of the international telephone
number field starting after the fourth
character.
So how we'd write this is telephone number
equals international telephone number
plus 4, which means start after the fourth
character,
open brackets 13 close brackets, which
references 13 characters.
Then we're going to move the output to the
screen.
Then the last example we have Is instead
of just moving specific
characters of the international telephone
number field, to telephone number.
We're actually going to be updating the
country
code sub-fields with the literal 01.
So how we write this is,
our country code field +1,
which means stat after the first character
and fill the next two characters.
So the country code field is only three
characters in total anyway, so in effect,
it's gonna fill the last 2 characters of
this field with the value of 01.
And the last line of the code,
is just going to produce the outputs on
the screen for us to check.
So first of all,
let me move this data statement to the top
of the program where it belongs.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now do the necessary formatting.
Have a quick check of the program, make
sure the syntax is correct.
Activate it, and then we'll run the test.
Here we can see the results.
So first of all,
we're outputting the full international
telephone number to the screen.
Then the next field, the country code
field, we filled with
the first three characters of the
international telephone number field.
The next one, the actual telephone number,
we reference 13 characters after the
fourth character.
So the fourth character was the Dutch
sign, so we can see
the next 13 characters starts with the
open brackets and ends with the number 6.
In our last example it updated the country
code field, but as a sub-field.
So it only updated the second and third
character of the field.
So it's quite straightforward.
And you'll see this used a lot in SAP
programs, and you'll probably
find yourself needing to refer to
sub-fields quite often, and
instead of creating brand-new fields,
holding values there, this's often a lot
easier just to use the subfield ten times,
instead of holding additional values.
As a variables in memory.
[BLANK_AUDIO]