For us to be able to build our selection
screens and use selection screens in
our program, the first thing we have to
understand are things called events.
Events are what we call processing blocks.
And what I mean is just a section of code
that's specific for the selection screens.
Now the structure of an event starts with
the event keyword, but
doesn't have an ending event keyword.
The end of the event block of code is just
implicit,
because the start of the next event block
will terminate the first one.
So what I mean is, the event that we
define will end when a new event starts,
such as a sub program, or our report
actually ends.
We're at the end of our code.
Now, when we run our executable programs,
the program is controlled by a predefined
process in the runtime environment.
And a series of processes are called one
after another.
These processes trigger events for which
we can define event logs for
in our program.
When we start our program,
there are certain events that get fired in
a certain order.
This image is taken from the SAP help
website, and it explains it quite well.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Here we have the SAP GUI, so that's what
the user sees.
And you can see we have a selection
screen.
And then we have our list output.
Now when our program starts, the first
thing the system does
is check your program to see if you have
included any processing blocks.
And if you have, it'll determine which
ones you are using and
will follow this sequence of events to
execute those blocks.
So we can see when the program starts, our
program global variables are declared,
so the system reserves memory space.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then the runtime environment will look
to see if you have an initialization
event block, and if you do, this event
block will be executed.
Now bear in mind, initialization event
block will only be run once and
that's at the start of your program and
the things you include in the
initialization block of code are things
like setting up initial values for fields
in your selection screen.
The runtime environment will then check
whether a selection screen has
been defined in your report.
So if at least one input field is being
used, then control will be passed
to the selection screen processor, which
is this piece right here.
Now, this selection screen processor will
display the screen to the user, and
once it is shown, the user can then
interact with the screen,
filling fields, select data from drop down
boxes, etc.
And when the user clicks on execute to run
the report
after filling in all the fields,
a screen processor will then trigger the
app selection screen event block.
And this is where you can write your own
code to check all
the entries the user has keyed in to the
individual fields on the selection screen.
If the user has entered any incorrect
values, your code can capture
these mistakes and instead of processing
your program, you can force the selection
screen to be displayed again to the user,
to allow them to correct any errors.
Now of course, if they make some errors,
you need to tell the user where the errors
are, so you will use error messages
to inform the user they need to check the
entries they have made and
key in some correct values before the
program can be run.
Now this type of action can just run round
in a big loop.
If the user keeps making mistakes, you can
capture those mistakes and
present the screen again and again.
Once the user has no errors, or at least
your code hasn't captured any errors, then
the runtime environment passes control to
the start of selection event block.
This event block can hold your code that
you create for setting up the values
of internal tables, internal fields used
within your program,
and maybe writing out header information
on the report.
Now there are other event blocks, as you
can see, in the rest of this diagram.
And there are many that actually don't
appear on the diagram.
But the ones we have been through are the
main event blocks used to display
a selection screen to capture user input,
which we can then use to process the rest
of our program.
Once all the event blocks that you have
defined in your program have been
processed, the ABAP processor will then
execute the rest of the program and
pass control to the list processor to
output your report,
which is this section right here.
So once the program's done everything It
can send the output to the screen for
the user to see.
Now just say, you see this down arrow
here.
I would just explain that one.
Up to now, we've been producing output on
the screen for the user to read.
Well these list screens can be interactive
as well.
So for example, if you wanted to drill
down on a report.
You can double-click a line or
double-click an individual field.
And the list processor will capture the
action and
fire the at selection screen event block.
And that's where you can include more code
to determine what the user clicked on and
then carry out some other activity, like
going to read some more tables
to find some more detailed information
that you can then output to the screen.
But we're not gonna dig into that.
We're gonna focus on the selection screen
and
making sure the user enters the right
values for our report.
And also make yourself a selection screen
as a good interface using various
text boxes and radio buttons that make our
program look a bit more inviting.