Our ABAP reports have two types of
screens.
There are selection screens and list
output screens, and
we have already used the output window to
produce list output screens.
So now, let's focus on the selection
screens themselves and
how we put individual fields on there,
like drop downs,
text boxes, radio buttons and so on.
For the user to enter values themselves.
Now, if you have used SAP at all,
you will know no doubt have used selection
screens already.
And just by looking at this course, you
can see a selection screen right now.
In transaction SE38 natural selection
screen that we see
has a textbox with a dropdown, has a
button, there's some radio buttons.
So, you know, we're gonna reproduce this
type of thing for our programs.
Everything that we produce will allow the
user to select data
to be used as parameters in our programs.
And when we produce selection screens, we
are actually creating dialogue screens.
But the beauty is we don't have to write
the actual dim pro code ourselves.
All we need to do is use specific ABAP
statements and and
the system will take care of all the
screen flow logic for us.
Now, as already mentioned, list screens
and
selection screens are both dialogue
programs.
Every dialogue program has at least one
dim pro
which is held in what's called a module
pool.
Now, a dim pro report program called
Standard Selection Screen,
is called and controlled automatically by
the runtime environment.
While the program is executed the dim pro
number itself is actually 1,000.
The user will only see the screen when the
programmer includes the parameters
in their program using specific ABAP
statements.
And it is these ABAP statements that cause
the screen to be generated
undisplayed to the user.
This means it's really simple for the
programmer to get started
writing their own programs without needing
to think about code to control the screen.
However, there are a few specific pieces
of information.
You need to understand in order to use
selection screens with your programs.
Which is what we are going to cover next.