We are now gonna move straight on, and
start looking at some of the ABAP
code that we will use to generate our
selection screens.
So I'll start by creating a brand new
program, I'll call this Z_SCREEN_1.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay, we have our blank reports.
And the first thing we're gonna do is have
a look at the initialization event.
If you remember, the initialization event
is the first thing that gets triggered in
our program, the first event block.
So, if we recall, we have a employee table
that we set up in the system.
And let's say, for our program, we would
like to know
the last employee number that was used to
create an employee record.
Now, the initialization event is the ideal
place for this type of code.
So we can find out what the last employee
number was, and
display to the user on the selection
screen, so
that they know not to select any values
greater than that last employee number.
So let's start off, we'll just Save, and
check everything.
Let's start off, and then declare the
table statement,
because what we're going to do is read
records from our z employees table.
So we'll declare the tables that we're
going to use, z employees.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And let's declare a data statement.
So we can hold the value of the last
employee number that has been used in
the table.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So wa_employees has like a work area.
We'll use the like statement to reference
our table, and
the field is going to be the employee
field.
Now, this is where we create our
initialization section.
So what we need to do is type in
initialization, and then we start writing
our code.
So, to get the last employee number, we'll
use a select statement,
let's just use a generic one, we'll select
all the fields even though,
all we need is the employee number field.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And because this is going to be a select
loop,
what we're going to do is populate our
work area field to be
wa_employee with a value of the employee
number from the table.
So we will say wa_employee
equals z_employees dash employee.
Then we will end our select statement, and
that's about it.
Let's just pretty it up or check.
Hm, that's a refreshing change, no, no
typos.
So what this is gonna do, when our program
is run, the run-time environment
will realize we have an initialization
event block, and
execute the code in this event block.
And that's gonna be select every record
from the z employees table, and populate,
our work area field to be y employee with
the employee number field.
And that's all there is to it.
Lets just test this piece out, that's what
we'll do,
is just a simple write statement, and we
will write out wa_employee to the screen.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now, just comment out the initialization,
so it's a standard program.
[SOUND] So I'll press F8 to execute, and
there you can see the last number being
used in our table.
So as a reminder, the select statement is
a loop, okay.
It's not picking up all the records, and
putting it in a table.
It's going to process the records one at a
time.
So what'll it do, it'll read the first
record, populate this work area field,
come to the end of the select statement,
and then start again.
And it'll continue that loop until the
last record in the table has been read.
And then it will write our wa employee
work at your variable to the screen.
So now, we have the last employee number
stored in a variable,
let's get rid of this write statement, and
put back in the initialization.
We can move on, and take a look at the at
selection screen event.
[BLANK_AUDIO]