So as a reminder, we've just done the
initialization section and
we'll now have a look at this at selection
screen event.
And remember I said this event is
triggered when
the user tries to execute the report.
The selection screen process that says,
hey if your program has an out selection
screen event,
let's execute that code before we go on to
the report processing itself.
So in our example, the at selection screen
is the ideal place for
us to check what value the user entered
into the screen for
the employee number selection field.
Now we haven't defined it yet, don't
worry, we will come to that,
but I'm just saying, you know, what,
what we're gonna do is write a logic to
check the value the user entered.
If it's incorrect, or, if it doesn't meet
the criteria we're checking against, we
can display a message on the screen to the
user, to tell them to correct that entry.
Now, the first thing I'm going to do is
add the parameter statement.
I'm not going to explain what the
parameter statement is right now.
That will come along in a few minutes'
time.
I just want to put it in there and all you
need to know is that's how we declare
a parameter that will appear on the
screen.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So I use parameters and, well I might as
well talk,
talk about it as I'm typing.
It's very much like the data statement.
I'm going to declare it a brand new
variable
called my_ee for employee and I'm going to
make it like the employee field in our
table.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now, we'll get down to writing the at
selection screen event.
So, below our initialization section,
let's type at selection screen.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And I'm going to use an addition here
called, on.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then the parameter.
So that indicates to the system,
this at selection screen event is
specifically for
this parameter field that we've declared.
And this is where I'd want to you know,
check to make sure the employee number.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
These are not greater.
Than the last employee number in our
table.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, I can do that with a simple if
statement.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And this is where we would display a
message to the user.
The entry you would put into the field is
greater than the maximum employee number
in the table.
And then we would finish it off with the
end if statement.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We will fill in these pieces shortly.
But for now, that's really the
pseudo-logic.
So because we store the last employee
number in memory,
we can then check with the at selection
screen event to make sure
the user has not entered a value greater
than our stored employee number.
If they have, we're gonna display a
message, and
that will present the screen to the user
again for them to re-enter the value.
Now you'll be able to see by the coding
here.
Remember Ilia mentioned that these event
blocks end implicitly,
meaning they end only when another event
block starts.
So this is an example of that.
The initialization section finishes when
we start
the at selection screen on my employee
events.
And this one will finish when we create a
brand new event below it.