Let's now step back and have a look at
this parameter statement.
Now just by the simple fact that we have
defined a brand new variable
called my_ee using the parameter
statement,
is enough to tell the system we are going
to generate our own selection screen.
And the parameter statement is all we need
to display a field on the screen.
Let me just make sure this program works.
And let's just display this one field on
the screen.
So there you can see, we've got my
employee, and we've got an entry field.
That's all it took, one statement.
Now let's go through it in a bit more
detail.
As I've said, it's very much like the data
statement.
We specify a new variable name.
We can make it a type, so we could say
type i for an integer.
Or just like I've done here, I've used the
like statement.
So it picks up the field attributes of the
employee field in
our tables at .employees.
Let's add a few more fields just as an
example to show you how this works.
[NOISE] So let's do my
[NOISE] put date of birth.
We'll make this like, I think it's DOB is
the field.
Let's give
it a check.
And there you can see we've got date of
birth field and
it's picking up the parameters.
And it's picking up the field attributes
from the table, and
it even gives us a field drop down box
where we can select a date.
How easy is that?
Then if we want to do an example without
using the like.
Say my number type i for integer.
Oops, what have I done?
Oh.
There's something I need to mention, when
you specify parameters,
you are limited to your parameter name
being a maximum of 8 characters.
And I think I just went over here.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, yeah.
So let's take off that e.
There we go.
My number.
And one other point is the parameter
statement can use any data type,
just like the data statement.
Apart from floating point numbers,
the floating point data time cannot be
used as a parameter.
You will have noticed when we showed the
fields on the screen,
that the screen automatically gives us a
text label here for
each field and it just uses our parameter
variable name by default.
And the order in which the fields are
displayed
are determined by how they are defined in
our program.
And, one other thing to see is,
notice how our available names have been
converted to uppercase.
This is the default action.
So, let's step back and clear some of
these example parameters out.
So we're back just to our employee number.
And let's take a look at some of the
additions we can use with
the parameter statement.
The first one is the default addition.
So we could write default.
One, two, three, four, five, six,
seven, eight.
And no surprises.
This is going to default this value Into
the field on the screen
as you can see here.
Now for those of you who are paying
attention,
the default statement actually isn't used
with the data statement.
For the data statement, we use the value
addition but for
parameters, we use default.
Now the default is only a suggestion.
The user can override the value.
You know there's nothing saying they have
to use that,
it's just a default value that we can
populate on the screen
maybe could down the amount of data we
want the user to enter on the screen.
Our next addition
is by making the field mandatory we can
use the addition obligatory.
So, with this addition, we have the
default and
we have the, the default value and then we
would just write, obligatory.
Let's just put these on a new line.
So it's easy to read.
See, you can see, this addition here when
executed forces this little tick box to
appear in the blank field.
See if I try to run the report, we'd get
this message box at the bottom, saying,
Make an entry in all required fields.
So we're telling the user you must put an
entry in this field.
It's a very useful addition.
Now, another addition is the value check
addition,
but I just wanna step back and let, let's
have another example of the parameter.
[SOUND].
Now I need to jog my memory, so I'm going
to open up a new session.
Have a look at our table.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay.
For this,
I'm going to use the ZEMPLOYEES2 table.
[SOUND].
And we're going to look at a field called
gender.
Let's make sure I've got everything
correct.
[NOISE].
Now with the gender field, notice when I
click on it, we get the drop down.
And this is because when we created this
table we actually
created some individual values that can be
used as
a drop-down list for entering data into
that table.
So when we use this field on a selection
screen,
the ABAP dictionary is working away in the
background,
helping to ensure any fields that we use
like this automatically
refer to any value help text or foreign
key relationships that
we've all ready set up to help the user to
select valid values.
Pretty cool, huh?
So let's go back and now here,
I think if we try and run this program and
put any old value in here.
So normally we would have to select M, F
or U.
Let's say I enter K.
We don't get any error message or
anything like that to say K is invalid.
The only help we get is to say, hey,
we've got some drop down values for you.
But this value check addition [SOUND]
allows us to include value checking.
[SOUND] So any entry we make into this
field,
the program will now check that entry
against a valid
value list that we have defined in the
ABAP dictionary.
Enter K, press enter and
there you can see, enter a valid value.
M, press enter, everything is good.
So that's the value check addition.
And of course you could add it on if we
had some values to check,
just at the end of this parameter as well.
So we have 3 separate additions all in a
row.
[SOUND].
So let's get rid of that for now.
And remove this entry for ZEMPLOYEES2.
Okay, the last addition is going to be the
lower case addition.
Remember I mentioned earlier that the
parameter statement
converts everything to uppercase.
We can get around this by using the lower
case addition.
So let's define a brand new parameter and
we'll be super original.
And use surname.
And make it like zemployees-surname field.
And we're going to add the default value.
[SOUND].
for Mr. Blogs, and then we're gonna say
lowercase.
[SOUND].
To demonstrate how this works and
how it's taken effect I'm going to enter
some lowercase letters.
And when I press the Enter key, nothing
happens.
We still have the uppercase and we still
have the lowercase letters in the field.
If we didn't have the value check addition
there,
these lowercase letters would all be
converted to uppercase.
Let me show you that.
[SOUND].
So, we'll take away that addition.
Activate our program.
And now when I put a load of lower case
letters in and press enter.
It converts them to upper-case.
Let's pop that back in.
And that's everything you really need to
know about parameters.
There are, there are a lot more additions
you can use but really what we've gone
through there Is probably 99% of what you
will see being used in SAP systems.
If you do want to look at any of the other
parameters, and this goes for
any ABAP statement, just click on the
field, press f1, and
up pops the ABAP help.
To help you understand about all the
different additions.
[BLANK_AUDIO]