The next thing we're going to look at, is
adding checkboxes to the screen.
I'm sure you are all familiar with the
checkbox, and
will agree, it makes data entry for your
users a very simple task.
The checkbox is just another form of a
parameter.
And there's a rule that the checkbox
always has to be of data type C,
a character with a length of 1.
And the content that gets stored in that
parameter, will either be an x, for
when it's checked, or it will be blank.
So let's have a look how we defined a
parameter.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's get rid of the surname field.
And we can add the new field.
Let's see.
What was what did we have in our table?
Well, we didn't have one.
Let's just define a, a standard field.
Oops!
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's call this my_box1.
And it's gonna be of type c.
So, you know, we don't have to declare it.
All we have to do, is say the parameter
name, and
include as, check box.
And that is it.
Simple.
Let's check our code, activate, and then
we can see it on the screen.
Notice how this field is displayed
differently to the other parameter fields.
Yes it's a checkbox, but the label for
the checkbox is now on the right hand
side, with the entry field on the left.
But apart from that there's not much
difference.
If we don't enter a value, in other words
we don't click the box, then the my box
one parameter, the variable will hold a
blank character.
If we do tick it, it's going to hold a
value of X.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
That's as complicated as check boxes get.
So now, let's move on and have a look at
radio buttons.
Now radio buttons are another common
method
of controlling the values that get stored
in our fields.
A normal parameter field allows you to
enter any value.
A check box parameter allows you to enter
one or two values, an X or a blank.
Now when it comes to radio buttons,
they're very similar to checkboxes,
but checkboxes, they are individual
parameters in their own right.
So you can have many checkboxes and select
many checkboxes on the screen.
But radio buttons have to belong to a
group
in which only one radio button can be
selected at any one time.
And the way we define radio buttons, is
very similar to checkboxes.
They have to be of data types C, and a
length of 1.
And because they belong to a group, let's
say a group of three radio buttons,
we would define three individual parameter
fields.
Let's have a look at an example.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So we'll define the new parameter, but
this time,
we structure it a little bit differently.
Let's work with colors.
So let's say we're gonna define a radio
button representing the color green.
So we key in the parameter variable name,
but then we follow it with-
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Radio button group to define we're making
a group of radio buttons,
and then we give the group a name.
And let's just call it group 1.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Then we define our second field.
This time we'll define blue.
Exactly the same thing.
lt's a radio button.
[LAUGH] Look at that.
It's a radio butoon, apparently.
There we go.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And again, this belongs to group 1.
And finally-
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Mister yellow.
Let's line him up as well.
And again, that's part of group one.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now because I'm using the chain command
with the parameter statement,
got to have commas there.
So that's it.
That's how we define a group of radio
buttons, where we will limit the user
entry, just to one value in the group.
So let's check our code.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
I do apologize.
And it looks like I've gone a bit too long
with yellow.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, I'm afraid yellow is gonna have to go.
And we'll choose red.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we'll activate it, and now test.
And as you can see, we have the radio
buttons, and
these follow the same conventions as a
normal parameter,
in that we have the label on the left, and
then the entry field, and the radio button
on the right hand side.
And as you can see, by selecting any of
the radio buttons,
we can only ever have one value.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And that just about sums up the parameter
statements.
You've seen we can have normal input
boxes,
we can have drop down buttons that define
through the ABAP dictionary.
We can have uppercase, lowercase, we can
check the values,
we can make them mandatory fields by using
the obligatory addition,
and also our default values, along with
the checkbox and radio buttons.
It's quite a good selection and that
[UNKNOWN] covers every source scenario you
are likely to come across for individual
field entry on the report screen.
Now next up, we're gonna have a look at
something called Select Options.
Now parameters, they can be looked at as
simple screen entry fields,
where the SELECT options, let's call them
complex screen option fields,
but they're not really complex, but
they're super flexible, and
they have a lot of functionality built
into them.
[BLANK_AUDIO]