So we have looked at parameters, and now
we're gonna take a look at select-options.
Now parameters are fantastic for
letting the user select individual values
that we want to filter on in our reports.
But what do we do when we want to allow a
range of values on multiple
individual values?
Well it would be incorrect to create lots
of separate
parameters to store these values all based
on the same field.
So this is where the select-option
statement comes into play.
Now the first thing we need to consider
when using a select-option,
is that we're going to be using internal
tables
to start our values that use entering into
the fields.
A much more detailed discussion on how we
create internal tables is coming up.
But for now, we will just deal with what
we need to know.
To use the select-options statement in our
program.
So when an individual user wants to enter
multiple individual values or select
a value range we need to install them in a
table in memory that our program can use.
An internal table we create for a select
table has a similar restriction to
parameters in that we can only give them a
name of up to eight characters in length.
And the select tables themselves contain
four separate fields,
which get defined when we create our
select-option statement.
These fields are sign,
option, low, and high.
So before going any further, let's get
these down in our program,
just so you've got something to reference
as I'm talking.
So I said when we use a select-option
statement,
we have these four fields, SIGN, OPTION,
LOW, and HIGH.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
When a user makes a choice by filling in a
selection field on the screen,
whether that is a single value or range of
values,
a record is generated, and put into this
internal table.
And because it's a table,
this allows the user to enter as many
records, as they wish.
And all these records will be used to
filter our data.
So let's now get a little more granular,
and
have a look at each one of these fields in
the internal table.
Now the sign field has a data type of c, a
character, with a length of one.
The data stored in this field determines,
for each record, whether or not the record
is to be included or excluded from the
result set that our report selects.
And the possible values that get stored in
this field are I and E.
Now, I stands for inclusive, so we are
including the criteria, and
E stands for exclusive, it's an exclusion
criteria.
At the options field also has a type of c
character,
but this one has a length of two.
And this field holds the selection
operator.
So for example it can hold a value of EQ
for equals and E for not equals.
GT, I'm sure you can work these out.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we have a couple of special ones CP,
and lastly, NP.
And as you can see they're the same type
of logical operators as those
that are used for logical expressions, but
CP and
NP do not have the full functional scope
they have in normal logical expressions.
Now if wild card characters are entered
onto the selection screen,
the system will automatically use the
operator CP.
Now the low field is used to enter the
lower limit for
a range of values that a user can enter.
And you might guess, the high field is
used as the upper limit for
a range of values.
Now both of these are low and high fields.
The data type is determined by the
database table
to which our selection criteria is linked.
So the data type will vary.
If the field we are selecting on is an
integer,
they will take on the data type of an
integer.
If it's a character, they'll use a
character data type.
When we define our select-options, we can
of course refer to fields
in the database table as well as defining
individual fields in our program.
When we define a select-option field that
refers to a database table field,
the attributes of that field will
automatically
apply to the input fields on the selection
screen.
Why would we use a Select-Option instead
of a parameter?
Well if you recall back on our z employees
table we created,
one of the fields is data birth.
Now we could create a parameter on the
date of birth field, and
have the user enter a date of birth that
we could then use in our program to select
data from a database table.
But you know, the date of birth field is
very, very unique.
Most of the records in our database table
are going to have a unique date of birth.
So if we use this field where, at best,
we can get one record returned for our
program, and it's not flexible,
we would require the user to know the
exact date of birth of an employee.
Whereas, if we use a select-option we can
give the user
the functionality to allow them to use
wild cards.
They can use date ranges to select
employees.
You know, they could say the first of
January 1960,
to the 31st of December 1980, and return a
whole bunch of records.
They can exclude certain values, and they
exclude ranges of values too.
The select-option is so much more
functional in a single parameter field.
You'll find users requesting this type of
input field a lot more than the standard
parameter.
So enough of the talk,
let's get straight on to having a look at
how we define select-options.
So let me clear out, this piece of text,
[SOUND] and we'll come back up here and
then just below parameters we can take a
look at the syntax.
So I just mentioned the date of birth
field, so let's use that as our example.
So the way we define a select option is
simply by typing select-options.
Then we declare the field we are going to
use for
our select-option, so let's say, my date
of birth.
Then just after the parameters, we have to
identify the field type.
For the select-option.
And this is where we include FOR and
then we can say zemployees, and I think
it's zdob.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And if we say this, and I'll just double
check.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Oh, it's not z dob, it's just dob.
And just pretty it up, and
there we go that's all you need to do to
define a selection-option field.
Let's have a look at how it gets displayed
on the screen.
So, I'll just execute the program.
Oop, after I've activated it.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Oop, we have some errors.
Oh, I didn't take away all the rubbish
text.
There we go.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let me just get rid of this other program
I was working on.
So now it's active, we can execute, and
here we go.
You can see the my date of birth field,
that we just declared.
And you can see, we have two fields we can
input, and a button.
Users can now entire a single value into
the low field,
which is this one on the left, and
they can also enter a value into the right
hand field which is the high field.
So just by having these two fields
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's do this, we can have a range, so
now our select-option low field will
contain the 1st of July,
and the high field will contain the 30th
of July.
Now if a user didn't enter anything into
this field,
and our table is going to be blank.
It won't have, any records generated.
And you might be wondering what's that
button on the right?
Well this is where, we get a load more
functionality.
Let me click it and then, I will explain.
So now we get this pop-up box.
And as you can see we got four tabs along
the top.
Here we can enter individual single values
for this field.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And it doesn't matter what sequence you
put them in.
You can enter as many individual values as
you wish.
And also, hopefully you're familiar with
how these work, but if you have let's
say a, a 50 entries, 50 single values you
want to put in there,
that you are having a spreadsheet or
something like that.
You can copy those values to the
clipboard.
Click on an empty line, and just Paste
them in.
So you got functionality down here, to
allow you to Paste, Remove records,
Delete every record there is on the
screen.
So go through these and have a look.
Now, let's move on to the next hub.
And this is ranges.
To where we could enter a single range,
and now a first low and high value here.
We can actually go to ranges, and enter
multiple range values.
So we could say, the 1st of May to the 5th
of May, and
the 10th of May to the 15th of May, and so
on.
Now, you'll notice, two of these tabs have
got the green square,
and then two have got red circles.
So the green, that indicates we're gonna
include values in our selection criteria.
And if we click on to the red, any values
we enter here, will be excluded.
So the internal table, if we step back to
it.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
As I mentioned previously as a sign field,
an option field,
a high, sorry, it's a low first then a
high.
So by filling in those field on the green
square tabs,
our sign field will get filled with the
inclusion.
And if we fill in anything on the red
circle tabs this value
will be equal to E indicating we're gonna
exclude values.
And we'll just comment that out, and we'll
go back to the screen again.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Actually, let's step back here.
Now, the other thing to highlight is these
fields.
I mentioned you can include wildcard
characters and things like that, but you
can also include the logical operators, so
remember we have the option field.
If I right-click here, and choose Options
then we get a list of logical operators
that we can assign to the individual
fields on our select-option records so by
default.
It's always going to use the equal sign.
But if we want it to say less than or
equal to, we can double-click, and
we get the little graphical representation
of less than and equal to,
and then we can fill in the value.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And the same on the two, just right click
select-option, and
you can choose any you want.
And you'll notice, we also have the, the
green and the red options down here.
So it's include or exclude.
Just as we have on this single line,
you'll bring up the multiple selection
dialog box.
You can see it's carried through the
single selection, and
as with the other terms, we can do exactly
the same type of thing.
Just instead of right clicking, we just
click on the little button at the side.
And it will bring up the select-options.
[BLANK_AUDIO]