We already have our select option defined,
so let's start some code.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
We'll go to the end and all I'm going to
do,
is recreate the select statements.
Select star from z employees, so
here, we're creating a loop.
I'll put the n select in.
And now, I'll include an if statement.
If, for z employee record,
date of birth field.
In my DOB.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
We will just write out the full record to
the screen.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
So now we have this code.
Let's just format it correctly,
ended up with our full stock.
There we go.
So what this is going to do is
select all the records from the employee
file if our date of birth
matches any record from our select option.
So don't forget we can have, we could have
20 different Individual records here,
with a mix of single values, a range of
values to include,
a range of values to exclude, and
maybe a, a list of individual V\values to
exclude as well.
Well just by using this in operator, the
system will take care of the selection for
us, it will do all the work that is
required to only return true if
the employees date of birth doesn't meet
the criteria set up in the internal table.
And we will then write out the record onto
the screen.
So let's debug this code and we can see it
step by step and you can see how
the internal table for the select option
for my date of birth, gets filled up.
Now first of all, I'm just gonna comment
out some code.
[SOUND] Take this out and we'll take,
take these out as well.
Just so we've got our very simple select
option.
[BLANK AUDIO].
I got attack of the typos once again.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
What have I got here?
Select start from, oh, look at that.
We need the fingers don't seem to be
working quite correct.
There we go.
I'll stick a break point here as well.
Now we'll execute the code.
So first of all, we get presented with the
select screen, and what I'm gonna do
is not enter anything into date of birth,
just so you can see what's presented.
I'll press F8 to execute.
Now, we come to the break point.
And if I double click my DOB.
We can see, by this icon here, it actually
represents an internal table.
So I'll double click them.
And now, you can see the individual
fields.
And make up this table.
The heart symbol and we will come to
later, that represents a header line.
And then, here, we would have the
individual entries.
One for each record that makes a power
select option.
But because we didn't enter anything,
we've got no records here.
So, I'm just going to F5.
We should loop through the table and
output every record.
It shouldn't be too many, five or six.
There we go.
And I'll just make a note of the date of
births here.
So we've got 1969, 77, 58.
So we've ranged from 58 up to 2000.
Just so I know what to use in the
selection criteria.
Now, let's run it again.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
And, this time, we'll fill in a value.
So let's say, greater than.
Now, I'll tell you what.
F8.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
Let me pick a specific date.
Let's choose this guy here.
All into one value,
of course one two what was
the value 021258.
F8, now we will look
at date of birth [SOUND].
And now you can see we are one record.
The sign has been included, that's the
inclusion.
And we're saying equal to, and there's our
date-of-birth field in the low field.
So now when we step through our code, the
if statement
gets evaluated.
We'll go
back to fields and show the employee's
DOB.
We can make out individual entries right
here, so this is 18th of November,
1969, and you can see what the 2nd of
December 58.
So this shouldn't match.
And it doesn't.
And it skips straight through.
Our next record shouldn't match either.
This one does match
week of the second of December.
And as you can see, using this N operator.
A statement has been evaluated as true.
So therefore we will write a record to
this screen.
I just zoomed through, and I guess we will
see one record display on the screen.
And there we go.
Let's run it again.
And we'll include some more options.
So the first thing we did, was that one.
Let's click the multiple selection tool.
[SOUND] And you know what, I forgot on the
other values.
[LAUGH] I need to open another session.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
Let's put this over here, and z employees.
[BLANK AUDIO].
There we go.
Now lets just change this a little bit,
choose fields now all I want is the data
birth field, with the employee.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
That part there.
Shorten this one.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
That's all we need.
Now, go to the multiple selection tool.
I will also choose the 13th of December.
[SOUND] And then let's exclude,
how many dates have we got.
58 to 92.
Let's exclude [SOUND].
First of January, 1999.
To the 20th of December 2002.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
Click execute, and just a note, when you
do fill additional entries in,
on the multiple selection screen, the icon
does change.
We have this little green square to
indicate we have got multiple selections.
So I will execute and now we will take a
look at the my date of birth table.
That's the first record.
Let's do this.
So now we can see the three entries.
The first one which we saw before.
And the second one and
the multiple selection screen and we can
see it's the same.
It's the inclusion equals to sine.
And then we have a range that we are
excluding.
So, you can see we are excluding the first
of January 99.
The 20th of December, 2002.
And bt, that equals between, so between
this date, and this date.
So now when our if statement gets
evaluated, just this simple, in operator,
triggers the system to automatically check
all the records in this internal table.
And if you ask me, I think that's really,
really neat.
Because you just don't have to think about
All the different type of logic,
the different permutations you would have
to code for
yourself to be able to check against all
these different types of entries.
You can just say, if our field, in, then
the select option field.
And that's it, all of your logic is done.
So F8, and then we get to records return.