As with most ABAP statements in SAP,
we have a number of additions we can
include with the select option statement.
So let's have a look at those.
So very similar to the parameters
statement,
the select options also has
the obligatory [SOUND] also lower case
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And some more, but they are very similar
to the parameters, so
we don't really need to go through them.
They all work in exactly the same way, no
difference whatsoever.
Now the one thing I do want to discuss
though,
is a no extensions edition.
This allows us to prevent the use of
making multiple selections.
So we can still give the user the ability
to make our value range selection.
But we can stop them from entering
multiple value ranges
and it's quite straightforward.
This is how we do it.
All we do is our no extensions onto
our sort option statement.
[SOUND] Let's activate our code take a
look and low and behold.
That additional button has now
disappeared.
We can still do our individual value and
include one range.