We have covered parameters and select
options.
And no doubt, you will have noticed that
each field on the selection screen
contains the technical name of the field
which we declared in our program.
Let's have a look how we can change that.
Our program still needs to reference these
types of fields, using the technical name.
But the user always prefers to see the
descriptive text.
And to do this, we may use a special text
element called selection text.
Now, as you know, every ABAP program is
made up of its own sub-objects.
Like text elements.
If we go back to the SE-38 screen, you can
see here, that when we create our program,
or probably a better example is when we
choose copy.
Let's create one called screens three.
You can see here, it's saying, do you want
to copy these sub-objects,
the documents, the variants, user
interface, screens and includes?
Well notice we have got two types of
objects.
They are always copied no matter what you
select on the screen.
First one is obvious, it's the source
code, but
then the next one is the text elements.
And your text elements that you create for
your program,
belong to your program, and that's why
they have to be copied across.
So let me cancel this and we'll just go
back into our original program.
Now when we create text elements, we
create them in what are called text pools.
And these text pools hold all the text
elements of our program.
Now every program that we create is
language independent.
This means we create text elements for our
program.
That can be quickly and easily translated
into other languages,
without the need for changing our source
code.
There are three kinds of text elements
that we can use in our program.
I've already hinted at one called
selection text, but
there are two others, text symbols and
list headings.
Now tech symbols, these are text elements
that we can create for
our program, to give us some flexibility
so
we don't have to have code literals into
our source code.
We can use these text symbols instead.
List headings.
Well as you might guess from the name,
when building reports,
we create report headers.
You know, the title and field names, or
column headings and that type of thing.
By using list headings instead of hard
coding the headings into our program,
we can ensure they get translated into any
of the languages we need.
And also if the headings have to change
later on, but we can just go in and
change the list headings text elements,
instead of changing the source code.
And the last one, selection text, this is
what we're working on right now.
And this is where you can display text
elements on the screen, so
that the user doesn't have to see the
technical name,
as we've seen in all of our examples up to
now.
So sticking with selection texts, as with
many things in SAP,
there are many different ways we can
navigate to the screen where we create and
change these text elements.
Again, I'll step back to SE-38, and you
can see we have an option for
creating text elements from this screen.
Now alternatively, if you are in your
program,
like we are now, you can use the Go To
menu,
select text elements, and go to selection
text from there.
And as you can see, the other two, list
headings and
text symbols can also be navigated to from
this menu.
So let's click on selection texts, and
notice anything familiar?
Well the fields that appear here on the
left hand side in the screen,
they're the technical names for the fields
we defined for our program.
Let's step back and have a look.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Oops.
So here's our program.
We have parameters, we have my employee,
my box one,
the [UNKNOWN] green, blue and red.
Let's go back to the text elements.
And there you can see it.
My employee, my box one, and we've got my
date of birth as well,
I didn't see that one.
But we have DWA green, blue and red.
So, the system automatically knows that
you've declared parameters and
select options.
Fills in records here, and all it requires
is for you to enter some descriptive text.
Now, there's one thing to notice here.
We have this third column, that refers to
dictionary references.
And what this is, it's recognizing that
some of your fields refer to field
setup in the about dictionary, and we're
able to use this chatbox button.
So when I click this, and choose Save,
notice how it brings the actual field name
from the ABAP dictionary.
You know, the table we created earlier,
and just populates it for us.
This is one of the beauties of an SAP
system.
Everything works together.
So we don't have to declare our own text
for these fields.
Now you can of course choose not to use
these dictionary objects,
and just overwrite them yourself, put in
any text you want.
But why bother?
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now for the others, all we need to do, is
just key in the text ourselves.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We'll have blue and we'll have green, and
red.
And just before we leave this screen, I'll
just say,
you're limited to 30 characters in length
for your text element.
So just bear that in mind.
Now before these text elements can be
used, just like programs and
dictionary objects, we need to activate
our text elements,
which will automatically save them into
the text pool for our programs to use.
So I just activate, job done, and come
back.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now when we run our program,
we can see the proper text coming through
that we declared in our text elements.
And you know what?
That's as difficult as it gets.
So just remember, when you're declaring
screen elements, your parameter
select options, just go to your text
elements, key in the text you want, and
then it will be dragged through to the
screen automatically.
[BLANK_AUDIO]