[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now if you've used SAP systems for any
length of time,
you will be familiar with variants.
Now for those that haven't used variants,
it's really simple.
I'm just gonna run our program again and
just show you our screen.
Now, when we fill in values, so we can
fill in,
any values we want, let's just say this
one,
we have the option of saving all the
entries we make in this screen.
And the object that we save, we call a
variant.
So once you make your selections and click
the save button,
this allows you to save a variant.
Now, just click save.
Oops, give it a name, Z1.
Oops, oops.
I'll need to give it a description.
That's it.
Now all of that has been saved.
So what that allows us to do is next time
when we come back to our program,
when we have a default screen we now have
this button up here.
Get variance we can click that, select the
variant we want,
and then it will populate the screen for
us.
And that's it that's what a variant is,
now what we've just done there
is what a user normally does.
They would make their screen entries, then
click the save button and
save the variant.
But I want to show you some other ways of
creating variants and
go through some of the specific properties
of variants that can be useful for
us when creating programs.
So, first of all, back at the se38 screen
We have the variance button.
And if we choose create, we can enter a
brand new variant name.
Choose the create button.
He shows us our screen.
We can make our entries.
Give it a description.
Click save.
And we're done.
We have another variant.
And if I do a drop down, you can see
there's the first and
the second one we've just created.
Let me step back.
Now what I suggest is when you're creating
your program,
you create your variants this way.
It's just cleaner and if we go in,
we have this additional screen where we
can work with the variant.
Now what I'm gonna do, is select one, and
then we're gonna choose change.
These are the values, let's step back, we
got attributes as well.
Attributes take you into this second
screen.
If you go to the values then do change,
you then have the option of clicking the
variants attributes button from there.
Now let's work our way down this screen
and
have a look at the different attributes,
of the variant.
Well first of all, we have only for
background processing and when we create
ABAP programs, quite often these programs,
they might not be report programs.
They might just be batch jobs.
And we really only want to run them in the
background.
Maybe we only want to trigger them in the
early hours of the morning,
to do some batch updates when no one else
is around using they system.
Well, we can save variance for those types
of programs, and
specify, only allow this variant to be
used
when the program is being run as a batch
job in the background.
And when this happens, that means we don't
have to have the program on the screen.
We can schedule the job to run overnight,
by itself, without having to monitor it.
The next option is protect variant,and
this allows us,
as you might guess, to protect the
variant.
It stops other users from being able to
select the variant,
and using it on their reports.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The next option down, only display in
catalog.
Well, this basically makes the variant
inactive.
The variant will exist, but when a user
does an F4 drop down to have
a look at the list of variants, it won't
show in the list.
Now moving on down, we have this section
in the middle, field attributes.
And if we work from left to right, which
means bottom to top, we can see,
we can protect an individual field that is
displayed on our screen.
We can hide a field, this one, and
we have another hide field, and selection
variable,
save fields without values, switch GPA
off, and required field.
Have a play around with these.
I mean, things like your required field,
it will make field mandatory, so
it has to be filled in.
You can see we already made Employee
Number mandatory.
So the users can do this themselves with
variance.
Now in case you're wondering, the P and S
down here,
P represents Parameter, and S is Select
option.
Now just as a little practice, let's use
some of these.
And let's protect a field so that we can't
change the values.
Let's protect date of birth.
Oops.
Click Save.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now, when we come back and run our
reports, oops, wrong one.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we'll choose our variants.
Oh, it looks as though [LAUGH] I hid the
variant, did I?
Hm.
Z1, change, oh, I did, didn't I?
Let's take that off and that one and that
one.
Click save.
And we've still go the, protected data
birth field.
Go to our source code, run our program,
and now we can select variant.
Now, see we protected date of birth, it's
grayed out.
We can't make any entries in there.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
If we load another variant, and it opens
it up.
So have a play around with variants.
They're very useful and when you have
large selection screens,
you'll find that users create loads of
variants.
So if you've got 30 fields to fill in, or
maybe you got 30 fields on the screen but
only need to fill in.
Say six or seven.
Users save variance so that other users
can pick them up and
use them without having to really fully
understand everything on the screen.
Every month they may save a variant that
the rest of the team may use.
So they are all consistent when running
the reports.
By using the different options, the
different attributes of the variance,
they can remove fields to make it look a
lot easier.
They can protect fields.
They can define default values and then
hide the fields, so
that when other users are in the reports,
it doesn't look so complicated.
They're really useful parts of the system.
There are various ways we can start a
report with a variant.
Now, from this SE38 screen, we can see
a with a variant execution button up here,
I think that's shift F6.
Yeah, that's right.
So when we click this one, it says choose
a variant.
Green tick.
And it starts it automatically.
But you know, a user won't normally have
access to SE38.
This is really only useful for us in a
development environment.
When a user runs a transaction in SAP,
they usually select the transaction from
the SAP menu tree, or
they enter the transaction code, in the
top left hand corner of the screen.
Now another way of running a report,
is by the user going to the system menu
and then the services option.
And choosing Reporting from there.
So they'll go System, Services and choose
Reporting.
Now this is like a real cut down version
of SE38.
Takes away all the added in functionality.
And just allows them to select the
program.
And then they can choose to execute it
directly or start with a variant.
Now most users will run our program
directly and
then load a variant up.
Now by using the go to menu as well as our
little variant button,
we can choose the variant option, and we
choose get.
Then that'll display a list of variants
for us to use.
Once a variant's loaded up, then the user
and you, can just execute the program.