There are a couple more things we need to
look at to complete covering text objects
in general to enable you to completely set
up your own selection screens for
your programs.
These are text symbols and messages.
So what are these?
Well, text symbols were used to replace
literals in our program.
For example, when we use the right
statement, we can choose to use text
symbols, which will enable us to reuse
text we have already set up.
And it gives us the added functionality of
being able to use translated text
within our program.
So basically we stay away from using any
hard coded literals in our program, and
use text symbols instead.
Now let me go back into SE-38.
And we'll have a look at our program.
And we'll discuss, well, what are text
symbols.
Well, quite simply, they are just place
holders for text
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Instead of having a write statement such
as [NOISE] let's say,
write new line surname as a title,
we can use a text symbol instead.
And we would do this by creating our right
statement again,
but instead of having a literal same
surname,
we would say use text dash and then a
number.
And this represents a text symbol that we
can set up.
Now it's important you take note how the
text symbol is declared.
You must use text, which is this word
here,
followed by a three digit number.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] You are allowed to use up to 1,000
text symbols in your program,
of which each one can be translated into
as many languages as you wish.
Now, there is a limitation to the length
of a text symbol and
that's 132 characters.
But as you can imagine, that's probably
enough for
any situation you'll come up against.
Now we have already seen how to get to
text elements
by using the menus when we had a look at
selection text.
But there is also another way we can get
to it.
And that's by using forward navigation.
So because I have just used this text
double one, I can use forward
navigation just like when we did with
creating a database table.
You know, when we created the data
elements and
the fields, we use forward navigation to
actually create objects.
We can do the same here.
So all I'll need to do is double-click
this text-001.
And now the system says do you want to
create the object.
We'll choose Yes.
And yes, we'll save the program first so
we don't lose it.
And now it takes us straight into our text
element screen.
You can see it's using the code 001 that
we defined in the program, and
now all we need to do is enter some basic
text into this field.
Now, previously we used surname as our
text, so let's do the same.
[SOUND] Let's just use surname.
The field here on the right, D-length,
that's just the length.
I've just pressed enter, and
that's just the length of the text that
we've keyed in.
In the field on the far right is the
maximum length.
So let's activate this object.
Now we can step back to our program.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And what I'll do, just in this example,
let's just remove the select statements.
What else have we got in the program?
That's fine.
We'll leave the selection screen in and
we'll run this report and then you'll see
the word surname output twice.
First by our write statement outputting a
literal, and
then by who's using the text symbol.
I'll activate the program.
Press F8, click execute, and there you can
see, surname is output twice.
First by the literal and then by our tech
symbol.
So as you can see, tech symbols are super
easy, super easy to define and set up.
And I advise you do use them wherever you
can,
because if you ever need to change any
text that you have up on the screen,
you can just change the text symbol value
without having to recompile your program.
And plus, it has the added benefit of
allowing you to use translations for
other languages