Now moving on, the next thing we'll look
at, is messages.
When we want to provide feedback to the
user,
we could use literals in our program.
But I'm sure you know by now, we don't
wanna be doing this.
We need to avoid using literals where we
can.
So, that we don't have to recompile our
program every time they change.
And plus.
We also want to allow the facility for
our messages to be translated into other
languages.
So how do we use messages?
Well the first thing we need to do,
we need to store our messages in what we
call a message class.
Which in turn gets stored in a database
table called T100.
Let's have a look at T100.
I'll open up a new session.
Go to se11, t100.
Choose display.
And there we can see this table, called
messages.
And it only contains four fields.
Lets have a look at the contents, so it's
easier to understand.
And here we go.
You can see we have a language key.
D represents German language.
We have an application area and we have a
message code and then the actual text
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, let's go to the message to your screen
right now.
Now we can if we have messages already
existing is to go to,
on the messages option, go to create new
messages.
You can either use forward navigation or
go directly to transaction SE91.
Now, the messages we create get stored
within message classes.
So, when we create messages, we need to
create a message class.
And when creating a message class,
you need to take into account the customer
name space rules.
So, this means for us, start with the
letter zed.
And for this example,
I'm just gonna do zmes1.
Now, we'll leave the messages radio button
selected, and I'll choose create.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now it's important to realize, and keep in
mind, that messages are different
from text elements in that they are not
objects that are part of your program.
Messages are stored within the table we
just looked at, table T100.
And because of this, we can reuse messages
across any number of programs.
Now back to this screen.
When you first create a message class, you
have to fill in the attributes.
Now I'll just give it some short text.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then we save it and it'll ask for a
transport.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And once it's saved we can then click on
the messages tab.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And key in the messages.
So let's create a message, and if you
remember back to our program,
let's see if we can jump back to it.
>> [BLANK_AUDIO]
We have a selection screen, where we're
looking for an employee number.
We have some radio buttons then we have a
selection option for date of birth.
Well, some time back, we created this app
selection screen event.
So let's bring this back in.
And this is where we can check.
To make sure,
the employee number is not greater than
the last employee number in our table.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, in that case, we need to bring back in
our initialization section.
So, remember, this is going to be run as
soon as the program is run, and
it will store the last employee number in
this variable, wa_employee.
And when the selection screen is shown, we
can do this check.
If the value the user entered is greater
than
the employee number we have stored in
wa_employee, we can display a message.
So what message do we display?
Well, let's go here and we can key in a
message that's going to tell
the user that the employee number they
entered on for the screen is too
high in value and they need to choose a
lower one so we can just type.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Employee number is too high.
And click save.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So let's go back to our program and
take a look how we can use this message
within our code.
So we just need to locate the line where
we need to put the message,
which is right here, and key in the
relevant number.
Now before we do, I want to tell you about
the different message types that we can
use in the program.
Now, I have graphic here that comes from
the SAP website
that lists the message types and you can
see we have A, E, I, S, W, X.
So A, a termination message.
You can just read the text here.
And it just tells you a message is thrown
up and then the program terminates.
Next one is E, error message.
And this is the one we're gonna use in our
example.
Because we want to tell the user this is
an error.
But depending on where we use this,
it can have a different effect within our
program.
We're gonna use it in the selection string
event.
So, what's gonna happen is processing of
the event will stop, the message
will be shown on the screen, and the user
will be able to amend their entry.
When they press execute or
press Enter, the add selection screen
event will fire again.
And then the if statements will
test the condition to see if the user
entered the correct values.
if it's incorrect again, another error
message will be shown on the screen.
If everything's okay, then processing will
continue.
Now if we used an error message outside of
an event like the at selection screen,
let's just say it was in the body of the
program.
Well this would cause our program to
close.
So you've got to be aware of where you're
using this type of message.
And you can read the rest here, we have
information status warning and
an exist again.
So let's get back to our example.
And we'll put in the code for displaying
the message.
Now it's really easy if we refer back to
our message class.
Let's make it a bit smaller.
And we'll pop it over here.
Our message class is ZMES1.
Now our message is three zeros.
So down here in the code,
[SOUND] we would write [SOUND] Message.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Then the message type.
And in this case it's going to be an error
represented by the E.
And then the message number which is three
zeroes.
And then, open bracket, and we put the
message class.
ZMES1.
Close bracket, full stop.
And that's it.
That's all there is to displaying
messages.
So, let's check our code,
make sure everything's correct [LAUGH]
and
of course, it's not so we'll just make
that into a comment.
Like it should be.
Okay.
Everything is good.
We'll activate the program and now we'll
test it out.
And what I'll do, I'll put a break point
here.
So we can see the code in action.
Now press F8 to start.
So just as a note, first of all we'll have
the initialization section,
that'll execute and load up the last
employee number.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay, now.
We do have a default value, which is
greater than our highest
number in the table, but because the user
hasn't triggered any action yet,
our error message hasn't kicked in.
Which means the app selection screen event
hasn't fired.
So let's just key in 55555.
Now press Enter.
And just by pressing Enter, that's caused
this event to trigger,
app selection screen and don't forget
we're basing it on the employee field.
And now we're gonna check our condition.
So double click my_ee.
There's the fives, that we've entered.
Our highest number in our work area
employee.
As you can see, is one lots of zeros and
six.
So this should trigger our message.
I will press F8.
And there, there you can see at the bottom
of the screen we
have an error message, employee number is
too high.
And that just represents what we keyed in
for the message text.
So that's it.
That's how you can use messages
within your program to prompt the user to
do something or
tell them why a program was terminated, or
just for information purposes.
So one thing, because it's an error
message here, oops,
sorry, I pressed Enter again.
Okay, it's forcing us to enter a good
employee number, so I'm just gonna do one.
And this one, and now it should be good.
I'll press Enter again.
It's doing this event.
I'll press F5 to step through.
And that's it, it's just gone through the
program, the error message wasn't
triggered, so the error message has now
disappeared from the screen.
I'll step back out, and we'll get rid of
this break point.
Now before moving on,
let's talk about the addition that we can
include with our messages.
And the addition for messages that we're
gonna discuss, uses the word with.
And then we can specify a field.
Now this width addition is very handy, it
allows us to include up to
four different operands, or parameters,
that we can pass into our message.
So, for example, here,
we're displaying an error message, based
on the employee number field.
Well we can actually include the value
that the user entered onto the screen,
to display inside our message.
And the way we do this
is by first of all making sure we have an
error message that can accept parameters.
So let's bring this across, and let's
create duplicate of this.
Let's use error message 001.
And what we need to do, is edit this
message with the ampersand character.
So, I'm going to say the employee number.
And then we'll put the ampersand here.
Is too hard.
So, in effect that will insert the
employee number,
the user entered onto the screen and we
captured in
our my_ee variable, so let's save this
message, move
it out of the way come back to our code.
And now, with this with addition, all I
need to do is send
my_ee into the message.
So it's gonna display the message saying,
with my_ee variable.
Let's do a code check.
Execute.
I won't do a break point this time, we'll
just execute the program.
Let's key in our fives, now press Enter.
And it didn't work.
Why didn't it work?
Oh I know, sorry.
My mistake.
We're using the wrong message number.
So we created a new message number.
Zero zero one, so we need to specify that
in our program,
I will activate it again, fingers crossed
its gonna work this time.
Press Enter and there we can see, employee
number five's is too high.
That much is exactly with the message we
set up.
[NOISE].
Now, this, with addition to the messages
statement,
allows you to send up to four different
parameters into your message.
You'll find this type of error reporting
throughout lots and
lots of programs in SAP, and you'll find
that there are hundreds,
if not thousands of different messages set
up all throughout the system.
And remember, because messages can be used
across all programs.
It makes sense to see if there is some
messages already set up
by colleagues that you can reuse.
They'll be standard message classes set up
for HR,
finance, and different other modules of
SAP systems.
That you can probably go into, have a
look, and
reuse those message classes and the
individual messages inside.
That wraps up messages.
Let's move on.
[BLANK_AUDIO]