We will now take a look at how we can
format our selection screens.
And this will help us make our selection
screens look a lot more attractive and
intuitive to the user.
You already know how to make parameters
and select options appear on the screen,
but you haven't included any specific
layout options.
Yes, you have seen the objects on the
screen,
but the system has determined where it
places them all itself.
And this type of layout more often than
not is not sufficient.
For example,
when you group a group of radio buttons
together, you should group these and
separate them from other input fields so
the user can identify them as a group.
So how do we do this?
Well, pretty simple.
We start to look at using the selection
screen statement.
Now, this statement has its own formatting
options
that you can use to define the layout for
your selection screens.
It allows you to define the layout of
parameters and selection criteria and
display comments and underlines on the
selection screen.
Now, the selection screen statement needs
to have additions
with it that specify the specific type of
layout option you are defining.
So let's take a look.
That's our code, and we will go through
some examples to show how it all works.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So the first thing we're going to do is
locate the place in our program
where we start to specify the screen
layouts.
And this is here, where we have the
parameter statements.
Now, the selection screen statement is a
very simple syntax.
It is just SELECTION-SCREEN.
Can't be much easier than that.
But then we have additions.
So the first thing we're going to look at
is blank lines.
So if we want to insert a blank line
between parameters and things like that,
we would use, the SKIP addition.
And what we do is actually specify the
number of lines we want to skip,
and that's represented here, in these
square brackets.
Now, the simplest form is actually to
leave the number of lines out,
and just by using SKIP, that will mean we
just want to skip one line.
Now, before I run the program, I'm gonna
move this selection screen line,
because this would place a blank line at
the top of our report and
it'll be a little hard to see.
So I'm gonna move this and I'm just gonna
place it right here,
which means I'm breaking the chain
statement for parameters.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
There we go.
So I'll save, do a check, and
then execute the report.
So you can see here, we have the employee
number parameter,
then we have a blank line where we skipped
one line.
And then we get the check box and radio
buttons.
So it's pretty simple.
You just place it where you want it to
appear between the individual fields that
you're outputting on the screen.
Now, if we wanted to skip two lines, we
have the number 2.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And as you can see in the test, we now
have two lines.
Now the next addition I want to show you
is how we add a vertical
line to the screen.
So I'm just gonna copy the selection
screen statement and just add another one.
But this time, instead of SKIP 2, I'm
going to add ULINE.
Do a save, and as you can guess, ULINE
means underline.
Check activate and execute, and there you
can see we have added a horizontal line.
Very simple stuff.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
There are some additions we can add to the
underline, and
these are quite easy to understand.
We have a position and a length addition.
So on the example we've got, I will show
you first of all,
we can either slash, which actually gives
us a brand new line, then we can add
the position, let's say position 1, which
is the first character on the screen, and
then we can give it a length, let's say
just eight characters long.
We'll give it a check.
And then activate, and then give it a
test.
And there you can see, just eight
characters long.
If we wanted to move it into the middle of
the screen,
all we would do is change the initial
position.
So let's say we want to move it 40
characters along.
Let's activate and test.
And there you can see.