Next up, we'll take a look at comments.
And comments are just to allow you to
place text on the screen
without actually placing a field.
You know, it's just standard text.
So to place comments on the selection
screen, we would use the following syntax.
[SOUND] We do
the selection
screen again.
And then we use the addition comment.
And as with the underline, we can also say
put our comments on the new line,
and we can give it starting position.
Let's say 40 characters long, and then we
can give it a length.
Let's say our comment will be 15
characters in length.
And then, we just need to add our
comments.
You can either use a text symbol,
which we've already looked at creating in
a previous video, or a field name.
But your field name has to be a maximum
length of eight characters.
And this character field must not be
declared with the data statement.
But it is generated automatically when we
declare the length of our comment.
So let's take a look at it in action.
And then you'll see what I mean.
So first of all, let's use a text symbol
we've already created.
Now I'm gonna choose text, you'll put it
there as text, zero, zero, one.
And save, and I'm just gonna double click
the text element,
just to make sure it does exist, here we
go.
It's called, well, it actually has a value
of surname.
So we should get the word surname up here,
40 characters in.
[NOISE] Let's activate and test.
And there you can see, the surname.
Now to make it a little easier to see on
the screen,
let's move this two lines skip down.
[SOUND] There we go.
You can see it's directly underneath our
underline.
Now let's change this around.
And we'll copy it.
And instead of using text dash zero zero
one,
what we will do is just specify a brand
new variable name.
Don't forget, I've said we don't declare
this variable ourselves with
the data statement.
Just by us using this statement with a
specific length,
the system created it for us.
So here, let's specify comments 1.
Just comm1.
So now you'll probably think, well, what
does it contain?
Well at the moment it contains absolutely
nothing.
So what we have to do is,
when our program has first started, we
have to fill comm1 with some data.
And if we go down and
have a look at the initialization section,
that's where we can put this code.
So we can say com 1equals.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hello SAP.
How original.
[LAUGH] So it'll do a check, and activate,
and there you can see,
com 1 gets initialized as soon as the
program starts
with the value hello SAP, and then we can
output it.