Let's now take a look at how we can format
a single line on the screen.
And when we define individual lines for
our selection screen, we need to define
the start and end of each line.
And in between the start and end, we
include the specific parameters and
select option statements.
So let's have a look at the code.
Let's see how the screen looks at the
moment, and then we can maybe tidy it up.
Okay, so that's the first line,
the employee output.
So let's start the code here.
So to begin with, what we do is type
SELECTION-SCREEN and then BEGIN OF LINE.
And then to define the end of our line,
we do SELECTION-SCREEN,
it would help if, spelt it properly
wouldn't it?
SELECTION-SCREEN, and as you may guess,
just END OF LINE.
So now anything between the begin and end
will all appear on one line.
So let's change the three lines in
between.
Or two lines, [LAUGH] first of all we have
a comment.
And we'll say this is going to start,
position one.
We don't want to, a new line there.
It's going to be 15 characters long, and
it will contain the word surname.
If you remember text001, contains the
value surname.
Here we go.
And that will be followed by another
comment.
And we'll say lets start this at position
20, and that's gonna be for
a length of 10, and that's gonna contain
the value stored in variable comm1.
Which as we saw earlier gets assigned
during the initialization
session of the program, and that will say
hello SAP.
And then lastly, let's start another line.
And let's just define a brand new
parameter.
Lets define a parameter called ABC, and
we'll make
it a character data type with a length of
5.
And if you remember when we
define character data types we don't have
to define it as a type c.
Because that's implied because it's the
default.
So I'll just leave it in the short form.
Just like that.
And that's it.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's see what it looks like.
So there you can see, we have our first
field.
Or our first comment, and our second
comment.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then the parameter field, all
displayed on one line.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So anything between the BEGIN OF LINE and
END OF LINE can all be put on one line.
And all you need to do is make sure you
get your positioning and
length parameters correct.
Now those of you who have your eyes peeled
you may have noticed something.
Let's go back to the screen.
See here we defined the parameter field,
but
see how it didn't automatically get
assigned a comment or
description that refers to the technical
name of the field.
Well, that's because we used specific
comments on the line.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So whenever you use the BEGIN OF LINE and
END OF LINE to define the line on
the screen, the selection text itself that
describes the element is not displayed.
And that's when you would use the comments
to create your own description on the
line.
Now one more addition I want to show you
right here is, and the, and this can only
be used when you are at the BEGIN OF LINE
and END OF LINE, is the position addition.
Now to be fair,
I don't see this being used an awful lot
because the different elements of our
screen allow you to specify the position
of the element within its own syntax.
But we do have the option of
specifying the position of the next
element separately.
So we would do SELECTION-SCREEN.
And then we would include position, and
then we can specify the position using an
integer.
So we could say position 35.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And if we include a parameter straight
after this position,
then our parameter will appear in position
35.
Let's check it out.
Now its hard to see here but
let me step back, I'll tell you what I'll
do,
let's comment out these two.
I do apologize.
Tell you what, instead of commenting them
out [LAUGH] let's move them down.
So there you can see the parameter was
positioned at column 35.
Now that just so happens to be in line
with these.
So let's just change it a little bit.
Let's choose 30.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And now you can see we've moved it a back
a little bit.
Now we do have something else to add on to
the position.
And that is we have some I guess you call
them constants that we can use.
So by default we'll go back to the screen.
We can see we have a default position
here, and we have a default position here.
Well this is referred to as position low,
and this is position high.
Now we can use these default positions
with our position addition.
And all we need to do is add pos.
I'll tell you what I'll do.
I'll choose pos_high first and it's pos
underscore high.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And what you'll see is when we execute the
program
our parameter is lined with the high
position.
So if you are defining your own fields,
and
you want them all to line up just as they
do with the select option,
you can use the pos_high so you don't have
to remember the actual value.
[SOUND] And the pos_low, well that
will bring it in line with the first.
There we go.
[BLANK_AUDIO]