This video is going to be about element
logs.
And when we define selection screens for
our users, it's common practice to group
certain fields together.
And we can use these element blocks
which will draw frames around the groups
of fields we choose.
We also have the option of adding frame
labels.
As we take a look at element blocks,
bear in mind that you can nest element
blocks within other blocks,
allowing you to subdivide individual
sections of your screen.
Let's get straight onto the code and you
can see how element blocks get defined.
So this is the program we've been working
on.
And in the previous videos we had a look
at the begin of line edition.
Well element blocks are very similar.
So what we will do is key in selection
screen.
Then instead of begin of line we just
write begin of block.
And what we do, we then add a name.
So we give our block a name.
We'll call this my block one.
As you can see, the syntax is very basic
and it looks very similar to the begin of
line with just that one addition of
defining a block name.
Now you have the option of choosing
whether you want to apply a frame around
a block of fields in your selection
screen.
We do that by using the width frame
edition.
So let's add that in.
So all we do is type width frame.
Simple.
Pretty it up.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And now another addition is we can add a
frame label.
And we call these labels titles.
So we add a title to the frame.
And as with comments we can use text
symbols or
field names with a maximum length of eight
characters.
Type in the addition title, and then we
add add the text elements.
Now because we defined the start of a
block, with the begin block addition.
We also have to remember to include an
ender block.
So, let's copy this line.
And we'll go down and let's put the ender
block here.
Let's group these together and there we
have a block.
And instead of beginner block, all we do
is type, you'll never guess, end of block.
Again, keep the block name to define which
block you're ending.
And then a full stop.
Let's check our code and see what it looks
like.
And there you go, you can see we defined a
frame.
We gave it a title, and
it's picking up the text element, which
has the text surname.
And now your screen starts to look, well,
I won't say a whole lot better [LAUGH] but
it starts to look a bit better.
Element blocks help give your field some
context, and
to help group your fields together.
And you'll see them used all over the
place in SAP.
So when you're designing your screens keep
element blocks in mind.
Make sure you make use of them,
because it looks a lot better from the
user's perspective.
So we have looked at many different
elements of designing screens
for our programs.
We've discussed events parameters, select
options How we can use text elements,
to saving variance, and how the user can
actually change the screen layout as well.
And then finally how we, let's say, pretty
up our screens.
Group fields together.
Make it look a lot more presentable to the
user.
And that covers our selection screen
statement.