[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this section of the course,
we're going to take a look at program flow
control and logical expressions.
This really is the meat of ABAP program.
This is where it all happens.
How you structure your program using
logical expressions.
Determine the complete flow of your
program and
in what sequence actions are taken.
So first of all, let's have a look at
control structures.
Now, when we create a program,
we break a program up into some multiple
tasks and subtasks.
We control how and when these sections of
our program are executed
using logical expressions and
conditional loops, often referred to as
control structures.
So, let's get straight down to the ABAP
code, and
have a look at how we define these control
structures.
To make it easy to understand what I'm
talking about.
[BLANK_AUDIO]