First of all,
let's create a brand new program,
where we can test out some
of the logic we will build.
So I'm going to take a copy
of the Z_OPENSQL_1 program
that we used in the previous module.
With the program name in the text box,
just click the Copy button, and
we'll give our program a brand new name.
Let's call this Logic_1.
Z_LOGIC_1.
And we'll just choose Copy > Local object,
and our program has been duplicated.
So let's go into Change mode, and
we'll tidy the program up a little bit.
And what we will do,
is just keep this first section.
And I'll make some space.
So when we talk about control structures,
we are talking about lots of code
that allow us to make a decision,
and based on that decision, we can
have a number of different outcomes.
Let's take a look at the if statement
to explain the basic logic of
control structures.
Now, the if statement is probably
the most common control structure
that is found in just about every
program and language there is.
The syntax of the if statement,
does vary from language to language, but
each use is pretty much universal.
So if we have a look at the piece of
code that we created in the last module.
We have this if statement.
If a logical expression do something.
And then we have an addition saying else,
do something else.
And then the end of the if statement.
So if we were to just talk about
it in pseudo-code we just say,
if a logical expression.
[SOUND] We will then do something.
And then we will end our if statement.
So you can see if starts the expression,
and
the end if is the end of the expression.
So this allows us to see the control
expression has a start with the if
statement here, and
it terminates with our end if statement.
Both of our statements belong together.
And every control structure we create
will always have a start and an end.
Now when we break our program into smaller
tasks we will break these tasks up.
That will allow us to branch off, in
the middle and do some other smaller task.
Which in turn could have
its own if statements,
its own control structures
to do even smaller tasks.
When we have defined our control
structure, what we put between the start
and the end, determines what tasks
are going to be performed as subtasks.
We branch off and do something else or
we repeat a whole
bunch of tasks in-between our control
structure in what we call loops.
Things are gonna get a lot
more interesting from now on.
We will be using control structures
like the if statement to determine
the flow of our program,
to execute different sub tasks or
branches of our programs,
and to perform loops.
So to begin with, I'm going to
comment out all these code for
now, and I'm gonna write some code here,
and see if you can determine
what's going to happen.
And to do this let's make
use of the pattern tool.
So I'm gonna click the Pattern button,
Ctrl+F6,
which brings up the insert
statement dialogue box.
Now what I'm gonna do is go down to the
bottom where it says other pattern, and
just put it in IF.
Now what this has done.
It's brought back the structure of an if
statement that we can follow as a guide so
that, for those that are new to ABAP, you
will get the syntax right and you won't
have to worry too much about the actual
placement of the fore stops and so on.
So we have our if statement.
Now I'm going to do this.
I'm going to create a data statement
that's gonna hold an employee surname.
So I'm just going to create a field call
surname [SOUND] a type character.
I'll give it a length of 15.
And pretty it up.
[SOUND] We're gonna set
our surname to a value.
[SOUND] And
then we'll use the if statement.
So there you can see,
I've written some logic.
Now can you work out what that's gonna do?
It's pretty easy.
Let's execute the program,
and see what it says?
Opps.
Silly me.
Using the wrong quotes.
And again.
I would like to apologize.
There you go, you've won a car.
So yeah, this is a simple if statement,
just saying if the surname is equal to
Smith, and of course it is, because
we've set the surname to Smith already,
it performs a branch of our program.
So let's extend this program to
include the else if statements,
and it's quite simple.
[SOUND] Let's say now, if SMITH.
Equals BROWN.
This time you've won a boat.
Now as you can imagine,
our surname equals SMITH, so
you're gonna win a car every time.
But let's change it to, to BROWN.
[SOUND] And now you can see
the outcome is do you want a boat?
The first if statement was not true,
therefore this branch of
the program was not executed.
So we went down to the next branch in
the statement which is the else if.
Else if surname is BROWN, which it is,
then it will write this
branch of the if statements.
And we can keep on with the else if.
We can, you know,
repeat it any number of time.
The only problem is I
may run out of prizes.
So this one is a PLANE.
How fortunate for being a Mr. Jones.
Oh, didn't notice,
I had the extra full stop right there.
And lastly,
let's change this one to ANDREWS.
And what does Mr. Andrews win?
He's very fortunate.
He wins a house.
So as you can see, we can keep
going on with this structure, and
depending on what is true?
Different branches of this
logic block will be executed.
JONES, you've won a plane.
ANDREWS, you've won a house.
And the last part.
Is the else statement.
And the else comes in when it's
the last piece of your if block.
So we could say, if you're name isn't
any of these, what are you gonna win?
Unlucky, you go home empty handed.
So by introducing these different
else if statements, and
the else statements, there is always
going to be an outcome that is
performed depending on
the value of surname.
We have taken care of
every single possibility.
If it's Smith, we're gonna do this.
If it's Brown, we're gonna win a boat.
If it's Jones, a plane.
Andrews, a house.
Anything else,
we're gonna do this block of code.
So the if statement is very powerful,
and it is the key logic statement
used in just about every program going,
to determine the flow of your program.