[BLANK_AUDIO]
We have a whole set of ABAP operators that
we can use with our logics things.
So, as we have seen with the if statement
we've been using the equals.
We also can use the not equal to, which is
the less than and
greater than sign together.
The less than, the greater than, less than
and equal to and the greater than and
equal to now, ABAP, because of its roots,
also has some other way to writing these.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And these are the EQ for equals and E for
not equals.
And you can work the rest out.
Less than, greater than, less than or
equal to and greater than or equal to.
More and more you, you tend not to see
these being used too much and
I suggest you don't use them because
everyone's now familiar with the standard
way of writing these operators.
And like I mentioned in the previous video
we're not just limited to these,
we can link logical expressions together
using the or
operator the and operator and the not
operator.
We will come onto these in the examples
that follow.
So we can link our logical expressions
together, just like this.
Let's copy the if statement for surname.
And instead of a full stop here,
we can then use one of the linking
operators, in our case, AND
we'll say forename equals John.
So there you can see, we've used the AND
operator to link
two logical expressions together in this
one IF statement.
[SOUND]
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] So the rest of the code to make up
the statement would be like this.
Very simple one.
The right statement represents our
statement locker code that we would want
to execute, and then we close the if
statement with the end if command.
So that's using and.
We can also say if Smith, sorry, if
surname equals Smith or
full name equals John, execute the code.
[BLANK_AUDIO]