Now, let's have a look at nested ifs.
Now as you can see, with our else if, we
are nesting our logic just one level deep.
We're saying, if this do this.
Else this, do this.
Now with a nested if, we can go down to a
more detailed level.
Let's have a look at an example.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, first of all, we have if surname
equals Smith,
we're going to write something out.
Well, at this point, with a nested if, we
can say.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
If forename equals John.
Else, we can say,
oh, yeah, so close.
[SOUND] And then we end this if block with
this
line of code [SOUND] Let's pretty it up.
And go through it.
So we have our first [UNKNOWN] statement
if Surname equals Smith.
Then, instead of writing out, you've won a
car.
[SOUND] We're nesting another if
statement.
Saying if forename equals John.
Now for completing this, just know just
don't create it forenames.
So, let's stick that in there.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] Okay.
So, if your forename equals John, you've
won a car.
Else, oh, you were so close so we are
checking two logical expressions.
To win a car, you've got to have a name of
Smith and
you've got to have a forename of John.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then for each if statement, we close
it with a corresponding end if.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now you are not limited just to nesting,
you know, down to two levels.
You can go on to your heart's content.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
You could do a third level [SOUND] if we
print Europe.
It should indent it for us.
So you could have something else.
If the surname is Smith and the forename
is John.
And then, and, you know, another field
here.
Location UK.
I know we haven't defined it as a field,
but you get the idea.
We can keep embedding logic like this
until it meets all the criteria for
your program.
And you don't always have to nest if
statements one after another,
just like in this case.
We could have
[BLANK_AUDIO]
A bunch of statements here, a bunch of
statements here,
some more statements, some more statements
at this point.
So going back to when we started this
exercise,
we're looking at we define our controls
structure.
We then execute some code, then we close
our control structure.
So the code that we execute can be
anything at all.
Writing, reading from database tables,
more logical statements such as the
embedative.
You can introduce loops, call function
modules anything you can think of.
And that's really it for the if statement.
That's the structure.
You have the if, you have the else if, you
have the else and
then the end if to close off the block.
And you can nest if statements and other
logic statements as deep as you wish.
So, the if statement analyzes a logical
expression, and
like any other programming language, we
are not just limited did to unequal.
We can use any logical expression.
We can use the equal, not equal, less
than, greater than, the or,
the and, the nots and so on.
So let's have a look at some of those, and
see how they are written in our-