I want you to keep in mind that when you
create logical expressions,
and especially linking logical expressions
together
it's always best to make sure your code is
as readable as possible.
And the reason why I say this is because
if you you know,
start producing code just like this.
Well, even though it will work, you know,
we're linking lots of expressions
together.
Ahh, boy, it's so difficult to read.
So try and limit the number of logical
expressions you do link together,
you know, structure your code a little bit
differently,
where you might use multiple single
logical expressions.
One after another or if you don't want to
do that,
at least structure your code so it is
easier on the eye.
[SOUND] For example, we can line things up
like this
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And so on.
I won't keep going, but you get the idea.
It's a lot easier to read something like
that than the code we had before.
Now this brings us on to the next
statement I want us to go through and
that is, the case statement.
The case statement does a similar job to
the IF statement, but
it has the flexibility to structure our
code so it's a lot more readable, but
at the same time is limited to one logical
expression.
Let's take a look at the case statement so
it's easier to understand.
So we will start a new block of code let's
have a separator here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we will begin the case statement with
the word case, and
we will use the surname and forename that
we have used previously.
So I will write the code first, have a
look at the structure of the statement,
and then we'll compare it to see how it
differs from the IF statement.
So we have case surname full stop
then we can include the word when and this
is where we put our Values.
Let's copy this write statement to save
me typing.
I'm sure I've got a Jones a little further
up.
I certainly do.
Mr. Jones, Windsor Plain.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] I'll introduce a new MR,
MR Green and Mr.
Green well he wins the boats.
And last but not least we have our closing
when.
And we say when others.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now lastly, we end the case statement with
endcase.
So let's pretty it up.
Get the indenting correct.
So now let's go through the case statement
again.
So the first thing we do, is we use the
word case, and we say case field name so
in our case, it's case surname, and we are
checking the contents of surname.
And we are going to perform an action
depending on its value.
So we are saying when the surname equals
Smith, you've won a car.
When it's Jones, you've won a plane.
When it's Green, you've won a boat.
And anything else with when others, you
don't win anything.
Unlucky.
And then we close the case statement.
Now personally I think the case statement
is much easier to read
than lots of nested and linked IF
statements.
And when we look at the differences with
the case statement compared to the IF
statement well just as I mentioned the
case statement
can only check one field whereas the IF
statement,
by using linked expressions, we can check
multiple fields.
Just like here, we're checking the surname
and forename field.
So this is a limitation with a case
statement,
you just checked one field, but I still
like it.
[LAUGH] There's not much more to explain
about the case statement.
But before we move on I will just mention
just like with the IF statement,
case statements can be nested.
So with our example Pull when we have when
Smith we could
write out some text to the screen and then
we could introduce another case statement.
And we can choose to have a case statement
on another field, include the when.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] Just like so.
Oops.
I do apologize.
That's better.
So there you can see a nasty case
statement within the original case
statement.