In this video we are going to discuss
iteration statements,
otherwise known as looping statements.
We use iteration statements to execute a
block of ABAP code multiple times.
So to start off with, I'm going to
generate a new program,
by copying the one we used in the previous
exercise.
And then I'll strip it down.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So we can start fresh.
There are various ways to loop through
blocks of code in your app-app program.
And we can separate these types of loops
into those that have conditions attached
to them and those that do not.
Now you've already been using a loop in
the form of the select statement.
And the select statement allows us to
iterate through a record set.
So let's revisit the select statement, and
we've been using it in the form of select
star, which means select every field from
the table, I mean in our case it would be
zed employees.
We would then have some ABAP that we would
loop through; in this case,
let's just do a simple write statement.
By doing this zed employees,
it would output the entire record onto the
screen.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then all we need to say is end select.
So as you can see, this is a very simple
loop,
select every field from the table, write
the record to the screen.
It's corrected.
And then we get to the end select which
means we are finished writing our blocker
code, go back to the start until there are
no more records left in the records set.
So let's do a syntax
check, oops we do have an error.
Oh, my apologies.
I missed the table statement at the top.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Pretty it up.
There we go.
So let's give this program a quick run and
you can see it in action.
As you can see, it's looped through the
entire table and
output the contents to the screen.
A very simple loop.
Now I did mention how our iteration
statements come in two forms,
those with conditions and those without.
Well this is a select statement, a loop
without a condition on it.
But we can add the condition very simply.
In this case, let's extend the first line
of the select statement
to say where surname equals Smith.
So now when the select statement executes,
it will only select records where
the surname is Smith and output them to
the screen.
Let's do a quick check, make sure the code
is correct.
Activate it and then give it a run.
And nothing was output.
Let's have a look at our table.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Oh, well, look at that.
We got rid of all our Smith records.
Let's use another surname.
Let's choose, we have Jones, our first
one, or Mills in the middle.
Let's choose Mills instead.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Everything is good.
And there we go, it's output the one
record where the surname is
equal to Mills.
So you can see it's quite easy to add
logic into your select statement.
To limit the number of records you're
going to iterate through.