Let's now take a look, at the Do loop.
A Do loop is very simple.
We start with defining the Do loop.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We then execute a statement block, and
then we end the Do loop.
So, in our case, we would change our
statement block, to our write statement.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Instead of z employees,
we would just output the word, hello.
Let's do the Pretty Printer.
Oops.
Look at that, making silly mistakes.
Here we go.
And, as you can see, it's very simple.
But one thing you might notice,
is that there's nothing telling this loop
statement, when to stop.
Let's see what happens when we execute
this code.
[SOUND] As long as I put the proper
full stop in place.
[SOUND] So, now we're executing the
program,
but see how we're stuck?
This is because, this Do loop, is
processing thousands and
thousands of times per second, and
outputting the word hello to the screen.
So, we're stuck in a loop.
And that's not good for anyone.
[SOUND] So, we need to come back out, and
amend our code.
[SOUND] So, what do you think we need to
do here?
Well, we need to add some mechanism to
this Do loop, to tell it when to
stop processing the block of code,
in-between the Do and End Do statements.
And that's where we introduce the times
addition.
And the times addition will go straight
after your do.
So, we would say 15 times, for example.
[SOUND] Now when we test it,
you can see the word, hello,
is written out 15 times.
Tell you what, let's stick it on a new
line, so it's easier to see.
[SOUND] There we go.
So, the Do statement is useful for
repeating a number of tasks,
a specific number of times, but you must
remember to always include,
a number and the times addition,
otherwise,
you could end up in an endless loop, just
as we did in the first example.
So, now, I want to rewrite this Do
statement.
Let's, instead of writing out let's have
some processing.
Let's have a equals 0.
Oops.
Wrong line.
Do apologize.
Let's define.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
Okay, so, we define a, as an integer.
We set its value to zero.
And then what we will do inside the loop,
is a calculation.
A equals a plus 1, so, this is just going
to be a very simple counter.
What I want this to demonstrate, is the Do
loop actually uses an internal counter,
to control how many times the loop is
executed.
You can check the SY index system
variable,
to see how many times your loop has been
processed.
So, let's do that.
First of all, let's make sure we write out
our own counter, and
then we can compare it, against the system
counter.
[SOUND] Everything looks good.
I'll stick a break point on the Do, and
then let's execute.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay, so now we're into the code.
Let's step through it.
I'm going to use the F5, single step.
I'm going to double-click on a, so we can
monitor that variable value.
And what you need to have a look at as
well, when we execute the, the first one.
[SOUND] Is, SY index, and as you can see,
that has a value of one as well.
This is a system variable.
You don't have to declare it, you just
need to be aware of it,
to execute the loop again.
As you can see, as soon as we step into
the loop, the SY index,
increases by one, to indicate we are in
the second iteration of this loop.
Then our own counter gets executed, and
we'd write it out to the screen.
[SOUND] And so on.
And it will keep executing until it gets
to 15.
[SOUND] Now I'll just zoom along.
And there's our output.
And once again, I should have stuck it on
it's own line.
[SOUND] And there we go,
all 15.