As with many of the statements, do loops
can be nested, and if you do nest them,
each do loop will have its own SY index
created and monitored by the system, but
do be aware that when you start nesting do
loops, and other types of loops,
you need to consider how much work you're
going to make the system do.
So let's get straight in and have a look
at an example of how we nest
another do loop inside this one.
So first of all, well I'll leave that
break point on,
and then let's call this outer loop so
we can monitor it properly.
[NOISE] and then lets do our do loop
statements inside.
So we'll do lets say ten times.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we will do a similar type of
statement.
We will write out the value of B on its
own line.
I have remembered it this time.
We will call this inter loop.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's just get it all in line.
And don't forget, we need to declare our
variable.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now because we have a do loop inside our
original do loop,
let's initialize our variable B at this
point.
Because if we did it up here,
it's value would not be reset every time
we got to the inner do loop.
So by doing it here, we can do this second
do loop ten times.
And then when the first do loop comes
round to it's second iteration,
it gets reset to zero and then it will
count to ten again in the second loop.
And finally, let's just do one more little
thing.
Just to count the total number of loops
that we are processing.
We'll have a variable called c.
Also a type i.
[SOUND]
and at the very end [SOUND]
let's do this,
we'll write out
the value of C.
That so it adds up correctly, what we need
to do,
at the end of each second do loop, is to
let c equal the value of b.
So, once it does ten times the value of b
will be transferred to C.
Watch what we need to do.
C plus B.
So it gets added up every time,
and then at the very end,
we can C plus K.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So this should be a good counter for us.
To count up how many times the system
loops through both loops.
So, the first loop is 15 times and then in
each loop it loops ten more times.
So we should If my math's correct, have
around about 150 loops.
That's quite a lot of code being executed.
Now, obviously we're using an SAP system
and
it's gonna process this instantaneously.
But, you can imagine if you were
processing through, let's say, 10,000
records at this level, and then you are at
50,000 records at the second level.
And 10,000 times 50,000,
I can't do the math but it would equal a
lot of Iterations.
And it could take quite a long time, so
just be wary of nested loops.
Anyway, let's get on and test our code.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Our break point is set here at line 22, so
let's just execute it and we'll Bring up
the values of a.
You double click.
Tell you what.
Change that to b, and we'll put c there.
And we will also bring up sy-index at this
point.
And we can see that as a value of 0.
And while we're processing through this
code, keep an eye on sy-index and
notice how the value changes as we go from
the outer loop to the inner loop.
So let's get straight on and step through
the code.
So, our first loop is gonna be done 15
times.
As we step into it, s y index equals one.
We will increment the value of a.
Write out our first statements.
And we can see that b gets initialized.
And now we're gonna step into the second
loop.
SY index is one again.
But because it's the first time we're
going into this second loop.
We don't actually see any change in the
value, but SY index is pointing
at the second loop now, which it's
monitoring this SY index value.
As we step through you'll see it change.
So, B is incremented by one, we write out
the statement,
and now we're into the second.
Iteration of the second loop.
And we can see SY index is equal to.
And that's what we step through.
It should do it ten times.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So now we're in our tenth iteration of
this inner loop.
Goes back up, registers it's been done ten
times,
jumps straight down to the undo statement,
and then processes the calculation of C.
And then continues on,
in this first iteration of the outer loop.
And we can see the SY.
Wrong one.
Sorry.
And we can see the SY index has been
changed back to one.
You'll carry on.
And now we're in the second loop of our
how to do statement.
And as we jump into our In a loop,
sy-index should be reset to represent the
value of the inner loop,
and so it is.
[NOISE] So to save my fingers all this key
pressing.
I am just going to place a break point on
this line of code,
then I can press the F8 key, which is the
same as this one to zoom through.
So we can see b, which is our inner loop,
has been processed ten times again
and see, it gets incremented to 20 and so
on.
I'll just press F8, and keep pressing it,
and
we can see our outer loop is going to be
processed 15 times.
There we go.
And do, to the bottom.
And then C gets incremented with the value
of A.
And we write out the final value of C.
So we can see our outer loop and
the inner loop values outer loop again,
inner loop, and so on.
As we scroll down to the bottom we finally
get the total number of
loops that have been performed in our
code.
It might've been a little bit better if I
was just to, maybe
increase the number of positions from the
left-hand margin of the inner loop print.
I'll double click the breakpoint to
get rid of it, and then zoom through the
code.
There we go.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
That's easy.
It's a read.
There we go.
So, that's nesting do loops.