We're now going to take a look at another
looping statement,
and this one is the while loop.
Now, this differs from the do loop, and
that the while loop checks for a condition
that we have defined within the while loop
before it executes any code.
All the statements between the while and
end while statements will be repeated as
long as the condition is met.
As soon as the condition is untrue, the
loop will terminate.
Just as we did with the do loop, we also
monitored the sy-index
field to see how many times the loop is
executed.
So, let's get straight in and have a look
at the code.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's introduce a few blank lines, then
what I'm going to do,
[BLANK_AUDIO]
we just comment this out because we don't
want all these few loop output
on to the screen, and then we'll take a
look at the syntax for the while.
[SOUND] So, it's quite straightforward.
We have a while, then we have a statement
which is our condition statement.
So, let's do that, condition statement.
[SOUND] Then, we have a block of code that
we would execute.
[SOUND] And then, we end our end
while loop, with end while.
[SOUND] Pretty straightforward.
Looks quite similar to the do statement.
So, let's turn this into a proper code.
So, we have our while statement and
we would change this conditional statement
to something proper.
So, we can say while a is not equal to 15.
[SOUND] Let's copy this.
[SOUND] Well, it's not equal to 15.
We can output, [SOUND] the value of a.
Now, at the moment, a will always be less
than 15 because we are initializing a a
little higher up in the code.
So, what we need to do, after we write out
the value of a to ensure we don't
end up in an endless loop, we need to
increment the value of a.
So, we'll just do the simple a equals a
plus one.
Tidy our code up.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] Execute it.
And, we can step through the code.
So, we will monitor the value of a, and
also [SOUND] sy-index.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And as we step through the while loop, it
will check the condition.
And as we can see, the value of a is zero.
So, we write out the statement to the
screen,
then a gets incremented, and the loop
continues.
And notice our sy-index is incrementing
just as it did when we
took a look at the do statement.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, I just keep my finger on the button
here to step through,
until we get close to 15, which we're
right at right now, so do it end while.
Checks the condition.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Skips the statement block and goes to the
end of the loop.
And then, outputs everything to the
screen.
Now, because a started with a value of
zero, that was the first cycle.
So, the maximum value a reach when it was
output on the screen was 14.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[SOUND] So, what we could've done, just to
get 15,
is just what these statements around, just
hide that.
So, a gets incremented first.
[SOUND] I'll press F8,
and there we go.
So, there we have the 15.
It looks a little bit easier on the eye.
So that's it, a very simple while loop.