Just as we did with Do loops, we can also
nest While loops.
The process is exactly the same.
So, we're not gonna spend too long on
this, but
I will do the code so it gives you an
example.
And then we will just zoom straight
through the code.
So, I generate some space.
And we'll follow the example we did in the
Do
loop, so we will use the a, the b, and the
c variables.
So, the first thing we need to do.
Is initialize our b variable.
And then we'll create another While loop.
Our b [INAUDIBLE] equal to ten.
We can write our total statement, and
obviously,
we need to use the copy and paste.
[SOUND] And then it's important at this
point,
to make sure we increment b, so,
just as we did with a, we'll increment b
right here.
So, b equals b plus 1.
If we didn't do that, we'd end up with a
continuous loop,
it would never end, and we would be stuck.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, we have that.
We'll bring that line back up.
Then we'll increment c.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, c equals c plus b, once that inner
loop ends.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we can have our last endwhile, and
then write out our final line.
[SOUND]
There we go.
So, I'll just have a final check, we're
incrementing a.
Resetting b, incrementing b.
That will do it, until it reaches the
tenth iteration.
We write out b, increment c.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Oh.
And there's one more.
I need to increment c here, with a value
of a.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
There we go.
[SOUND] Have a code check, then activate
it.
And then we'll run straight through.
I don't think I've got a breakpoint set.
Nope.
There we go,
so we, we have the same type of result, as
we did with the Nested Do loop.
We can see our outer loop.
And the cycle of ten inner loop
statements, outer,
and then inner, and so o,n until we get to
the bottom,
where we can see a total of 165
iterations.
Let's move on.
[BLANK_AUDIO]