Up to now, we have gone through our loop
statements and let
the condition inside the loop statement,
determine when the loop will finish.
ABAP contains Terminate Statements that
allow you to terminate a loop prematurely.
And there are two categories of
termination statements,
those that apply to the loop, and those
that apply to
the entire processing processing block in
which the loop occurs.
So, first of all, let's have a look at how
we terminate the processing of a loop.
And the first statement we're gonna
discuss, is the Continue Statement.
Now, this allows us to terminate a loop
pass unconditionally.
And you'll see, when we take a look at the
syntax,
that there are no conditions added to the
statement itself.
When I first started ABAP,
I thought the continue statement seemed a
little bit odd.
Why would you want to use the word
continue, to terminate a loop?
It just seemed a bit backwards to me, but
maybe that's just me.
The continue statement actually means,
do not process any more statements in this
loop.
Just immediately end the processing, of
all the statements in the loop,
right here I jump to the start of the loop
again.
So, if we include the continue statement,
inside our loop the remaining statements
will not be executed.
As soon as the Continue Statement is hit,
processing jumps right to the top of the
loop again and starts another loop run,
as long as the conditions set by the start
of your loop statement are still met.
So, let's have a look at the structure of
the Continue Statement, and
go through a quick example, so you can see
exactly what I'm talking about.
I will use the DO loop, for this example.
So let's get rid of this WHILE, and
bring back our DO loops.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And we don't need an inner DO loop for
this example.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Let's get rid of B.
Okay, and what we're gonna do is introduce
an IF statement.
So let's say IF sy-index, which should be
the same as
the variable a that we are setting as a,
as a separate counter ourselves.
So we're saying if sy-index equals 2.
And we will say, continue.
And that's all there is to it.
Just that one word, continue.
Then we will end our if statements.
So, what this is gonna do is start this
loop?
It thinks it's going to execute it 15
times,
then as soon as we're in this second loop
we will hit the Continue Statement.
And processing should jump straight back
to the top of the loop.
Which means we are not gonna write out,
this outer loop cycles text with a value
of a on the second loop pass.
So, it should run through.
And we'll put the debugger on.
Here we go.
So we'll step through.
Let's have a look at the value of a, and
the value of xy-index.
So, if sy index is 2, which it's not, it's
going to output the text to the screen.
And we'll have a quick look.
There you Go, there's the output.
So, we'll step through again to the second
time.
Now sy index has been set to 2, so the if
statement should be true this time.
So we get to the Continue Statement, and
you can see execution jumps straight to
the top of the loop again.
And I'll continue processing and we're on
the third iteration.
So as soon as we hit the Continue
Statement,
the rest of the code was not executed.
Processing jumps straight out the loop,
back to the top.
So now, I will just zoom along to the end.
There's our output and we can see we are
of one, 3, so we have that missing 2.