The next statement we'll have a look at to
terminate
the processing of a block is a check
statement.
The check statement allows us to terminate
loop pass,
just like the continue statement does.
But It allows us to check certain
conditions.
We can use some sort of logic.
So when we define our check statements and
define the logic, if the condition
is not true, any remaining statements in
our current statement block.
After the check statements will be ignored
and
the next loop pass will start, just as it
did with the continue statements.
The check statement is a little bit like a
combination of the if statements and
continue statement we used in the last
exercise.
Let's have a look at the code and see it
in action.
So here we have the due statement from our
previous exercise.
So let's edit this.
And we will keep the due 15 times or just
take the break point off for now.
Looks way better, we will increment the
variable A.
And then we will say, instead of the F,
check SY index not equal to two.
And then we will get rid of these two.
So this will check to see if the sy-index
system variable
does not equal the value of two.
And if that statement is true, it will
carry on processing the code.
If the statement is untrue, the right
statement will not be executed,
because processing will jump straight to
the top of the DO statements again.
Let's debug the code and see how it works.
[SOUND] We will have
a look at XY index and A.
And then I'll press F5 to step through.
So S-Y index has a value of one at the
moment.
So that's fine, we know that one is not
the same as two.
So it will write out our statement to the
screen.
Our next run-through Now this time, SY
index is equal to two.
So our statement is not correct.
So we should terminate the processing of
this loop, and
go straight back to the top, let's have a
look.
I'll press F5, there we go, it jumps
straight to the top of the loop.
Now it's equal to three, so it should
execute the right statements, and it does,
and so on.
So it should execute it 15 times I'll
press F8 to zoom and there we go.
Process 15 times but missing the second
write statement.
So it's very similar to using the if and
continue statements in the last exercise
but we can do it with just one line of
code.
And when you are looking at programs that
have been created by other people, and
maybe creating programs yourself further
down the line, don't be surprised
to see the check statement outside of
loops like the do loop or the while loop.
Because the check statements only
terminate an individual loop run,
called loop pass, but it can also be used
to check
other processing blocks, like subroutines
or events.
And a check statement is executed,
it all depends at what level in your
program it is being executed.
If our check statement was outside of this
loop,
then it would actually terminate our
program.
If it was inside another processing block,
maybe the app screen selection processing
log.
Or they would terminate that block of
code.
So you can use the check statement
whenever you like.
Just be aware of where you're using it
because that will have a big impact
on the processing of your code.
Let's have a quick example here.
Let's take the check statement outside
this loop, and
just see it in practice on how it will
terminate our program.
Cred a few blank lines.
I'm gonna stick the asterisk there so
we've always got a few blank lines for us.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And, all I'm gonna do is write a brand new
check statement here.
So check More say, we'll change the value
of A.
So we're gonna check the value of A is
equal to 1.
Now of course, we can see here, we're
setting the value of A to 0.
So this is never gonna be true.
Which means, it's not gonna process the
rest of our code.
[SOUND] let's activate it.
We'll stick a breakpoint, well, let's get
rid of this one first.
Stick a breakpoint here.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So we'll set the value of A to zero.
And now we'll do the check statement.
[SOUND] and the program ends.
So as soon as I hit the check statement
and the value was not true,
the check statement caused processing of
our code to step out of the current block,
which in this case was the program itself.
[BLANK_AUDIO]