We can also use the exit
statement to terminate loops.
The exit statement allows us to
terminate a loop immediately
without any condition being checked.
And you may think, well isn't this
the same as the continue statement?
Well it sounds as though it's the same,
but there is a difference.
Where the continue statement stops
processing the current loop and
jumps back the top of
the loop to carry on,
the exit statement terminates
the whole loop itself.
So once the processor meets the exit
statement, the whole loop will finish and
the program will continue to process
a statement immediately following
the closing statement of your loop,
such as the end do or the end while.
Now keep in mind, because we can exit
loops using this exit statement,
it will only exit the current loop.
So if we have nested loops, and
we hit our exit statement within, say,
the second level of the nested loop
only that level loop will terminate, and
we'll go back to the higher level loop.
Now the exit statement can also be used
outside of loops, just like the check
statement, but you've got to be aware that
if you use the exit statement outside
of a loop it will terminate whatever type
of code structure you are currently in.
So for example, if you used the exit
statement within a subroutine it will
terminate the subroutine and processing
will return back to the calling program.
If you use the exit statement in your
calling program and it's not in a loop or
a different event structure then it will
actually terminate your whole program.
So just be aware of where you use it,
what context.
So let's have a look at the code, and
see how we can use the exit statement in
the examples being looking at so far.
So with our example do loop, let's change
this code so instead of having this check
statement, let's change this back to
an if statement like we've had it before.
And let's do this, if the SY index
is equal to three, let's exit.
And what I'm going to do here is just
write another couple of write statements,
just to act as fillers.
So that once our loop exits, we still have
some code that will execute afterwards.
So by looking at the code, it should
be pretty straightforward how it works.
We step inside our loop.
When we meet the third
iteration of the loop
this if command will return true and
therefore execute our exit statement.
Now note there's nothing else you
need to add to the exit statement.
That's all there is to it so
it's pretty simple.
Once the exit statement is met,
then processing will drop
straight down to the loop and
jump to the two write statements
we have at the end of the program.
So let's do a syntax check, activate it.
Oh, just one thing,
we have a rogue check statement just here.
Let's take that guy out.
I'm sick of seeing this little fellow.
And, you know while we're at it,
let's comment out this.
Okay, let's activate again.
That looks better.
Let's get rid of this break point and
we'll set it up here on
the initialization of A.
And now we can test the program.
So I would just press F5 to step through.
And we are in the first iteration.
And the second, and
now SY index equals three.
So we should execute the exit statements.
Which we do,
it doesn't continue doing the loop.
Jumps to the top and
then straight back out to the end.
And continues with our
write filler statements.
So we'll step out.
And then let's do one more change.
Just to show this in action.
If we have it outside of the loop.
We should never get to
execute any of this code.
As soon as the exit statement
is hits within our program,
our program should terminate.
Let's test it.
As our break point.
Five and five again.
And there we go.
The program exited without writing
anything out to the screen.